Introduction

I do solemnly swear (or affirm) that I will faithfully execute the Office of President of the United States, and will to the best of my ability, preserve, protect and defend the Constitution of the United States.

Article II, Section I of the United States Constitution states that before entering upon the president's duties, the president-elect must take an oath. It does not require that the president then deliver an inaugural address to the nation. But nations are built on tradition as much as on laws. Traditions evolve, certainly—the first inaugural address was delivered in the Senate chamber, not in front of a crowd—but their core remains, sustained and strengthened by each abiding generation.

The inaugural address—often the first speech that a president delivers in their new role—contains the hopes, dreams, and soul of the United States of America. No matter the length, the president lets their fellow Americans know what the country is facing and how they intend to confront those challenges. War or peace, recession or boom—whatever challenge the nation faces, the transfer of power has occurred. It is not always a statement of policy, but of resolve—the resolve to leave the nation in a better state, well-positioned to capture the winds of change and to meet the trials head-on.

Though written to suit its time, it may be a timeless speech. Abraham Lincoln's storied second inaugural address, FDR's first, and JFK's are often quoted to this day. But we cannot forget that even they were written for the times. And when we read the inaugural address out of context, we are in danger of losing that thread. Beyond the platitudes, what would the incoming president be dealing with? If on their second term, what were they already dealing with? How would their term measure up to their ideal? Hindsight is 20/20, but the orator does not have that benefit when they speak to a nation's future, and all that entails. Their decisions could have drastic implications down the road—for better or worse.

The essays that follow are not meant to be a panegyric or invective of the president in question; nor are they meant to be an in-depth look at a respective presidency—after all, entire books are written about single events that occur during a presidency. Rather, they are meant to provide context for the inaugural address. What might've been going through the president's mind when they wrote the address? Who, or what, might've influenced their writing? And as a president does not operate in a vacuum, the decisions made by a predecessor could come to a head during their term. The throughline of the executive office ties them all together, and each is the inheritor of a legacy that stretches back to 1789.

A couple of notes on the addresses that follow. There have been 58 inaugural addresses across 45 presidents. A further 3 are not inaugural addresses proper, but a speech the president delivered upon assuming the presidency. Herein, they are referred to as that presidents "Address Upon Assuming the Office of President of the United States." 2 presidents—Millard Fillmore, who was inaugurated after the death of Zachary Taylor; and Andrew Johnson, inaugurated after the assassination of Abraham Lincoln—have neither an inaugural address nor something that can be considered an address upon becoming president. Two options remained: skip them entirely or use the closest thing. The latter, I believe, is the correct option. And so I use the text in closest proximity—the message they delivered upon becoming president. I thought it would be more egregious to skip a president than to justify the text that most closely resembles the inaugural address, though it will remain an imperfect choice. For presidents that served out a partial term and were re-elected to an additional term, I used the inaugural address given before the beginning of their full-term only—not the message they gave upon the death of their predecessor.

As we begin the transition of power anew, it is essential to look back at where we started and where we are now. Nations are built on tradition and ideals—the inaugural address represents both for the United States of America. Whatever the situation, the transition happens, a new president is inaugurated, and we set our eyes towards the future.

Yuvraj Singh

The First Inaugural Address of George Washington

by Stephen H. Browne

George Washington did not invent the inaugural address, but he did establish it as an abiding ritual of American political life. The Constitution requires no such statement: an oath of office, yes, and an annual report to Congress on the nation’s business. But of the inaugural address, nothing is said or even implied. Why then did Washington feel obliged to deliver a speech on the occasion of his assumption to office? Because the first president commanded a very keen grasp of power and how it ought to be managed on behalf of republican government. Citizens of the republic, in turn, expected power to show itself, to identify and explain the principles underwriting the office-holder’s claim to the public trust. No one, of course, was more entrusted with power at the time than George Washington. That he, of all people, should nevertheless perform such a duty tells us much about the man, the moment, and the functions of the inaugural address.

On April 14, 1789, a thoroughly fatigued Charles Thomson, Secretary of the Continental Congress, dismounted in front of Mount Vernon. He then informed Washington that he had been “elected to the office of President of the United States of America.” No one, safe to say, would have been surprised at this news, least of all its illustrious recipient. Washington indeed had prepared a statement for just this occasion, and reading from it declared: “While I realize the arduous nature of the task, which is conferred on me and feel my inability to perform it, I wish there may not be reason for regretting the choice. All I can promise is only that which can be accomplished by an honest zeal.” Two days later, the president-elect, Thomson, and David Humphreys set out on a what can only be described as a republican variant on the royal procession. The journey would take them from Mount Vernon to nearby Alexandria for a brief round of toasts and speeches, and from there to Baltimore, through Delaware and into Philadelphia; thence up to Trenton, Elizabethtown, and now on barge into the Upper Harbor. On April 23, 1789, Washington debarked onto the streets of lower Manhattan amidst much noise, festivity, and collective pride. The house on Cherry Street was readied for the president’s occupation; Congress had figured out most of the protocols; and in a week’s time Federal Hall would host the new nation’s first presidential inaugural address. On the appointed day, Washington was accompanied onto the balcony by New York Chancellor Robert Livingston, who administered the oath of office. Immediately upon its completion Livingston let out “Long live George Washington, President of the United States.” Thirteen canons roared their approval, and back into the chambers stepped the chief executive of the new nation.

What kind of speech might his fellow citizens expect? Washington was no orator, no Patrick Henry, and he never pretended otherwise. But whether on the fields of battle, at Mount Vernon, or in politics, he appreciated the power of language; and if Washington was not eloquent by nature, he knew how to get the best people around him to craft words for optimal effect. To this end he had enlisted Humphrey’s aid in composing the inaugural message. James Madison, taking one look at the 70-page jumble, nixed it and composed with Washington’s support a rather more precise, coherent, and compelling draft. From this document he would deliver his address before the House and Senate gathered on the second floor of Federal Hall on April 30, 1789.

Just what executive power meant in the new order of things was as yet uncertain. But the new nation had fought a war in part to ensure that those who commanded such power were motivated by principles consistent with widely held ideals of republican virtue. This meant above all a regard for the public good over and above private desire. Americans wanted to be certain that the president was there for the right reasons. Washington accordingly devoted the first two of the address’ five paragraphs to assuring the people that though longing to remain at Mount Vernon, “the asylum of my declining years,” he had accepted the “summons from my Country, whose voice I can never hear but with veneration and love.” In truth Washington had little to gain in any material way from assuming the office; he needed no boost to his reputation; and he certainly had no particular taste for the tumble of politics. Washington accepted the call because it was the right thing to do. For guidance he would look to Congress and people, but ultimately “to that Almighty Being who rules over the Universe, who presides in the Council of Nations,” confident that, in the end, “No People can be bound to acknowledge and adore the invisible hand, which conducts the Affairs of men more than the People of the United States.”

The assembled law makers that day would hear little in the way of specific recommendations or legislative priorities. Concerns about the military establishment, or commerce, or treaty relations with indigenous peoples, or indeed foreign policy are not even mentioned. Washington sought rather to underscore the essential tenets of republican government and the shared commitments upon which it must rest. Above all, he wished to stressed the unprecedented obligations shouldered by those gathered before him that day, this, because “the preservation of the sacred fire of liberty, and the destiny of the Republican model of Government, are justly considered as deeply, perhaps as finally staked, on the experiment entrusted to the hands of the American people.”

Ensuing presidents might and did on occasion insinuate into their inaugural address particular measures. Washington for the most part chose to emphasize just those principles with which the new nation could, without contest, give their unreserved assent: “reverence for the characteristic rights of freemen, and a regard for the public harmony.” He did make it a point to remind his listeners that Article Five of the Constitution provided a preferred method for amendment, and attempted (unsuccessfully) to decline compensation. Beyond these brief comments Washington hoped only to impart such sentiments as he thought proper to the occasion, praying, finally, that the blessings of “the benign parent of the human race” may “be equally conspicuous in the enlarged views, the temperate consultations, and wise measures on which the success of this Government must depend.”

Everything Washington did as president was, as he acknowledged, a precedent of some kind. The first inaugural address was no exception; the very fact that he chose to deliver it remains a lasting contribution to American civic life. That afternoon and evening, New Yorkers spilled onto the streets to celebrate, vessels in the harbor festooned their masts, guns bellowed, and troops marched. Judging from the evidence, all America seemed to rejoice. At 1,431 words it was not particularly long, nor was it especially colorful or provocative. The aim was rather to establish firmly and with utmost clarity the essential values necessary for making the republican experiment a success. In this the address might justly be said to have achieved its ends. On a personal level, the address served as a fair reflection of the man speaking: as the comte de Moustier recalled, the speech prompted “remembrances of that great man’s past services, his actual elevation, his modesty.” As a statement of political principles it extends well beyond the circumstances of the moment. More than two centuries later, the ritual of the presidential inauguration continues to function as a crucial means to republican ends.

The Second Inaugural Address of George Washington

by Kevin Butterfield

George Washington’s Second Inaugural Address is, by a good margin, the shortest inaugural address ever delivered. Using just 135 words, Washington focused directly on what is, of course, the key element of the inaugural ceremony—the oath of office, and the responsibilities that that oath imposes—and said little else. The speech seems to fit awkwardly in the company of inaugural addresses to come, ones that articulate policy visions and make grand statements of what the American nation should aspire to become. It has, on at least one occasion, simply been left out of a comprehensive account of presidential inaugural speeches.

Nonetheless, Washington’s Second Inaugural—all four sentences of it——merits our close attention. That it happened at all is itself important, the result of a thoughtful assessment by Washington and his cabinet, including Thomas Jefferson, Alexander Hamilton, and Henry Knox, of what was appropriate to the moment. And in the address’s focus upon the oath of office, Washington underscored an element of the presidency that can be overlooked: that the occupant of the office, while vested with substantial power, is also bound to adhere to the specific terms of an oath found in the Constitution itself.

There was no model to follow for what precisely should happen when a sitting president was elected to another term of office. The rituals of the American presidency were his to shape. In the election of 1792, Washington again had been elected president, unanimously, and again had great reluctance to take on the burdens of the office. There was a performative element in his repeated denials that he desired anything other than a long-delayed retirement, to be sure. But it is also true that Washington primarily saw his continuation in the presidency as the performance of a duty owed to the nation, not as a personal accomplishment or, as so many subsequent presidents would see things, as a mandate to follow through on a specific political agenda. All of these things likely shaped his thinking about how, if at all, to talk publicly about his election to a second term in office.

On February 27, 1793, just days before the new term was to begin on March 4, Washington wrote to his Cabinet members and asked the four of them—Jefferson, Knox, Hamilton, and Edmund Randolph—to put their heads together and propose to him their “opinions as to the time, place & manner of qualification,” or oath. When they gathered at the War Office at 9:00 the following morning, the cabinet members discovered that they could not agree. Jefferson and Hamilton, interestingly enough, both believed that Washington should simply take the oath privately, at his Philadelphia home, administered with no ceremony at all by Justice William Cushing of the Supreme Court, whose circuit included the nation’s capital. Knox and Randolph, on the other hand, advocated for a public event, in the presence of the members of Congress. In Jefferson’s recollection, Knox was “stickling for parade” and “got into great warmth” about the personal indispensability of Washington in the government’s survival: “it is the President’s character,” Jefferson remembered Knox arguing, “and not the written constitution which keeps it together.” Pomp and ceremony with Washington at the center, Knox believed, would serve a good purpose.

Ultimately, the four men recommended a public swearing-in, at noon, in the Senate Chamber with members of Congress and other dignitaries, such as foreign ministers, invited to observe. Hamilton acknowledged his initial concerns in a postscript he penned for President Washington, appended to the formal cabinet recommendation that Washington take the oath in a ceremony before Congress, but he did “think it right in the abstract to give publicity to the Act in question.” Washington agreed.

That Monday, Washington became the first man to be inaugurated president a second time. He also became the first president inaugurated on March 4, which would thereafter become one of the most important dates in the American political calendar—that is, until the ratification of the Twentieth Amendment in 1933, which moved the beginning of a presidential term to January 20. While the First Congress had been called to convene on March 4, 1789, Washington’s inauguration that year had come in late April, unavoidably delayed by the process of organizing the government. Beginning in 1793 and for nearly a century and a half, March 4 would become the standard date when one presidential term ended and another began.

Washington entered the Senate chamber precisely at noon, before an audience that included members of both houses of Congress, his own Cabinet, justices of the Supreme Court, foreign ministers, and “a number of private citizens, ladies and gentlemen,” according to the Philadelphia National Gazette. Vice President John Adams, who in many accounts is often mistakenly described as present, had left Philadelphia to attend to his wife, Abigail, during an illness. In his place, President Pro Tempore John Langdon called the proceedings to order by addressing Washington directly: “Sir, one of the Judges of the Supreme Court of the United States is now present, and ready to administer to you the oath required by the constitution, to be taken by the President of the United States.”

Washington stood and, to put it simply, briefly explained to Congress why it was that he had chosen to take the oath “in your presence.” He first noted that he would wait until “the occasion proper for it shall arrive” to go into more detail about “the high sense I entertain of this distinguished honor.” That time would come nine months later, in early December 1793, when Washington delivered his annual message to Congress and described both his “gratitude” and his “earnest wish for … retirement.” On this day, at his second inaugural ceremony, Washington chose to focus on the oath itself and the public accountability it demanded. Should it be found that he had “in any instance, violated, willingly or knowingly, the injunction” of that constitutional oath, Washington asked to be held accountable, both to the strictures of “Constitutional punishment” (he refers here, of course, to impeachment) and to “the upbraidings of all who are now witnesses of the present solemn ceremony.” The man whom Americans most trusted to hold power spent the entirety of his Second Inaugural asking those around him to hold him accountable, both legally and morally, to the oath he was about to take.

Washington’s focus on the oath should not be surprising. Oaths and affirmations were extraordinarily important to the founding of the new nation, one that despite its powerful racial hierarchies and exclusions was nonetheless held together primarily by shared belief, not by history or an ethnic nationalism more typical to European states. The War for Independence itself had driven this point home for Washington, who wrote to John Hancock in February 1777 to “strongly recommend every State to fix upon some Oath or Affirmation of Allegiance to be tendered to all the Inhabitants without exception, and to out law those that refuse it.” As a wartime leader in a chaotic environment in which allegiances were constantly up for grabs, Washington saw that “by our inattention” to oaths as a way to bind the people together “we lose a considerable Cement to our own Force, and give the Enemy an opportunity to make the first tender of the oath of allegiance to the King.” Interestingly, it was in this same letter that Washington advocated to Congress that steps be taken to inoculate the Continental Army against smallpox. The goal, in some ways, was similar: to prevent the spread of danger by securing people against it in advance.

With independence won and, after the Constitutional Convention of 1787, a new federal government created, the oath remained a crucial component in holding things together. In fact, the very first bill signed into law under the new government, on June 1, 1789, was “An Act to Regulate the Time and Manner of Administering Oaths,” which dictated the precise oath to be taken by all state and federal officials as called for in Article VI of the Constitution—everyone, that is, except the president, whose oath was found in the text of the Constitution itself. Now, nearly four years later and entering a second term in office, Washington took an opportunity to underscore just why those oaths were important. They bound the officers of the government to remain faithful and to fulfill their constitutional duties.

His short speech concluded, Washington stood opposite Justice William Cushing, who administered the oath. It is worth noting that the contemporary account in the Philadelphia National Gazette makes clear that Washington did not add the words “so help me God” at the end, further evidence that the myth that he had added those words four years earlier in New York is without any basis. After taking the oath, Washington left “as he had come,” wrote the National Gazette, “without pomp or ceremony.” Though brief, though distinctly different from the addresses that would come from all those who would later assume the office, Washington’s Second Inaugural Address had one point to make, and it made it well: in a constitutional order full of checks, balances, and structural limitations on arbitrary power, the presidential oath was yet another safeguard to protect the American republic.

The Inaugural Address of John Adams

by Rhonda Barlow

On the day after his inauguration as the second vice president of the United States, John Adams wrote to his wife Abigail, “Your dearest Friend never had a more trying day than Yesterday.” As the successor to George Washington, he faced a daunting challenge: to the tearyeyed crowd gathered in the chamber of the House of Representatives on March 4, 1797, it appeared that a glorious sun was setting, and one “less Splendid” was rising. Adams nevertheless observed, “Methought I heard him think Ay! I am fairly out and your fairly in! see which of Us will be happiest.”

For President Adams, the unhappy circumstances of 1797 included not only unfavorable comparisons to George Washington, but also a crisis in foreign policy, which had contributed to a division of the Federalists between those who would follow his leadership, and the High Federalists, who tended to look to Alexander Hamilton for guidance, as well as the emergence of the rival Republican Party. Adams had been Washington’s vice president, Alexander Hamilton the secretary of the treasury, and Thomas Jefferson the secretary of state. Hamilton, though now a private citizen, held tremendous influence with Washington’s—now Adams’s—cabinet, and emphasized the advantages to the United States of commercial ties with Great Britain. Jefferson, sympathetic to the French revolutionaries, had abandoned his retirement from public life, and although acknowledged head of the Republican Party, was nevertheless Adams’s vice president. The political chaos seemed to call for the independent executive, balancing opposing forces, whom Adams had written about in the three sprawling volumes of his

Defence of the Constitutions of the United States

.

The crisis in foreign policy centered on yet another breach in the peace between Great Britain and France. The 1789 French Revolution first appeared to be establishing a constitutional monarchy similar to that of Britain, then a French “sister” republic, even more worthy of the 1778 alliance. But President Washington instead declared the United States at peace with both powers, and sent John Jay to negotiate a commercial treaty with Great Britain. Americans disagreed on their interpretation and application of the 1778 French treaties. Was the United States obligated to take an active part in the war on the side of France? Could French privateers enter American ports with their prizes, and have the local French consul declare them legal captures? Was a treaty made with the French monarch still valid with a revolutionary republican government? Was the Jay Treaty simply a commercial treaty between the United States and Great Britain or was it an unprincipled surrender to the enemy of America’s French ally? Was Washington’s Neutrality Proclamation a violation of the Constitution?

Two days before Adams’s inauguration, the Directory, whether genuinely appalled that America has signed the Jay Treaty with Great Britain, or simply eyeing American commerce as a source of revenue—or motivated by some combination of the two—granted permission to French privateers to seize American merchant ships. Writing to his son, John Quincy on March 31, 1797, Adams explained that his presidency was commencing with a “Misunderstanding” with France that he hoped to resolve through diplomacy without sacrificing American honor. He insisted, using large letters for emphasis, that America was not “Scared.”

In preparing his inaugural address, Adams needed to acknowledge the status of George Washington, reassure listeners that he took the French threat to American shipping seriously, and attempt to unite the High Federalists and the Jeffersonian Republicans. At over 2000 words, his inaugural address was longer than those given by his predecessor, George Washington, and his successor, Thomas Jefferson. His call for a system of neutrality appears at first glance to be support for George Washington’s Neutrality Proclamation. But Adams’s commitment to an independent foreign policy predated the Washington administration by more than a decade.

Accordingly, Adams’s speech was an overview of American history that began with the struggle for independence during the American Revolution. By drawing attention to the overreach of the British Parliament, he suggested that the French Directory was attempting a similar tyranny. He praised the Constitution as the foundation for a successful foreign policy, made clear his appreciation for the French, but warned that political factions invited foreign meddling in American politics. By recounting the nation’s history, he highlighted his own role in that history. He was the Atlas of Independence who insisted the time for reconciliation was past, the diplomat in France who refused to be cowed by the Comte de Vergennes, the representative who negotiated the Anglo-American peace treaty that ended the Revolutionary War, and the first minister to the Court of St. James who heralded a new relationship with the former mother country. The patriotic American familiar with both courts, who had conquered them during the Revolution, was now at the helm. Adams was the revolutionary who insisted, “I will be buried in the Ocean or in any other manner sacrificed, before I will voluntarily put on the Chains of France when I am struggling to throw off those of Great Britain.” There was no danger that as president he would be a pawn of Great Britain, and although not as friendly to France as his vice president Thomas Jefferson, neither was he as hostile as members of his cabinet.

Adams was unsure if his speech had been successful. Recognizing the opposition he faced, he explained to Abigail on March 9, 1797 that in both his farewell speech to the Senate and his inaugural address, “I was determined to say some Things, as an Appeal to Posterity. foreign nations and future times will understand them better.” But two days later, the Philadelphia Aurora General Advertiser, normally highly critical of the Federalists, conceded that Adams’s inaugural address was that “of a fellow citizen, who will not deign to become the President of a Party, but the President of the United States.” Still in the future were the failed commission to France, the French demand for a bribe which led to the XYZ affair, the new provisional army, the potential escalation of the Quasi-War with France into a full-scale war, the threat of a formal alliance between the United States and Great Britain, and his loss of the presidency.

Adams would later boast that he was the founder of the American system of neutrality, that he had “humbled” the French Directory, and that in making peace with France he had prevented a tyrannical alliance between the United States and Great Britain. But the memory of his presidency has instead been focused on the notorious Alien and Sedition Acts. The balance between defending the Union from threats foreign and domestic, and at the same respecting individual rights and freedom remains the legacy of his administration.

The Man of the People: The Second Inaugural Address of Thomas Jefferson

by Annette Gordon-Reed

On March 4, 1805, when President Thomas Jefferson gave his second inaugural address in the wake of his re-election to the presidency of the United States, he faced drastically different circumstances from the time when he famously pronounced, “we are all republicans: we are all federalists” on the occasion of his first inaugural address. On that day, in March of 1803, those assembled to hear the newly-elected President speak in a voice so soft that many in the audience could not hear all he had to say were well aware of the bruising circumstances that attended his rise to the position of Chief Executive. After an extremely hard-hitting political battle against the incumbent John Adams, Jefferson and Aaron Burr (who was supposed to be vice-president) ended up with an equal number of electoral votes. The election had been thrown to the House of Representatives. Jefferson was elected on the 36th ballot.

Jefferson’s first election was notable, among other things, for being the first transfer of power between the political parties that had been formed during the country’s first decade of existence —the Federalists, headed by Washington and Adams, and the Democratic-Republicans, headed by Jefferson. Jefferson later referred to his first election as the “Revolution of 1800” in which he and his fellow Democratic-Republicans, in his view, had brought the country back to the principles of 1776. The battles had not ceased. Although the Federalist press had been even more aggressive in attacking him during the run-up to his second election, he ultimately had a much easier time winning the second time around. He crushed his Federalist opponent Charles Cotesworth Pinckney, receiving 162 electoral votes to Pinckney’s 14. The Democratic-Republicans gained large majorities in the Senate and the House. So, as he gave his second inaugural address, as softly as he had his First, Jefferson had every reason to feel that he was more in command of the situation than he had been four years before, a confidence that is evident in the language employed in his speech.

Notes he wrote in preparation for the address show that Jefferson perfectly understood the task before him.

“The former one [the First Inaugural] was an exposition of the principles on which I thought it my duty to administer the government. the second then should naturally be a Compte rendu, or a statement of facts, shewing that I have conformed to those principles. the former was promise: this is performance.”[1]

The choice of the word “performance” is interesting for two reasons. There is the substance—speaking about the things he did. But there is “performance” in another sense: the actual giving of the speech. Markings on the reading draft of the Address show that Jefferson paid particular attention to how he was going to deliver the speech. He placed markings for when he was to speak with particular emphasis and for moments when he was to pause. And unlike his first inaugural address, the Second was written in a form of shorthand. So, for example, the first paragraph:

Proceeding, fellow citizens, to that qualification which the constitution requires before my entrance on the charge again conferred on me, it is my duty to express the deep sense I entertain of this new proof of confidence from my fellow citizens at large, and the zeal with which it inspires me so to conduct myself as may best satisfy their just expectations.

was rendered:

proceedg. f. c. to yt qualfcn ′ wch ye Constn[2] reqres. befre. my entrnce. on ye charge agn. conferd. on me †

it is my duty t. exprss. ye deep sense I entertn. ′ of ys new proof of confidce. frm. my f. c. at large & ye zeal wth. whch. it inspires m. ′ s. t. condct. myslf. ′ as m. best satsfy yr just expectns.′′[3]

In his notes about the address, Jefferson set out six areas of concentration speech, or “heads” as he termed them, and he stuck to them:

These heads are, Foreign affairs; Domestic do. viz. Taxes. Debts. Louisiana. Religion. Indians. the Press. none of these heads need any commentary but that of the Indians. this is a proper topic, not only to promote the work of humanising our citizens towards these people, but to conciliate to us the good opinion of Europe on the subject of the Indians.[4]

Although well-written, as one would expect of Jefferson, his second inaugural address was not as profound or memorable as the first. That would seem natural given the circumstances outlined above, when much more was at stake. Jefferson was a known quantity by 1805. Before he was president, he had been branded a Jacobin who would bring chaos to the country. He would unleash the unbridled democracy of the mob. He would ban the Bible and confiscate it from private homes. Incest and adultery would become rampant.

Of course, none of those things happened. Instead, as Jefferson emphasized in the first paragraphs of his address, during the four years of his presidency, the country had been stable and thriving. On foreign policy, his administration had kept the United States at peace with other nations—“we have endeavored to cultivate the friendship of all nations, & especially of those with which we have the most important relations.”[5] Then, on the domestic front, the government was smaller and more efficient, he said. Playing to the voters who made up his base of support, he noted that the administration had favored the end to internal taxes, relying instead on tariffs which, he felt it important to point out, largely affected “those who [could] afford to add foreign luxuries to domestic comforts.” And then: “it may be the pleasure and the pride of an American to ask What farmer, what mechanic, what labourer ever sees a tax-gatherer of the US.?” He predicted that the country was on its way to being free of debt, one of his particular obsessions.

Then Jefferson turned to his most important achievement of all. He had scored a historic diplomatic triumph that transformed the physical boundaries of the United States. The Louisiana Purchase of 1803 had doubled the size of the country and was widely popular among white Americans who believed in the goal of westward expansion. The Federalists, as Jefferson reminded without mentioning his opponents by name, had, in the main, been opposed to the deal. They feared the prospect of upsetting the balance of power as the territory potentially would bring more Western and Southern states into the Union, the sprawl endangering the viability of the Republic. Jefferson had an answer to that fear in one of the address’s more memorable lines: “but who can limit the extent to which the federative principle may operate effectively?” The Purchase was of questionable enough constitutionality that Jefferson had drafted his own Amendment to the Constitution to allow for the transaction. As time was of the essence in making the deal, however, he decided to go ahead without invoking the Amendment process. This alone made him and his party enormously popular.

After a brief mention of religion—it was not a matter for interference by the federal government—Jefferson turned to the poignant section of the address, discussing the “Aboriginals”. He restated a position that he had expressed privately and in

Notes on the State of Virginia

: Native peoples had to be incorporated into the United States by a process of assimilation. They had to give up their ways of life. He scorned the idea that peoples should do things because their ancestors had done those things, a point he had made in other contexts, and presented the triumph of the European Americans as a fait accompli:

the stream of overflowing population from other regions directed itself on these shores. without power to divert, or habits to contend against it, they have been overwhelmed by the current, or driven before it.

There was no way, in his telling, of a different outcome.

Jefferson followed a fairly long disquisition on the nature of the press. He had been known as a champion of press freedom, but it appears that his bruising experience between 1798 and the period before the election had given him a more jaundiced view. He spoke of the “artillery of the press” that has been used against him and his fellow Democratic-Republicans. In any event, the best guard against overreaching by the press would be the public.

public judgment will correct false reasonings & opinions, on a full hearing of all parties; and no other definite line can be drawn between the inestimable liberty of the press, and it’s demoralising licentiousness. if there be still improprieties which this rule would not restrain, it’s Supplement must be sought in the Censorship of Public opinion.[6]

After stating all of his administration’s accomplishments, Jefferson ended on an optimistic note, indicating that he took the results to be a mandate to continue in the direction he had taken. Like most presidents who have two terms, Jefferson’s second term in office would be seen as, if not a failure, a disappointment. On March 4, 1805, however, the prospects for continued success seemed clear to him.

The First Inaugural Address of James Madison

by Stuart Eric Leibiger

At noon on Saturday, March 4, 1809, fifty-seven-year-old Virginian James Madison read his first—and the nation’s sixth—inaugural address from a hand-written manuscript in the House of Representatives chamber in the United States Capitol building in Washington, D.C. “A large concourse of citizens” joined Congress to witness the speech. “Such was the interest to be present at the Inauguration that the whole area allotted to citizens in the Representative Hall was filled, and overflowing several hours before noon,” reported the National Intelligencer. “It is computed that the number of persons surrounding the Capitol, unable to obtain admittance, exceeded ten thousand.”

After assuring his listeners of the profound sense of duty impressed upon him “by the call of my Country” to the presidency, Madison candidly pronounced “the present situation” of the nation “full of difficulties.” Yet he could not bring himself to blame the country’s political, economic, and diplomatic woes on the preceding administration. That regime had been led by his good friend Thomas Jefferson, under whom he himself had been the secretary of state, overseeing the realm of foreign affairs where the country’s troubles had begun. During Jefferson’s presidency, the United States had found itself caught between the belligerent nations Great Britain and France, who were locked in the bitter conflict known as the Napoleonic Wars. On the one hand, the war offered tremendous trade opportunities, as both sides eagerly sought U.S. agricultural products. But on the other hand, U.S. ships headed for either England or France were often seized and confiscated by the navy of the other side on the high seas. Jefferson’s solution to the dilemma was the Embargo, passed by a compliant Republican Congress in 1807. An ill-fated attempt at economic coercion, the Embargo banned all exports from the U.S. until the belligerent nations stopped seizing American ships. Instead of bringing Great Britain and France to their knees in their desperation for American produce, the Embargo instead threw the U.S. into an economic recession. One reason for the Embargo’s failure was the refusal of New England merchants to abide by it. These traders were willing to take their chances on the high seas, knowing that enough cargoes would reach their destinations to turn handsome profits despite occasional ship seizures. Determined to give his Embargo a fair trial, Jefferson tried to enforce it on the New England states by martial law. Congress’s repeal of the Embargo took effect on March 4, 1809, the very day Madison took office. The administration’s experiment in economic coercion had failed. It would be up to the new president, an originator of the hapless Embargo, to deal with the fallout.

Madison’s First Inaugural Address thus could hardly blame the nation’s troubles on his predecessor. “It is a precious reflection,” declared Madison, “that the transition from this prosperous condition of our Country, to the scene which has for some time been distressing us, is not chargeable on any unwarrantable views, nor, as I trust, on any involuntary errors in the public Counsils.” Instead, Madison blamed the nation’s misfortunes on the extreme and desperate measures of Great Britain and France. “In their rage against each other,” Madison bemoaned, “principles of retaliation have been introduced, equally contrary to universal reason, and acknowledged law.” With the unexpected failure of the Embargo, “how long their arbitrary edicts will be continued … cannot be anticipated.”

Madison’s First Inaugural Address did not offer new policy proposals to deal with the crisis. Instead, it promised that the U.S. would “cherish peace and friendly intercourse with all nations having correspondent dispositions,” and would “maintain sincere neutrality towards belligerent nations.” War would be a last resort. Madison further pledged “to support the Constitution … in its limitations as in its authorities.” Perhaps already anticipating a war with Great Britain, Madison assured that his administration would never use events as an excuse to trample personal rights and liberties enshrined in the Bill of Rights that he himself had authored. He would “avoid the slightest interference with the rights of conscience, or the functions of religion,” and would “preserve in their full energy, the other salutary provisions in behalf of private and personal rights, and of the freedom of the press.” His administration would not take advantage of the crisis to aggrandize the power of the federal government, or to militarize American society by the introduction of “a standing military force” that Revolutionary Era citizens had dreaded so much as an instrument of tyranny.

In facing an uncertain future, Madison’s First Inaugural Address promised that he would be guided by the “illustrious” examples of his predecessors as chief executive, including Jefferson. He would also rely on “the well tried intelligence and virtue of my fellow citizens” and on the support and advice of the other branches of the federal government. Finally, he would look to the “guardianship and guidance of that Almighty Being … whose blessings have been so conspicuously dispensed to this rising Republic.”

After failing to halt the seizures of American ships (mainly by the British, who had established naval superiority on the Atlantic Ocean) and to stop the British practice of impressment of sailors from U.S. vessels, Madison sought a declaration of war against Great Britain in 1812. An uncharismatic leader, Madison performed disappointingly as Commander in Chief during the War of 1812. He failed to provide the vigorous and competent leadership of the armed forces during conflict that George Washington had once demonstrated. He could not prevent the British from invading Washington, D.C. in 1814 and burning the public buildings, including the White House. Throughout the hostilities, however, Madison scrupulously adhered to the promise articulated in his inaugural address to preserve and protect personal rights and liberties. President Madison, in short, led the U.S. through a second war for independence against Great Britain without undermining or infringing upon the nation’s republican principles. In so doing, he maintained the devotion of his fellow citizens, and could almost certainly have won a third term as president had he desired one.

James Madison is perhaps the only president whose pre-presidential career is studied more than his presidency. Yet his presidency witnessed many critical events, not the least of which was the first ever presidential request for a congressional declaration of war. Interestingly, President Madison’s First Inaugural Address was not the first inaugural speech that he wrote. In 1789, as a confidential advisor to president-elect George Washington, Madison had ghostwritten a draft of the very first inaugural address. Indeed, as the Father of the Constitution and the Father of the Bill of Rights, Madison came to the presidency more well versed in American constitutionalism than any other president, qualifications amply demonstrated by his First Inaugural Address.

The Second Inaugural Address of James Madison

by J. C. A. Stagg

At noon on 4 March 1813 James Madison delivered his second inaugural address before a concourse of congressmen, diplomats, judges, and other residents of the nation’s capital. As he was drafting his remarks, the president’s thoughts undoubtedly recurred to the message he had sent to Congress on 1 June 1812, listing the reasons why he believed the United States should declare war against Great Britain. That message had been organized as a catalogue of the violations of American neutral rights and sovereignty committed by Great Britain after 1803. It culminated in the prediction that the national legislature would issue a declaration worthy of “the enlightened and patriotic Councils of a virtuous, a free, and powerful nation” before concluding with the hint that the international situation of the republic was so fraught with difficulties that a war against France might also be necessary.

The intervening nine months had not gone well for the Madison administration. The principal justification for the war—Great Britain’s seemingly inflexible adherence to the trade restrictions embodied in the Orders in Council—had been removed in London five days after the commencement of hostilities on 18 June 1812. Worse, the United States proved to be a far less powerful nation than Madison had wished. Three invasions of the British provinces of Upper and Lower Canada had ended in embarrassing failures, with one of them resulting in the loss of Detroit and the Michigan territory to numerically inferior British forces and their Native American allies. The U.S. Army had been unable to equip and train the forces raised since the spring of 1812. Admittedly, the infant U.S. Navy had exceeded low expectations by winning three encounters at sea with British frigates, but there had been no comparable successes on the Great Lakes, which would have facilitated the operations of American land forces. Consequently, the British government was under no pressure to engage in negotiations over the grievances Madison had outlined in June. Nor had France improved its relations with the United States. Instead, Napoleon had embarked on the invasion of Russia at the very same moment the United States went to war with Great Britain. Madison had anticipated that Napoleon would win his war—thereby making Russia’s British ally more amenable to ending its American war—but by early 1813 it was clear that Napoleon had sustained a massive defeat, with French imperial forces in full retreat from eastern Europe. Great Britain was now in an even stronger position vis-à-vis the United States.

This was the situation Madison faced as he entered on his second term, immediately after three difficult months with the second session of the Twelfth Congress. Congressional dissatisfaction with the conduct of the war had compelled Madison to restructure his cabinet. The failures of the Canadian campaigns required hasty improvisations to raise and train new forces for the spring and summer of 1813. And the successes of the navy dictated a greater expansion of its forces—both for the Great Lakes and the Atlantic Ocean—to an extent that president and his Republican allies only grudgingly conceded. All of this would require significant increases in spending, but Congress balked at imposing taxes, even though it had pledged in 1812 that taxation would be required in a state of war. But over the winter of 1812–13, Congress did no more than double the duties on imported goods, an expedient that irritated the nation’s mercantile communities. Despite these difficulties Madison had won re-election in November 1812, albeit with a reduced majority from his success in 1808. However, his critics, in his own party and in the Federalist opposition, were now more numerous and more vociferous than they had been in 1812. The next session of Congress, which Madison had already summoned for a spring meeting to address the needs of the Treasury, promised to be the most difficult the president had ever faced.

For all these reasons, Madison’s second inaugural was a short document, barely 1500 words, and it concealed more than it revealed. The president’s immediate problem was: how to justify continuing a war under such unpromising circumstances and how might the United State emerge victorious? There is no evidence that Madison ever considered ending the war; his goal remained to obtain a peace treaty that addressed all the grievances he had outlined in June 1812. But after Great Britain had lifted the Orders in Council, attention had to be focused on the next most serious grievance—the impressment of American seamen by the Royal Navy on the high seas. This had long been an intractable dispute that had not even been the subject of serious discussions since 1808. At one point, Madison had contemplated that Great Britain and the United States might agree to forego the employment of their nationals in their respective merchant marines, but Great Britain would never accept this and the policy would have seriously harmed the expansion of American commerce. Even so, in February 1813 the president revived this proposal and called upon Congress to turn it into law in order to provide a firmer basis of support for the war.

The so-called Seamen’s Bill had passed Congress by the end of February 1813, but it hardly accomplished Madison’s goals. Certainly, many of the Federalists, all of whom had voted against war in June 1812, supported the bill, but a larger number of Republicans, including several of the strongest supporters of the war, voted against it. Their reason was that by seeming to accept in advance Great Britain’s claims that the United States should neither naturalize British subjects nor employ them on American vessels, the administration had made too great a concession to British doctrines about citizenship and sovereignty. Nevertheless, much of Madison’s second inaugural was devoted to justifying the war on the grounds that it was essential to protect all American mariners from impressment, regardless of their country of origin, and particularly to safeguard British subjects who had enlisted in the American armed forces and become prisoners of war from the threat of treason trials. Otherwise, the address said little else about the grievances Madison had cited in his 1 June 1812 message. He withdrew, to some extent, his charge that the British in Canada had incited Native Americans in the Northwest to wage war on the frontiers, and instead criticized the enemy for accepting the services of such “savage” allies. And about the possibility of a war with France, Madison said nothing at all.

As Madison delivered this address, many in his audience must have suspected that Great Britain would not agree to a peace based on the Seamen’s Bill. But Madison had withheld one piece of information that he believed might make a treaty possible. In September 1812, Alexander I of Russia had offered to mediate in the war between Great Britain and the United States. The emperor was allied to Great Britain in the war against France, but he also strongly sympathized with the United States in its rejection of British doctrines about maritime and neutral rights. The Russian offer had reached Washington by the end of February 1813, but Madison did not announce that he would accept it until 8 March 1813. He may have even concluded that Great Britain would accept the Russian offer. The prospect of Russian diplomatic support against Great Britain, even as French power in Europe declined, was one reason why Madison decided that the War of 1812 should be continued. Details of his other ideas about how the war might be waged were left until the first session of the Thirteenth Congress assembled in Washington on 24 May 1813.

The Era of Good Feelings: The First Inaugural Address of James Monroe

by Daniel F. Preston

James Monroe assumed the reins of government during a period of peace and prosperity. The European war that had begun in the early 1790s and that persisted until 1815, and that had ensnared the United States and led to the War of 1812 was at last ended. The American economy, which had been badly shaken by the years of maritime disruption and war, was showing a remarkable recovery, exemplified by the steady stream of revenue from land sales, import tariffs, and excise taxes flowing into the national treasury. To be certain, there were grave crises lurking just beyond the horizon, but in March 1817, a bright future beckoned.

When Monroe turned to address the crowd attending the ceremony—the first inauguration to be held outdoors—the new president began his remarks by examining the causes of the “present happy condition” of the country. For Monroe, the explanation could be summed up in one word: republicanism. The strength and prosperity of the United States flowed from an adherence to the principles of self-government championed during the American Revolution and enunciated in the federal constitution as well as in the constitutions of the various states. Republicanism—a system of popularly elected representatives and constitutional government free of the trappings of monarchy, hereditary aristocracy, and established religion—was Monroe’s political credo from the days of the American Revolution until his death in 1831.

How, Monroe asked rhetorically, can we explain the success of the American experiment in elective government in the face of wide-ranging skepticism about the practicability of such a form of government and the failure of other attempts throughout history to establish such a system? During a period “fraught with difficulties” the United States had “flourished beyond example.” The citizens were happy; the nation prosperous; territorial boundaries had been expanded and new states admitted; the states themselves, protected by the national government from foreign aggression, enjoyed sovereignty in their separate spheres and effectively governed themselves. How was this done? “How did we accomplish the revolution?” “How sustain, and pass with glory through the late war?” The president had a ready answer: “The government has been in the hands of the people.” To the people, with their intelligence, their independence, and their virtue “is the credit due.”

Monroe encapsulated his absolute belief in the political virtue of the American people in just a few sentences. He went into much greater detail, however, in an unused draft of the message. The English heritage of representative government and the semi-independent status of the British American colonies imbued the American people with a love of republicanism. It gave them the fortitude and courage to fight for and win their independence. It gave them the understanding and temperament to form republican governments and the intelligence and virtue to sustain them. As long as the American people remained true to the principles of the Revolution and the Constitution, they could confront and overcome any challenge, domestic or foreign, that arose. “While the constituent body retains its present sound and healthful state,” he said in his address, “every thing will be safe.” There being no crisis of any proportion worth noting, the American people had only two major tasks at hand: to preserve the liberty and advantages they enjoyed under their republican government and to further develop the prosperity of the nation.

And yet, for all his faith in the American people, he still warned about complacency. Without proper vigilance the people may become “ignorant and corrupt,” “the willing instruments of their own debasement and ruin.” “Usurpation is then an easy attainment,” he warned, “and an usurper soon found.” To prevent such a situation, he vaguely suggested that Congress, “by all wise and constitutional measures,” create a system of academies “as the best means of preserving our liberties,” a hint that he stated more explicitly in his first annual message to Congress in December 1817, by urging a constitutional amendment that would grant “a right in Congress to institute seminaries of learning, for the all-important purpose, of diffusing knowledge among our fellow citizens, throughout the United States.”

Nor should the American people be complacent about peace. The United States had been caught unprepared for war in 1812, and although the Americans had fought the war to an honorable termination, Monroe knew how perilously close the country had come to disaster. He was now adamant that this must not happen again. The possibility of war in the future should not be discounted and with an enemy determined to “overset our government, to break our union and demolish us as a nation.” The key to national defense was, of course, a well-regulated army and navy, moderate in size, but “adequate to the necessary purposes” of defense. Also, a system of fortifications was needed to defend the nation’s extensive coastline, a measure that Monroe had urged at least as early as 1805. And finally, there was the militia, the central bulwark of defense in any republic. The new president had been an advocate for a strong national defense throughout his public career, but like many of his generation he harbored a fear that a large professional army, detached from the daily concerns of the people, could become an instrument of tyranny. A standing army was certainly necessary to meet any immediate danger, but the great body of any defensive force should be embodied in the militia. Monroe’s experience as governor of Virginia and as Secretary of War made him well aware of the inadequacies of the militia, and he now insisted, as he had done in the past, that this people’s army be “organized and trained as to be prepared for any emergency.”

Monroe went on to note that the United States was particularly blessed in its geographic location, occupying a portion of the globe that produced a great variety of valuable crops and natural resources. “No country was ever happier with respect to its domain,” he wrote, especially in terms of agriculture. The United States possessed soil so fertile that there had always been a surplus for export, even at the times of the poorest harvests. This benefited not only the growers, but also the merchants and seamen who carried the agricultural bounty to other countries. The United States was home to a vast overseas carrying trade, a trade so critical that British interference with it led to the declaration of war in 1812. Monroe was well aware of the importance of foreign trade to the economic wealth of the nation, and both as Secretary of State and President sought commercial treaties that not only secured advantageous trade agreements with the European powers but also expanded American trade into new markets. At the same time, he hoped to expand the American economy at home, not only by bringing new land into cultivation but also by encouraging the development of manufacturing. The United States possessed the necessary raw materials and capital and “ought not to depend in the degree we have done” on foreign countries for finished goods. This beneficial economic independence could be achieved with “the systematic and fostering care of the government.”

Monroe ventured on to more controversial ground when he urged the passage of a constitutional amendment granting the national government authority to construct a network of roads and canals. Most Americans acknowledged that such a system was needed, and being national in scope, that it ought to be undertaken by the national government. But they disagreed whether the government possessed the constitutional authority to do so. Monroe was one of the doubters and favored the expedient of a constitutional amendment specifically granting the power. But he had no doubt of the necessity or benefit of such a network. Not only would it add to the “convenience and comfort” of the people, but by shortening distances and making the various parts of the country “more accessible to and dependent on the other,” it would “bind the union more closely together.”

This brought the president to the other basics tenets of his political creed—the absolute necessity of the union of the states. Monroe believed that the state governments bore the responsibility of protecting the liberty and promoting the welfare of their citizens. But he also believed that they were not strong enough individually and or regionally to do this. They must unite in a continental union to protect the republic from all threats domestic and foreign. Monroe told his audience that he was gratified by the harmony that pervaded the nation. “Discord does not belong to our system.” Unity had carried the American people through past trials, and it would continue to promote prosperity and happiness. The American people “constitute one great family, with a common interest.” “To promote this harmony, in accord with the principles of our republican government, and in a manner to give them the most complete effect, and to advance in all other respects, the best interests of our Union,” Monroe promised, “will be the object of my constant and zealous exertions.”

The Second Inaugural Address of James Monroe

by Sandra Moats

James Monroe’s second inauguration as president in 1821 proved to be unusual in several respects. With the congressionally mandated date of March 4th falling on a Sunday, Monroe delayed his inauguration until Monday March 5 in deference to religious observances. (The inaugurations of 1849, 1877, and 1917 also occurred on March 5 for the same reason.) Monroe’s path to a second term was even more remarkable: he ran unopposed, the only president other than George Washington to enjoy such a distinction. His lack of a presidential opponent underscored the political crossroads the nation confronted in 1820. The once robust Federalist party no longer enjoyed a national following. Meanwhile, younger members of Monroe’s Democratic-Republican party, lacking the stature and prominence of the founding generation, waited in the wings for their shot at the presidency. Monroe’s second inaugural address anticipated this political watershed as he reviewed his first term accomplishments and largely avoided making bold policy pronouncements for the future.

Speaking to his “Fellow Citizens,” Monroe began his inaugural address by situating his presidency within the larger context of the republican ideas and the sovereign citizens whose “confidence” made his second term possible. He reminded his audience that the American government was “founded by the people, who possess exclusively the sovereignty.” He also honored his presidential predecessors, “whose names are so much more conspicuously identified with our Revolution.” Instead, Monroe saw himself “as the instrument than the cause of the union.” He renewed his commitment to the United States’ founding principles of “liberty, prosperity, and happiness.” With the nation’s sovereign citizens entrusting Monroe with a second term as president, he believed he owed his “constituents” a “review” of the “principal occurrences” of his first term and “further explanation” of his “judgments.” This overview guided the content and organization of his 1821 inaugural address.

As Monroe discussed his first term accomplishments and their future ramifications, he emphasized foreign affairs. He explained to his audience: “The conduct of the government . . . to foreign powers is an always an object of the highest importance to the nation.” Other issues such as the nation’s “agriculture, commerce, manufactures, fisheries, revenue, in short, its peace, may all be affected by it.” For this reason, “attention is therefore due to this subject” of international affairs.

Of course, the most significant issue in foreign affairs was the recently concluded War of 1812 with Great Britain. Trading disputes in the Atlantic, particularly British impressment of American sailors, provided the principal motivation for this war. Monroe reminded his audience that “the events of that war are too recent and too deeply impressed on the memory of all to require a development from me.” Instead, Monroe focused on the war’s hefty price tag: $120 million, as well as the lessons from the war: the need to build fortifications to defend the nation’s Atlantic coastline and to raise a navy capable of supporting and protecting these military facilities. With these defenses being constructed, Monroe also reported that more than half of the war debt, about $67 million, had been paid.

Monroe then turned his attention to the warfare occurring between Spain and its colonies in South America. Despite the geographical proximity of these conflicts to the United States, Monroe reiterated that these disputes were “a contest between different parts of the same community” and did not concern the United States. Instead, he renewed the nation’s longstanding commitment to neutrality, an approach that had begun with George Washington’s Neutrality Proclamation of 1793. American neutrality emphasized friendly trading relations with all nations, even those at war, along with a steadfast avoidance of political or diplomatic alliances that would entangle the United States in unnecessary warfare. Monroe explained how this principle worked in practice: “by this equality between the parties their public vessels have been received in our ports on the same footing; they have enjoyed an equal right to purchase and export arms, munitions of war, and every other supply . . . permitted under laws.” Nonetheless, Monroe left open the possibility “to adopt such measures” as needed, if the warfare in South America continued.

Closer to home, Monroe discussed the unauthorized invasion of Spanish Florida by a “band of adventurers” in 1817-1818. Known officially as the First Seminole War, General Andrew Jackson had led this assault against Spanish authorities, Florida’s Seminole tribe, and even two British officers. Despite the diplomatic embarrassment of Jackson’s escapades, his successful attack exposed Spain’s weaknesses in Florida (and elsewhere) and paved the way for the Transcontinental Treaty of 1819. Although Monroe did not mention Jackson by name in his Inaugural Address, he did highlight the importance of the 1819 treaty: “Great confidence is entertained that the late treaty with Spain . . . has placed the relations of the two countries on a basis of permanent friendship.” This landmark treaty resulted in the legal acquisition of Florida as well as a clarification of the nation’s western boundary along the vast Louisiana territory, acquired from France in 1803. In 1818, the United States had also concluded a treaty with Britain affirming the northern boundary of the United States at the 49th parallel.

As he discussed the state of European affairs in 1821, Monroe could not have seen that the Napoleonic Wars between Britain and France during the 1810s, as well as Spain’s attenuation as a power, would produce an important diplomatic opportunity for the United States. Nonetheless, several years later, Monroe and his able Secretary of State, John Quincy Adams, recognized a diplomatic opportunity and issued the landmark “Monroe Doctrine” in 1823. A bold statement of solidarity between the United States and its “sister republics” in South America, the Monroe Doctrine declared that the Western Hemisphere was closed to further European colonization. And despite an official stance of neutrality, the United States would view any new colonial encroachments as a threat to its well-being.

Although receiving much less attention than foreign affairs, Monroe’s Inaugural Address highlighted two domestic issues. One was the economic downtown known as the Panic of 1817, in which Americans experienced the loss of jobs, homes, and lands. To alleviate the financial burden on struggling Americans, Monroe had recommended the lowering of taxes. The second domestic issue concerned Native Americans, and unlike other parts of the address, represented a dramatic change in policy rather than a reflection of past accomplishments. Monroe explained: “We have treated them as independent nations, without their having any substantial pretensions to that rank.” Instead, he recommended “the education of their children, for their instruction in the arts of husbandry [farming], and to provide sustenance for them until they could provide it themselves.” In recommending Congress consider these proposals, Monroe was advocating what would become known as an “assimilationist” approach. Notably absent from his discussion of domestic matters was the Missouri controversy of 1819-1820, in which this territory hoped to become the nation’s 12th slave state. Although the Missouri Compromise of 1820 resolved this crisis, the specter of slavery threatened the delicate compromises that held the young republic together.

Generally regarded as the last of the “founding father” presidents, Monroe had no obvious successor. Although a younger generation eagerly sought the reins of power, none of them possessed the national following or stature of the nation’s first five presidents. Without a revolutionary war to fight or a republican government to build, younger politicians such as Andrew Jackson, Henry Clay and William Crawford would need to find new ways to distinguish themselves. Not surprisingly, the election to succeed Monroe ended inconclusively, with none of the four candidates receiving enough electoral votes to be elected outright. The 1824 election was resolved in the U.S. Congress through a compromise that resulted in John Quincy Adams, the son of a “founding father,” becoming the nation’s 6th president. Over the next decade, a new set of political parties would be established to support a new group of politicians and a new style of politics. As the nation inaugurated Adams on March 4, 1825, they also said goodbye to a president whose career and achievements embodied the nation’s founding era.

The Corrupt Bargain: The Inaugural Address of John Quincy Adams

by C. James Taylor

No person came to the presidency with a better résumé than John Quincy Adams. A native of Massachusetts, like his father, President John Adams, he was a nationalist. He spent most of his adult life in public service, as a senator, a diplomat in several European capitals, and as Secretary of State for almost eight years. In his limited time as a private citizen, he practiced law and held a professorship at Harvard. Adams enjoyed life-long interests in education, science, and the arts. The presidency, the ultimate capstone for most American political careers, proved to be merely an interlude for him. After a brief post-presidential sabbatical, he returned to public life as a congressman.

Adams carefully prepared his inaugural address and sent a copy to the press two days before the event. Late on the eve of his inauguration, he received and corrected the proof copy that would appear in a special edition of the National Intelligencer the next day. According to his diary, he had two sleepless nights before delivering the address. Added to the natural anxiety of the day, his wife was ill. She did not attend the ceremony.

He launched the address with a brief overview of the growth and success of the nation since the ratification of the Constitution. A territory once bounded by the Mississippi River, now “extended from sea to sea.” The new lands were not taken through conquest, but acquired by treaty or purchase. And, rather than subservient colonial status, the people in the new territories participated in the same rights and duties as citizens in the original states. Such was “our condition under a Constitution founded upon the republican principle of equal rights.”

However, he noted that “From evil—physical, moral, and political—it is not our claim to be exempt.” Almost at the moment of its’ founding, the nation suffered “a collision of sentiments and sympathies which kindled all the passions and imbittered the conflict of parties.” Sectional differences and disagreements over the proper response to the French Revolution and subsequent European wars created a twenty-five-year period of political unrest that ended with the War of 1812 and the presidency of James Monroe. Now that political calm seemed to have returned, Adams didn’t use the popular term “Era of Good Feelings” but did recognize that “this baneful weed of party strife was uprooted.” Understanding what had brought the country to this relatively tranquil point, Americans could now “indulge in grateful exultation and cheering hope.”

He reviewed the “promise and performance” of the Monroe administration, and stated that “to pursue their consummation … will embrace the whole sphere of my obligations.” In foreign affairs, he highlighted the peaceful expansion of the national boundaries and recognition of the independence of countries in the southern hemisphere from European colonial control. In the domestic realm he listed reduction of the national debt, reorganization of the postwar army, improvements in the nation’s fortifications and navy, suppression of the African slave trade, and the encouragement of the native American population to evolve from hunters to farmers as accomplishments during Monroe’s two terms. Internal improvements “emphatically urged by him [Monroe] at his inauguration” but still lagging, was the issue Adams embraced in his address. He acknowledged that “some diversity of opinion has prevailed with regard to the powers of Congress for legislation upon subjects of this nature.” He offered “the most respectful deference” to those who held constitutional objections to federally funded internal improvements. But, the benefits of these public works he predicted would mean that “all constitutional objects will ultimately be removed.” He offered Roman roads and aqueducts as examples of the lasting importance of a nation’s investment in internal improvements. As a nationalist, interstate communication and transportation would be an essential element in reducing sectionalism.

He concluded the address recognizing that he owed his position to “the peculiar circumstances of the recent election.” He had finished second to Andrew Jackson in both the popular and electoral votes. Because the vote was divided among four candidates, no one received the necessary majority and the decision fell to the House of Representatives where Adams emerged the victor. In the days leading to the vote in the House, he received warnings and threats of organized opposition and even civil war if Jackson failed to gain the majority. {Diary 1–29-1825}. After the vote, Jackson supporters condemned the apparent collusion between Adams and the fourth-place finisher, Henry Clay, as a “corrupt bargain.” Adams appealed to his auditors that “less possessed of your confidence in advance than any of my predecessors” he needed their “indulgence.”

The address, for the most part, sought recognition of the Americans’ common history and recent apparent tranquility during the Monroe administration. By extolling the nation’s founders, “those illustrious benefactors of their age,” he appealed to all the people. The address was conciliatory and suited to the moment. He would attempt to avoid all sectional and partisan conflict. In this he would fail and a second party system would evolve during his administration. Where he did succeed, at least moderately, was in pushing forward with the internal improvements. However, his commitment to internal improvements further angered the Jacksonians and intensified the growing partisanship.

If Adams had been elected with less controversy, the address certainly would have been more forceful and specific. His December 6, 1825, annual address to Congress is more often cited and recognized as representative of his vision for the nation. Among other things, he called for additional reciprocal agreements with European countries to improve commerce. He noted that the United States had accepted an invitation to a congress of American countries to be held in Central America. He listed advances being made in “surveying, marking and laying out roads” throughout the states and territories, including a continuation of the Cumberland road. In this address, Adams called for a national university, a national astronomical observatory, and government supported exploration of the Northwest coast. The partisan animosity that grew out of the contested election, and caused him to be cautious in his inaugural address, never subsided during his term.

Calm Before the Storm

by Harry L. Watson

Short, vague, and almost inaudible, Andrew Jackson’s First Inaugural Address belied the general’s stormy personality and the tumultuous path that took him to the White House in 1829. Humbly born and mostly self-taught, Jackson came to the presidency with a victorious military record but limited experience in civilian government and a vivid reputation for flouting established laws, procedures, and authorities. His winning presidential campaign had stirred an uproar of lies, distortions, and bitter recriminations, and his administration followed an equally stormy path that featured discharges of experienced civil servants, forced removal of American Indians, a threatened civil war with South Carolina, doom for a national transportation policy, a “Bank War” that destroyed the nation’s largest financial institution, and a revival of cutthroat political partisanship. Nevertheless, Jackson betrayed few signs of these developments when he addressed the nation on March 4, 1829.

A Tennessee lawyer, planter, and frontier land speculator, Jackson became major general of the state militia and won national renown when his forces overwhelmed the British and the Creek Indians in the War of 1812. Postwar clashes with the federal judiciary and civilian Army leadership did nothing to dampen his reputation for decisive, winning action, and paved the way for his first presidential run in 1824. In that contest, Jackson won the most votes against a field of prominent but unexciting figures from James Monroe’s incumbent administration, but he still lacked the required majority. For the second time in the young republic’s history, the House of Representatives had to choose a winner from the finalists.

Their choice had been John Quincy Adams, the second-place finisher and son of former president John Adams. Burdened by a chilly, distant personality, the younger Adams was a Harvard graduate and a former member of its faculty. He had grown up in foreign courts where his father served as a US diplomat, and ran on his distinguished record as the incumbent Secretary of State. By contrast, established leaders scorned Jackson as a mere “military chieftain” with dictatorial potential but no polish, education, or civilian accomplishments. When Adams, the brilliant but privileged insider, seemed to pay for his victory by naming House Speaker Henry Clay as the next Secretary of State, with an inside track to follow him as president, Washington exploded with charges of corruption. Incensed Jackson supporters denounced Washington schemers for violating “the will of the people” and vowed to vindicate democracy with a Jackson-Adams rematch four years later.

In keeping with Jackson’s rough-hewn image, Adams’ elitism, and widespread resentment of the last election’s outcome, Jackson’s 1828 campaign embodied a populist spirit that glorified the ascendancy of ordinary white male Americans over the eighteenth-century Framers. Sadly, however, the campaign also revealed democracy’s ugly side, with scurrilous demagogy on both sides and few policy debates. This time, Jackson reaped the benefits of calculated chaos, routed Adams, and drew massive crowds to Washington to celebrate his triumph. As he faced the throng who gathered to witness his oath-taking before the Capitol’s East Portico, however, Jackson seems to have understood that calm reassurance might yield political benefits, and sought to quiet fears that a frontier strongman might wreck the republic. Behind his bland platitudes, however, signs lurked of coming controversies.

Jackson began by thanking the American people for their trust, pledging his fidelity to their welfare, and offering to explain his guiding principles. First came a promise to respect the Constitution’s limits and the rights of the states. It was a loaded pledge. John Quincy Adams had come to grief by calling for a vast program of federally funded “internal improvements,” or roads, canals, and other expensive public works that defied public opinion and current interpretations of the Constitution. “Were we to slumber in indolence,” he had asked, “or fold up our arms and proclaim to the world that we are palsied by the will of our constituents, would it not be to cast away the bounties of Providence and doom ourselves to perpetual inferiority?” In a single sentence, Adams thus tied a radical expansion of federal powers to fiscal extravagance, intellectual snobbery, disregard of the Constitution, and contempt for the democratic process. Rejoicing at the New Englander’s blunder, Jacksonians gleefully swatted down his dreams and denounced them as extravagant and unconstitutional. Southern congressmen felt these concerns more than most. As recently as 1819 and 1820. Congress had nearly exploded over a proposal to ban slavery from the new state of Missouri, so any move to expand federal powers worried nervous slaveholders. Determined to preserve the brutal system of racial exploitation, one warned frankly, “if Congress can make canals, they can with more propriety emancipate.”

Like other southern leaders, Andrew Jackson was a very large slaveholder himself, and would never tolerate attacks on the system. A promise to respect both the opportunities and limitations of executive power thus became the first substantive promise in his inaugural address, followed by support for states’ rights. There was no hint that Jackson would eventually call himself “the sole representative of the American people,” claiming a right to override Congress and confirming his enemies’ worst fears of his dictatorial impulses.

The new president turned next to fiscal matters. Hoping to extinguish the national debt, he pledged “a strict and faithful economy” in public spending and then turned to the tricky subject of taxation. Ever since its creation, the federal government had depended on tariffs or import taxes as a major source of revenue. In addition, northern states increasingly demanded high tariffs to give their nascent industries a price advantage over foreign competitors. Southerners vehemently opposed such plans, convinced that tariffs would only aid manufacturers at their expense since slavery supposedly prevented an industrial South. Eventually, South Carolina decided that using tariffs to favor one economic sector over another was unconstitutional and attempted to block the policy by “nullifying” or cancelling the federal tariff within its borders. In 1832–33, an infuriated Andrew Jackson would quash this violation of majority rule and his own authority, but he gave no warning at his inauguration. There he only favored protection for military suppliers and vowed to settle all other tariff disagreements through compromise. Jackson took a similar approach to internal improvements, President Adams’ signature issue. He would later brand federal funding for most transportation projects as unconstitutional, but his inaugural address ducked this question and only acknowledged the “high importance” of internal improvements and education, if pursued by constitutional means.

As president, two of Jackson’s most controversial policies were his stances on presidential appointments and on Native Americans, but here too, he revealed little about these plans. Prefiguring modern attacks on the “deep state” and the Washington “swamp,” Jackson had vowed an overhaul of the small federal bureaucracy, which was filled, he believed, with Adams supporters and corrupt incompetents. His address pledged unspecified reforms, which took the form of mass dismissals of suspected Adams supporters. Though Jackson promised replacements with “diligence and talents,” he demanded their unshakeable loyalty as well. The President called this policy “rotation in office” and saw it as a democratic improvement over long-term appointments. Ever since, others have condemned it as the “spoils system.” Despite Jacksonian protests over alleged corruption by Adams and Clay, rewarding party activists with public office and using their help at reelection time became a fixture of nineteenth century politics.

Regarding Indians, Jackson and his frontier supporters passionately coveted the fertile lands still occupied by Native peoples east of the Mississippi. At the time of his inauguration, the president was already planning to seize these territories and force the tribes westward, but he also kept these intentions quiet and only promised a “just and liberal” Indian policy. Jackson told himself that separation would benefit whites and Indians alike, but the death toll on the “Trail of Tears” would tell otherwise. Jackson also said nothing about his plans for the Bank of the United States, the nation’s largest financial institution, but his later campaign to destroy it became the biggest controversy of his administration.

The new president concluded predictably by invoking God’s blessing and the example of his predecessors. His inaugural address had hinted at disputes that lay ahead without revealing his intentions. In time, however, Andrew Jackson’s policies became so controversial that his enemies formed an opposition political party to resist him, calling themselves the Whigs. Organized in the Democratic Party, the President’s supporters fought them relentlessly to the eve of the Civil War, and American politics has featured two-party competition ever since. It became the most enduring legacy of Andrew Jackson’s soothing inaugural address.

Old Hickory: The Second Inaugural Address of Andrew Jackson

by Thomas Coens

On March 4, 1833, shortly after twelve noon, Andrew Jackson took the oath of office for the second time in the Capitol’s Hall of Representatives. The ceremony had been slated for the Capitol’s East Portico, but a recent snowfall and sub-freezing temperatures forced the event indoors. The Hall’s tight quarters limited spectators, but there was room enough to accommodate Jackson’s Cabinet, Supreme Court judges, Senators and congressmen, foreign ministers, and Washington, DC’s mayor, as well as what the newspapers called a sizable “concourse of ladies and citizens.” Standing before the Speaker’s chair and flanked to his left by newly elected vice president, Martin Van Buren, and to his right by his nephew and private secretary Andrew Jackson Donelson, Jackson delivered his second inaugural “in an audible and firm voice.” The address was cheered by the audience, after which Supreme Court Chief Justice John Marshall approached Jackson and administered him the presidential oath.

Jackson began his address by thanking his countrymen for his reelection and the “renewed expression of their confidence in my good intentions,” and concluded with a “fervent prayer to that Almighty Being before whom I now stand, and who has kept us in His hands from the infancy of our Republic to the present day.” In between, Jackson devoted almost the entirety of his second inaugural to outlining, in very general terms, what he considered the “two objects which especially deserve the attention of the people,” namely, “the preservation of the rights of the several States and the integrity of the Union.” On the one hand, Jackson emphasized the importance of safe-guarding the constitutionally protected prerogatives of state governments. The “destruction of our State governments,” Jackson warned, “or the annihilation of their control over the local concerns of the people would lead directly to revolution and anarchy, and finally to despotism and military domination.” At the same time, Jackson encouraged Americans to cherish the federal Union and to give “a liberal support of the General Government in the exercise of its just powers.” “Without union our independence and liberty would never have been achieved,” Jackson reminded Americans, and hollowing out of the authority of the federal government risked economic chaos, constant strife and bickering, civil war, and, ultimately “loss of liberty.”

Perhaps the most notable feature of Jackson’s second inaugural was how short it was. At 1,176 words, only seven inaugural addresses have been shorter, and one of those was Jackson’s first, given in 1829. Virtually everyone who heard or read the address and commented upon it noted its slimness. John Quincy Adams, who was not present at the ceremony but received a first-hand report, described it as “brief and full of smooth professions,” while fellow diarist Philip Hone noted that it was “well done, not too long.” By contemporary as well as modern standards, Old Hickory was a rather infrequent public speaker, and it is not a stretch to suggest that the brevity of Jackson’s two inaugurals was no accident. Despite his reputation as the father of “Jacksonian Democracy,” with all its boisterous electioneering, Jackson rarely appealed to voters in person, and he limited his communications with the public to written exchanges published in newspapers, and, as president, to State Papers and messages to Congress. This was in keeping with the patrician practices of his predecessors, but Jackson’s aversion to public speaking and self-promotion went beyond even theirs. In fact, other than remarks he delivered at an 1833 monument cornerstone laying ceremony honoring George Washington’s mother, Jackson did not once formally address a public audience during his eight years as president.

The other noticeable thing about Jackson’s second inaugural is how lacking it was in specific references to concrete events or policies. Newspapers opposed to Jackson complained, with some justification, that it contained “no allusion to debatable matter,” and was filled with “generalities and non-committals” with which “none will be found to disagree.” It is not true, however, that Jackson’s address had nothing to say about the important issues of the day, even if what he said was stated so obliquely as to require listeners to read between the lines. As with many a presidential inaugural, Jackson’s second addressed contemporary political conflicts without mentioning them by name.

Near the end of his inaugural, Jackson dropped several hints that his reflections on states’ rights and federal power were not to be taken as abstract musings, but as commentary on recent events and his handling of them. In the address’s third to last paragraph, Jackson referred to the “existing crisis” and the “dangers which surround” the country, and he expressed his hope that the nation could pass through them by exercising “forbearance and firmness.” The “crisis” facing the country, as Jackson’s audience would have immediately known, was Nullification. In November 1832, a South Carolina convention, claiming to act in the name of that state’s people, declared void, or “nullified,” two federal laws raising tariff rates on imports, measures the convention believed to be unconstitutional and unfair on the grounds that they made Southerners pay more for imports while getting less for their agricultural exports. The South Carolina convention also warned that the State would secede from the Union if an attempt was made to enforce those laws within South Carolina’s borders. Jackson met South Carolina’s provocation with a fiery December 1832 proclamation denouncing nullification and secession as unconstitutional and reckless. The means to defuse the crisis, however, came from Congress, which during the 1832––33 session passed a so-called “Compromise” tariff law that gradually reduced rates over the coming years until they came down to levels thought to be acceptable to Southerners. Jackson had signed the measure into law only two days earlier, and whether South Carolina would back down—it did, more or less—was on Inauguration Day yet unknown.

Four drafts of Jackson’s second inaugural survive in the Library of Congress’s collection of Jackson Papers, and an examination of those drafts reveals that the decision to address Nullification with kid gloves, or at least indirectly, had been internally debated by Jackson and his aides during the address’s drafting process. Jackson’s first draft, written out in his own hand, reads like a slightly shorter, slightly less eloquent version of the final address. Jackson’s “Kitchen Cabinet” advisor Amos Kendall took Jackson’s first draft and lengthened and revised it. As the former Kentucky newspaper editor was wont to do, Kendall added to Jackson’s draft a fair measure of piquancy and punch. Kendall’s revision castigated nullifiers as “misguided men,” suffering from “madness or delusion,” and had Jackson dramatically vow to “preserve the union of these states although it may cost me my life.” Jackson’s dutifully copied over Kendall’s provocative comments into a third draft, but they were removed in the final draft executed by his nephew and secretary Andrew Jackson Donelson. Who was responsible for doing so is not known; given the rapid and peaceful abatement of the Nullification crisis in the weeks following, it is no doubt best that they were.

Also lurking beneath the generalizations of Jackson’s second inaugural was Old Hickory’s famous “War” against the Bank of the United States. Jackson had won reelection in 1832 over opponent Henry Clay by campaigning under the banner of his 1832 veto of legislation rechartering the Bank of the United States, a semi-private, semi-public institution Jackson felt to be unconstitutional, aristocratic, and dangerous. With his Bank Veto as the unmistakable subtext, Jackson in his second inaugural touted his willingness to “exercise my constitutional powers in arresting measures which may directly or indirectly encroach upon the rights of the States, or tend to consolidate all political power in the General Government.”

Seen this way, Jackson’s second inaugural can be read as a justification of his dual decisions, made during his first term, to wage war against the Bank and against Nullification. The two, each in their own way, violated his middle-of-the-road approach to states’ rights and federal power: the Bank was born of federal overreach and threatened to overawe the States and State-chartered banks; while Nullification took states’ rights too far, diminishing the legitimate powers of the federal government and jeopardizing the very existence of the Union.

It is fair, however, to ask whether this is an accurate description of how Jackson really operated. Did Jackson go after the Bank and after Nullification because of his constitutional scruples, or were constitutional scruples invoked as plausible cover for other, more decisive motivations? Critics of Jackson, both then and in the years since, have caricatured Jackson as someone who “shot from the hip,” and made decisions, not on the basis of political principles, but to indulge personal vendettas and fits of pique. Jackson’s first serious biographer (and not much of a fan), James Parton, famously wrote in 1860 that Jackson was at heart “a fighting man, and little more than a fighting man … [he hated] nullification much, but Calhoun more … the bank much, but Biddle more. He was a thorough-going human fighting-cock.” Documentary evidence, much of it only unearthed in the last few decades by editors of Jackson’s presidential papers, suggests that Parton’s take on Jackson is largely incorrect. Jackson began drafting closely reasoned arguments against the Bank’s constitutionality early in his first term, and he was heavily involved in drafting the parts of his 1832 nullification proclamation that denounced secession. Such evidence does not forbid us from wondering whether Jackson’s constitutional scruples were ultimately good rather than real reasons for his actions, but it is simply not true that Jackson acted impulsively or made important decisions during bouts of rage.

At the same time, it would be a mistake to suggest that Jackson’s middle-of-the-road approach to questions of federal power is an ideological Rosetta Stone capable of explaining all of his actions as president, during either his first or second presidential terms. Jackson, after all, had during his first term allowed the State of Georgia to effectively nullify federal treaties and laws protecting the Cherokees on the grounds that the federal government was powerless to intervene. Conversely, Jackson was not shy about exercising dubious federal powers under the right circumstances, as when he recommended curbing free speech by outlawing the circulation of abolitionist materials in the mail. All of this, however, only goes to show that Jackson’s second inaugural address, like all inaugural addresses, was first and foremost a political document, one that sought to mold public perceptions, and, in doing so, inevitably smoothed away some of the rough edges in Jackson’s record.

The Little Magician: The Inaugural Address of Martin Van Buren

by Michael J. Gerhardt

America’s seventh president, Andrew Jackson, was a hard act to follow, especially for the man who succeeded him, Martin Van Buren. Jackson led the popular vote all three times he ran for the presidency (1824, 1828, 1832). While not all Americans loved Jackson, he had a humble background, was anti-elitist, championed the common man against rapacious big businesses, and was the first president to stand firmly against secession. Stubborn to a fault, Jackson issued a directive in the final year of his presidency that prohibited the use of paper money in the purchase of federal lands. In his first few weeks in office, Van Buren watched helplessly as Jackson’s move provoked foreclosures and bank failures, which led to the nation’s first great depression.

Whereas Jackson manifested the toughness he wished to embody, Van Buren was well known for his wiliness and penchant for compromise. When Jackson reshuffled his cabinet to rid it of those who felt allegiance to his first Vice-President John Calhoun, Van Buren agreed to relinquish his position as Secretary of State in favor of serving as the Minister to Great Britain. But, when Calhoun cast the tie-breaking vote to reject Van Buren’s nomination as Minister to Great Britain, Van Buren instantly became a martyr for Jackson’s cause. Jackson picked him as his running mate in the 1832 election, and Jackson paved the way for Van Buren to win the party’s nomination in 1836 and the ensuing presidential election of 1836.

The scene of Van Buren’s inaugural on March 4, 1837, delighted Jackson: Swearing in his chosen successor was Chief Justice Roger Taney, Jackson’s long-time adviser whom Jackson had helped to secure the post after the Senate had rejected his nominations for Treasury Secretary and Associate Justice on the Court. But while the ceremony was a triumph for Jackson, it was not for Van Buren, who could take pride in becoming the first native-born American to become president but had the challenge on that day both to demonstrate his commitment to Jackson’s policies and popular support and his own toughness to fight, like Jackson, big business, an overreaching federal government, and secession.

Van Buren’s inaugural address demonstrated that he was no Jackson. Whereas Jackson spoke plainly and directly, Van Buren spoke formally and cautiously, ever mindful of the traps he had to avoid ahead. Van Buren had not been formally educated, but he had the presence of a man who overcompensated for his humble beginnings. Looking back on that day, Jackson’s long-time ally, Senator Thomas Hart Benton, aptly observed, “For once, the rising sun was eclipsed by the setting sun.”

The first sentence of Van Buren’s inaugural address gave an indication of where Van Buren was going—nearly eight lines long when put down in writing. He “cheerfully” agreed to “fulfill” the obligation set by his predecessors of delivering an inaugural, a sentiment he took 49 words to express. He went downhill from there, abandoning any pretense of being the verbal pugilist that Jackson was. Instead, he launched into a long disquisition—comprised of 12 of the addresses’ 18 long paragraphs underscoring his humility by retelling the story of America up until that moment. The longest paragraph of the entire address is the 13th, which addressed “the institution of domestic slavery.” Van Buren recounted some of the country’s early history in wrestling with that problem before he explained his “solemn duty” as a candidate to have “declared that if the desire of those of my countrymen who were favorable to my election was gratified ‘I must go into the Presidential chair the inflexible and uncompromising opponent of every attempt on the part of Congress to abolish slavery in the District of Columbia against the wishes of the slaveholding states, and also with a determination equally decided to resist the slightest interference with it in the States where it exists.’” This is Van Buren taking a strong stand: He was more lawyer than politician in trying to soften flashpoints of disagreement by using the least incendiary rhetoric he could to make his points. This kind of talk was classic Van Buren in trying mightily to please his audience while committing himself to a policy unpleasing to many. Van Buren placed these remarks roughly in the middle of his address, thus making it nearly impossible to reassure the very people he wanted to reassure. They wanted bluster and boldness but they got the opposite—calmly worded bromides, long disquisitions of history, and reluctance to showcase his strongest stand.

This paragraph continues to nearly the end of his speech when he finally spoke directly to the audience before him and those reading the address later: “For myself, therefore, I desire to declare that the principle that will govern me in the high duty to which my country calls me is a strict adherence to the letter and spirit of the Constitution as it was designed by those who framed it.” “I shall endeavor,” he added later in the same long paragraph (after recounting the origins of the Constitution), “to preserve, protect, and defend it anxiously referring to its direction in every action. To matters of domestic concernment which it has intrusted to the Federal Government and to such as relate to our intercourse with foreign nations I shall zealously devote myself; beyond those limits I shall never pass.” Van Buren echoed Jackson’s commitment to what has become known as original meaning as the touchstone of constitutional law.

Van Buren was pronouncing how he would govern and interpret the nation’s preeminent governing document, but he was also repeating himself and failing to frame anything memorable in his rhetoric. Van Buren, of course, was entitled as the duly elected president to speak in his own voice, but it was not a voice that convinced anyone he was a man of the people like Jackson. The verbiage confirmed his image as a clever politician that one had to watch carefully to keep in check.

After two long paragraphs about his approach to foreign policy (declaring he had little “discretion” to deviate from Jackson’s “uniform and intelligible” foreign policy), Van Buren arrived at his last two paragraphs. He concluded the first of these with his promise “to bring with me a settled purpose to maintain the institutions of my country, which I trust will atone for the errors I commit.” The more protestations of humility he made, the less tough he sounded and the more like a regular politician whom Jackson’s followers detested. Jacksonians did not want any career politicians but instead a man who shared their experiences and values as common folk. Van Buren had come into the presidency as a career politician; he sounded and looked like one. But, having been out of the country for a year before he became Vice-President in 1836, he was not a familiar face or presence to most Americans, but, through his inaugural, he was reminding everyone that he was exactly what his critics charged—a career politician more interested in helping himself than in helping others, especially those who needed the government to stand with them against the big businesses that were gouging them.

Most of the last paragraph was devoted to reminding Americans he had served under Jackson for many years and was “a daily witness of his exclusive and unsurpassed devotion to his country’s welfare, agreeing with him in sentiments which his countrymen have warmly supported, and permitted to partake largely of his confidence . . .” He praised Jackson further and then the nation before “throw[ing] myself without fear on its justice and its kindness” and looking for guidance to Jackson and the “Divine Being whose strengthening support I humbly solicit . . .”

The address sounded many of the right notes for Van Buren, but it sowed more doubts than confidence that Van Buren could ever be as tough as Jackson in opposing the forces preying on the common people who were his supporters. Van Buren served his country for many years—as a senator, as the attorney general and governor of New York, as Secretary of State, Minister to Great Britain, and now as president. His resume, loyalty to Jackson, and humility could not save him from political disaster when, just weeks after his address, and the nation confronted its first great depression. The crisis required boldness, imagination, and empathy, but Van Buren was not the man who could deliver these when he needed to and lost reelection in 1840.

Old Tippecanoe: The Inaugural Address of William Henry Harrison

by Daniel Walker Howe

The 3rd of March, 1841, was bitter cold in Washington, DC William Henry Harrison, having been chosen Ninth President of the United States in the election of 1840, was now due to take the oath of office and assume its duties. Harrison had been depicted during the campaign as a simple old man, content to read while sipping hard cider in the garden of a log cabin. This image had been created as satire by his Jacksonian Democrat opponents but then preempted by his Whig Party supporters, who found it helped Harrison win over some Jacksonian voters. The incoming President was eager to move away from this humble characterization toward a more presidential one, closer to his own self-image. Accordingly, he had composed a dignified and very elaborate address for his inauguration, only slightly edited by the learned orator Daniel Webster (whom Harrison had already selected to be his Secretary of State).

Defying the cold, the new incumbent refused to wear an overcoat while delivering his lengthy oration, even though, at 68, he was the oldest president inaugurated before 69-year old Ronald Reagan in 1981. The old man (by the standards of the age) caught the fatal chill that led to pneumonia. As President, he, of course, received the best medical care on offer—which, in an era of medical blood-letting, made his condition worse. Harrison’s address remains the longest one ever delivered at a presidential inauguration—heralding, ironically, the shortest term ever served by an American President. Harrison died exactly one month after delivering this speech.

Harrison conceived his inaugural address as a repudiation of the strong presidency that the Democratic Party of Andrew Jackson and his designated heir Martin Van Buren had introduced. Presidential power had been the major issue debated in the campaign of 1840. The Whig Party to which Harrison belonged had taken its name from an English political party that resisted the executive power of the King. Still a major party in 1840, the UK Whigs had been responsible for both reapportioning the House of Commons and freeing the slaves in the British Empire. A prominent feature of the new American Whig Party was the hostile portrayal of Andrew Jackson as a would-be monarch, “King Andrew the First.” Sometimes called the “country party” tradition, such resistance to executive power had been a recurring theme in both colonial and English political tradition during and before the American Revolution. This attitude retained sufficient appeal among the American electorate for the Whigs to invoke it successfully in the election of 1840. Meanwhile, in a variety of locations re-writing their state constitutions at the time, the Whigs consistently favored restricting the executive power of the governors.

The biggest factor in determining the outcome of the election, however, had actually been the Financial Panic of 1839, which the electorate blamed on the incumbent administration, as electorates always do in hard times. Harrison had beaten Van Buren 234 to 60 in the Electoral College. He could look forward to a Congress with comfortable Whig majorities of seven in the Senate and thirty-one in the House. Under the circumstances, one might expect that Harrison would be looking forward to a glorious triumph and exercising relatively unchecked power. In his inaugural address, however, he took an altogether different stance: assuring his audience that he would carefully restrict his own presidential powers, in keeping with his party’s campaign commitment.

Harrison promised “a summary of the principles which will govern me” as President. All too often, in both ancient and modern times, he noted, office-holders neglect promises made before election once they have secured power. (Classical allusions were consistent with the dignified image the speaker wished to present; Harrison had studied classics at Hampton-Sydney College in Virginia before turning to his military career.) The age cherished public speaking as an art form, and Harrison intended to lay his claim to its prestige. Yet the grammatical structure of his oration, with its long and complex sentences, does not seem very well suited to a large audience out of doors. At first it may have seemed to listeners that the incoming President prioritized Constitutional theory over practical matters, but Harrison soon gave his Constitutional interpretation specific relevance. Declaring that he regretted the Constitution had permitted Presidents to run for re-election, Harrison promised at the outset that he himself would not do so. Everyone in the audience would have immediately interpreted this as a reproach directed at both Andrew Jackson and Martin Van Buren, whose attempted re-election Harrison had just defeated.

The speaker immediately turned his attention to another power the Constitution had bestowed on the Federal Chief Executive: to veto acts of Congress. At that time, the veto power seemed much more drastic and unusual than it does to us. None of the first six Presidents had ever invoked it! The veto was closely associated with Andrew Jackson’s decision to use it to nullify Congressional renewal of the Charter of the Second Bank of the United States. Harrison took the position that legislative power belonged to the Houses of Congress, and the Executive Branch should not normally interfere with it. In the final analysis, however, he reluctantly conceded that the existence of a veto power was legitimate to help guard against abuse of the Constitution by Congress.

Harrison next complained about the President’s power to appoint all employees of the federal government. Andrew Jackson had turned this labor force (mostly postal employees in those days) into a huge source of political power by purging employees who were not active members of his party and filling their places with loyal Jacksonian Democrats. No Civil Service then restrained the president’s discretion in appointments. Harrison’s legitimate protest against such abuse of executive power was only gradually implemented during the late decades of the nineteenth century by the creation of the Civil Service. Another of Harrison’s complaints—that Jackson tried to interfere with freedom of the press in order to favor periodicals that supported the Democratic Party—did not identify a specific remedy and did not lead to any particular action.

Harrison expressed disapproval of Congressional attempts to interfere with the governance of the District of Columbia. He was undoubtedly referring to proposals to abolish slavery in the District, although he never mentioned the word slavery. Such proposals often included financial compensation for slave owners, but even so, they were bitterly resented and opposed by slavery’s advocates throughout the South. Harrison had consistently supported slavery during his long service as a governor in the Northwest Territories, and on this issue, he did not draw a distinction between his position and the well-known proslavery stance of Jackson and his Democratic Party. On the subject of relations with the American Indians, however, Harrison did draw such a distinction. Opposition to Jackson’s and Van Buren’s drastic program of “Indian Removal” had been strong among Whigs. Earlier in 1840, Harrison had published a sympathetic history of the northwestern tribes, and in his inaugural address, he called for “liberality and justice” in dealing with “our aboriginal neighbors.”

To summarize and conflate his moral precepts, Harrison deplored political partisanship. “The reign of an intolerant spirit of party amongst a free people seldom fails to result in a dangerous accession to the executive power,” he warned. Clearly, Harrison identified political partisanship with Andrew Jackson and his followers, but not with his own Whig followers. “All the influence that I possess,” President Harrison promised, “Shall be exerted to prevent the formation at least of an Executive party in the halls of the legislative body.” How this principle could have been followed in practice the American people never had a chance to witness. Harrison’s sudden and surprising death left the White House in the control of his Vice President, John Tyler. (Vice presidents succeeding to the presidency upon their predecessor’s death do not have an opportunity to deliver an inaugural address.) Tyler disagreed with the congressional Whigs about re-creating a Bank of the United States and vetoed their efforts to charter one. Tyler would have liked to create a party of his own, or to enlist the Democrats behind him, but never succeeded in either project. From our own point of view, Harrison’s election led into what historians have called “the second party system,” a two-party system of Whigs and Democrats, rather than the no-party system to which Harrison himself had aspired.

The President Without a Party

by Christopher J. Leahy

John Tyler’s accession to the presidency marked the first time in American history that a vice president took over the nation’s highest office because of the death of the incumbent—in this case, William Henry Harrison. Upon Harrison’s passing on Palm Sunday, April 4, 1841, his cabinet dispatched two messengers to Tyler’s home in Williamsburg, Virginia, with instructions to bring the vice president back to Washington, where he could take the reins of the government. Arriving in the capital around 4:00 AM on Tuesday, April 6, Tyler checked into a suite at Brown’s Indian Queen Hotel. Fully aware that Harrison’s death had created a potentially dangerous constitutional crisis, and imbued with a sense of the historical significance of the moment, Tyler took steps to ensure that he established himself as president of the United States. Later that morning, he took the oath of office in the parlor of the hotel and immediately made clear that he was in charge. “I am the President,” he declared, “and I shall be held responsible for my administration.”

Three days later, Tyler took another step to establish himself as chief executive when he delivered what amounted to an inaugural address before a small audience at the Capitol. Not nearly as long as a typical inaugural address, and unaccompanied by the traditional pomp and ceremony of a normal inauguration, Tyler’s remarks focused on three areas—foreign affairs, the federal government’s patronage system, and financial matters—and also included a summary statement of his political principles. Tyler believed that the American people deserved to hear from him and he wanted to lay out some general plans of public policy. He also aimed to reassure the nation that, despite the calamity of Harrison’s death, the government would continue to function smoothly and without interruption.

As he prepared a rough draft of his address, Tyler included a section that renounced his desire to seek a presidential term in his own right in 1844. Before leaving Williamsburg to travel to Washington, he spoke briefly with his neighbor and friend, Nathaniel Beverley Tucker. Tucker, a professor at the nearby College of William and Mary, advised Tyler to assert from the start that he would merely serve out the reminder of Harrison’s term and retire. Tucker recognized that despite Tyler’s nomination and election to the vice presidency as a Whig in November 1840, his long-standing political principles of states’ rights, strict construction of the Constitution, and limited federal power did not comport with the nationalist-oriented ideology of the mainstream of the party. Tucker worried that leading Whigs such as Senator Henry Clay, now in command of a newly-won majority, would seek to dominate Tyler and force him to accept the party’s entire agenda. Moreover, the opposition Democrats might attempt to exploit this potentially difficult relationship between the new president and Congress, which would tear Tyler “in pieces as by wild horses” if he appeared overly ambitious. In Tucker’s view, disclaiming a desire to stand for election in 1844 would allow Tyler to govern while other contenders for the presidency—including Clay—jockeyed for position. Tyler could thus adopt the pose of a disinterested statesman who only had the best interests of the nation at heart.

Tucker underestimated Tyler’s ambition. The statement disavowing a second term did not survive revisions to the address. The new president intended to seek his own term in 1844. In fact, the best way to read the majority of Tyler’s inaugural address is to interpret it as the opening salvo in his own campaign for the White House, though he made no overt statement in the address announcing his intentions. Not content with being remembered only as the man who had replaced William Henry Harrison, Tyler began to lay the groundwork for his campaign mere days after taking office.

The section covering foreign affairs was the most cursory of the address but nevertheless imparted a strong message. Tyler had been briefed by Secretary of State Daniel Webster on the progress of the case against Alexander McLeod, a Canadian who had been indicted for murder and arson by the state of New York for his role in the destruction of the Caroline in December 1837. The Caroline was an American steamer that conveyed supplies to Canadian rebels who were defying British authority in the area around Niagara Falls. McLeod had allegedly aided a contingent of British soldiers who boarded the ship with the intention of putting an end to the on-going insurrection. In the melee that ensued an American named Amos Durfee had been killed—shot through the head with a musket ball. McLeod had bragged of his role in the so-called Caroline affair and faced the death penalty if a jury in New York found him guilty of his alleged crimes. Britain had made clear to the US government that such an outcome could result in war, because, as a Canadian, McLeod was a British subject. Furthermore, Whitehall maintained that McLeod’s actions had been undertaken as a military necessity and with the concurrence of military authorities in Canada. The general statement in Tyler’s inaugural address that asserted his desire to “sedulously cultivate the relations of peace and amity with one and all,” alluded to the tensions between the United States and Britain over McLeod’s fate. Tyler further made clear, however, that “the honor” of his country “shall sustain no blemish” on his watch. What he had done with this statement was adopt a firm posture towards Britain that he hoped would buy him time to work behind the scenes to secure a not-guilty verdict for McLeod in a New York court. With the aid of Webster, he succeeded. Moreover, he and the secretary of state accomplished a tremendous feat in 1842, when they secured the Webster-Ashburton Treaty with Britain, a pact that, among other things, settled a long-standing border dispute between Maine and Canada.

Domestic political circumstances influenced the remainder of Tyler’s inaugural address. He paid lip service to the Whig argument that Democratic Presidents Andrew Jackson and Martin Van Buren had abused the federal patronage, or “spoils system,” by appointing and removing office holders based solely on their partisanship. He decried the practice and even suggested he would be willing to work with the Whig congressional majority to remedy the “evils” inherent in the system.

He did not mean it. In fact, Tyler used his inaugural address to put the Whigs on notice that he would not hesitate to remove appointed officials who sought to advance the party’s agenda at the expense of his administration. He signaled his willingness to act in behalf of his own political interests through patronage if circumstances demanded it. Tyler evidently intended to attempt to build a political base for himself using the presidential power to appoint and remove officeholders. Far from taking the advice of his friend Tucker and declaring he would not seek a term of his own in 1844, the new president was laying the groundwork for his political advancement. And he intended to head the Whigs off if they interfered with his overriding goal of winning the presidency in his own right.

With a similar objective in mind, Tyler also addressed the state of the nation’s finances. The effects of an economic depression known to history as the Panic of 1837 lingered as Tyler assumed the presidency. Indeed, Henry Clay had persuaded President Harrison to call a special session of Congress for the summer of 1841 so that the Whig majority could take steps to alleviate the country’s financial woes. Tyler was not keen on the special session, but recognized astutely that Clay and his comrades intended to repeal President Van Buren’s ineffective Independent Treasury, which had hampered the nation’s currency system, and charter a new national bank as the signature feature of their economic recovery program. Tyler favored repeal of the Independent Treasury, but would not cede control of the process to create an appropriate financial institution to Clay. He asserted his willingness to sign “any constitutional measure” the Congress devised that would provide for the “restoration of a sound circulating medium.”

But therein lay the rub. Tyler proclaimed that he would follow the example of “the fathers of the great republican school”—Jefferson and Madison—as he determined the constitutionality of the bank the Whigs were sure to create during the special session. As president, he retained the veto power and would be the ultimate arbiter of whether such a bank passed constitutional muster. This portion of the address served to remind the American people as well as the Whigs—of his longstanding political principles. Without calling it by name, Tyler returned here to the compact theory of government spelled out in the Kentucky and Virginia Resolutions, authored by those republican fathers in 1798, that he believed properly articulated the “balance” between the federal government and the states. He could not have made any clearer his intention to abide by the states’ rights, strict construction, limited government ideology that had guided him throughout his long career in politics. With this section of the inaugural, he thus set the stage for the inevitable clash with the Whig majority that would result in his banishment from their ranks as he became a president without a party.

The Inaugural Address of James K. Polk

by Walter R. Borneman

The America of the 1840s flexed its expansionist muscles. Railroads spread out from east coast cities. Steamboats plied the Mississippi River and its tributaries. Beyond the Mississippi, the western half of the continent beckoned. To many Americans, coming out of the country’s worst depression to date (the Panic of 1837), the wide-open lands of the West—though partially occupied by Native Americans, Mexican nationals, and British subjects—offered a relief valve and the hope of better times.

Settlers poured into the newly independent Republic of Texas; wagon trains rolled up the Platte River toward the Oregon country; and a few opportunists poked around the Mexican province of California. John Tyler, having become president upon the death of William Henry Harrison in 1841, wanted a term of his own but found little support from anyone.

Expansionist fervor aside, the two leading candidates for their party’s 1844 nominations, Henry Clay of the Whigs and Martin Van Buren of the Democrats, publicly stated that the annexation of Texas favored by Tyler might lead to war with Mexico and should not be undertaken. Andrew Jackson, hero of the battle of New Orleans and occupant of the White House for two tumultuous terms, became furious. Jackson felt betrayed by Van Buren, his vice president whom he had championed to succeed him in 1836.

Jackson summoned another protégé, James K. Polk, a former seven-term congressman, speaker of the U.S. House of Representatives, and governor of Tennessee. Jackson had long coveted Texas, but despite characterizations as a saber rattler, he had never taken affirmative steps to bring it into the union. Now, in the final year of his life, “Old Hickory” lectured Polk that he must win the presidency and accomplish the task.

It took Polk nine ballots and ample political arm-twisting to win the Democratic nomination in Baltimore. Despite the Whigs’ dismissive chant of “Who is James K. Polk?” Polk’s credentials made him one of the most seasoned and informed politicians of the era. A “dark horse” he definitely was not. In part to counter Henry Clay’s one-term pledge, but also to coalesce support among Democratic contenders who could look to their own chances four years hence, Polk pledged to be a one-term president. Whatever his goals, he would accomplish them in four years.

It proved a tight electoral contest. But for 5,000 votes in New York State, Henry Clay would have given the inaugural address that James. K. Polk delivered on March 4, 1845. Clay would have focused on federally funded internal improvements, extended an olive branch toward Mexico and Great Britain in foreign affairs, and, to the extent possible, toned down the drumbeat of westward expansion.

Polk’s vision was more sweeping. According to Polk’s secretary of the navy and would-be biographer, George Bancroft, Polk summarized his inaugural address when he confided to Bancroft “the four great measures” of his administration. First, the joint occupation of Oregon with Great Britain had to be settled; second, the American continent must be rounded out by the acquisition of California from Mexico; third, the protectionist tariff burdening southern states had to be reduced to a revenue basis; and lastly, an independent treasury had to be established.

But what about Texas? Lame duck president John Tyler was as much in favor of acquiring Texas as Andrew Jackson and James K. Polk. After considerable intrigue and political maneuvering, on the last full day of his administration Tyler dispatched a message to all Texans that the United States stood ready and willing to admit the Lone Star Republic into the Union as the twenty-eighth state. Tyler didn’t wait for his successor to make good on Texas.

Rather than being surprised or upset by Tyler’s last-minute act, Polk embraced it as he stepped to the podium to deliver his inaugural address. Even if Texas had not yet assented, the new president left no doubt about his view of its status to the United States. Polk counted the number of states at twenty-eight and noted “two of these”—referring to Florida and Texas—“have taken their position as members…within the last week.”

Before embracing Texas, Polk acknowledged his relative youth and professed to be “honored with this distinguished consideration [the presidency] at an earlier period of life than any of my predecessors.” He also gave strong measure to his model of constitutional government. It would be his “first care” to administer the government in the spirit of the Constitution, and he urged “strict adherence to the clearly granted powers” and abstention from the exercise of any “doubtful or unauthorized implied powers.”

If there were those who viewed him as a southerner first, Polk left no doubt that he was cut from Old Hickory’s cloth. “Every lover of his country must shudder at the thought of the possibility of its dissolution,” the Young Hickory proclaimed, “and will be ready to adopt the patriotic sentiment, ‘Our Federal Union—it must be preserved.’”

Polk further declared, “All citizens, whether native or adopted, are placed upon terms of precise equality. All are entitled to equal rights and equal protection.” Yet, in espousing this Jacksonian triumph of the common man, Polk failed to count the slaves he owned among that number.

Indeed, Polk defended the institution of slavery without mentioning it by name. “It is a source of deep regret,” Polk continued, “that in some sections of our country misguided persons have occasionally indulged in schemes and agitations whose object is the destruction of domestic institutions existing in other sections—institutions which existed at the adoption of the Constitution and were recognized and protected by it.”

Polk’s other domestic views were consistent with his “four great measures” and the planks of the Democratic Platform. “We need no national banks,” he said, or federal involvement in internal improvements. And almost verbatim, Polk repeated the careful wording of his tariff letter during the campaign—“a tariff for revenue” with just enough incidental protection to appease the North.

The second half of Polk’s inaugural was devoted to foreign affairs, expansionist affairs, one concludes. Even as the Constitution did not “force reform on the States” in Polk’s view, it had entrusted “the exclusive management of our foreign affairs” to the federal government. His prior words about implied powers aside, Polk would make the most of it.

He espoused long-stated but dubious annexationist views that Texas had once been “a part of our country.” It had been “unwisely ceded away to a foreign power,” but was now independent and had the sovereign right to become a state. Congratulating neither Tyler nor Congress, Polk instead chose to congratulate “my country” that Texas was finally on the road to reunion.

Polk went on to warn that the question of annexation belonged exclusively between the United States and Texas. It was not the concern of Great Britain or France, and it was certainly not the concern of Mexico. Polk asserted that he would act just as dutifully against Great Britain to maintain the right of the United States to the whole of Oregon as he would against Mexico vis-a-vis Texas.

With the British ambassador in the crowd, Polk repeated the pledge of the Democratic platform: “Our title to the country of the Oregon is ‘clear and unquestionable,’ and already are our people preparing to perfect that title by occupying it with their wives and children.” This was no military operation, Polk maintained, but “the peaceful triumphs of the industry of our emigrants.” And to us, the president concluded, “belongs the duty of protecting them adequately wherever they may be upon our soil.”

With that, cannon thundered and the rain-soaked crowd escorted the Polks down Pennsylvania Avenue to a reception at the White House. James was forty-nine, the youngest person yet to assume the presidency and a full decade younger than the average age of his predecessors. His wife, Sarah, was forty-one. Together they made a striking and energetic couple who signaled the passing of the torch to the next generation in a way that would not again reverberate so sharply until 1961.

James K. Polk did not hesitate in the coming four years to expand the powers of the presidency—particularly infringing on Congress’s right to declare war—to extend the Texas border, push the British out of Oregon, and wrestle California and what became the states of the American Southwest from Mexico. He accomplished his goals and died within months of completing his one term.

The Inaugural Address of Zachary Taylor

by Michael F. Holt

Zachary Taylor’s platitude-filled inaugural address was one of the shortest by any president in American history. His personal background largely accounts for its brevity and its patriotic paeans. But the few concrete items also reflect the campaign run for him before and after the Whig party’s national convention nominated him in June 1848 as well as the major issues that shaped that election.

The first sentence of Taylor’s address suggests that he considered it a necessary but unwelcome obligation. The inaugural may well have been the first public speech he ever had to make, and he kept it short. Taylor was not a politician. He had never sought or held a civilian public office, attended a party meeting, or even voted prior to November 1848. Rather he was a career army officer who commanded the American troops in northern Mexico during the first year of the Mexican-American War. The seemingly miraculous victory of his heavily out-numbered army at Buena Vista in February 1847 injected him into the presidential race. His fame and popularity simply exploded as news of his triumph spread eastward from the Mississippi Valley to the Atlantic coast, and by May 1847 savvy politicos predicted that he was certain to be the next president.

His early backers, like Taylor himself, presented him not as a Whig, but as a “No Party” or “People’s” candidate who would not be beholden to any party’s principles if elected president. This apparent contempt for traditional Whig programs and Taylor’s willingness before and even after Whigs nominated him to accept non-Whig nominations outraged established Whig leaders who vowed they would never support anyone but an identifiable Whig.

Party regulars’ hostility to Taylor forced him and his most trusted advisors to compose two public letters attesting to his Whig credentials, one in April six weeks before the Whigs’ national convention and one in September, six weeks before election day. Known as the Allison letters, they accurately previewed the inaugural address he gave in March 1849. Then, too, he tried to reassure suspicious Whigs that he deserved their trust. In the first Allison letter, Taylor identified himself as “a Whig but not an ultra Whig” even while adding his intention “to act independent of party domination” if elected. Then came a muted pledge of Whig allegiance. From the start of the Mexican War under Democratic President James K. Polk, Whigs blasted it as an unconscionable act of aggression aimed at grabbing land from a weak neighbor. In the first Allison letter, therefore, Taylor condemned aggressive wars of conquest and called for magnanimity toward the defeated Mexicans. This language augured Taylor’s words about foreign policy in his inaugural. His promise to “exhaust every resort of honorable diplomacy before appealing to arms,” was a thinly concealed shaft at Polk’s actions inciting the Mexican War. This was straight Whig doctrine.

Even more important, in the first and second Allison letters, just as in his inaugural address, Taylor embraced the fundamental Whig principle that it was Congress’s duty, not the President’s, to set domestic policies regarding tariffs, internal improvements, currency, and the like and that he would never veto congressional legislation unless it were clearly unconstitutional. This idea of the supremacy of Congress over the executive branch had been the founding rationale for the Whig party when it organized against Andrew Jackson in the 1830s.

Yet when Taylor said in his inaugural address that “I shall look with confidence to the enlightened patriotism of that body [Congress] to adopt such measures of conciliation as may harmonize conflicting interests and tend to perpetuate that Union which should be the paramount object of our hopes and affections,” he referred to far more than the proper relationship between the executive and legislative branches. Instead, he pointed obliquely to the sectional quarrel over slavery expansion that had dominated the election of 1848 and that remained unsettled as of March 1849. By the fall of 1847, in fact, Taylor had privately written that this escalating sectional conflict over slavery’s possible extension was the gravest threat to the Union since the adoption of the Constitution. His inaugural words about perpetuating the Union were not mere platitudes. To this old soldier, they were heartfelt, as his subsequent actions as president emphatically made clear.

From the moment the war started in May 1846, Northerners, many of them Whigs, denounced it as a Democratic plot to seize Mexican land so that Southerners could extend slavery west of Texas. In part to refute that charge, in August 1846 a Pennsylvania Democrat introduced an amendment to a bill in the House of Representatives that would bar slavery from any land taken from Mexico as a result of the war. This so-called Wilmot Proviso passed the House, where free-state members outnumbered slave state members, on a strict sectional vote. Northerners supported it. Southerners vehemently opposed it because it denied slaveholders the right to enter national territories on an equal basis with northern non-slaveholders. The amended bill died in the Senate, and the Wilmot Proviso never passed Congress. But it continually came to a vote in subsequent sessions of Congress, always polarizing the northern and southern members of both the Whig and Democratic parties against each other. The longer it did so, the more tempers frayed. By mid-1847 northern state legislatures were instructing their United States Senators to impose the Proviso on any land taken from Mexico while growing numbers of southern state legislatures threatened to secede from the Union should the Proviso ever be enacted into law. This was the crisis that so disturbed Taylor a year before his election.

To restore unity across sectional lines in 1847, both Whigs and Democrats sought alternative policies to the Proviso for dealing with the slavery extension issue. Democrats did so with a formula called popular sovereignty. This called for Congress to forego any action concerning slavery in territories and instead allow the actual settlers in them to decide whether to admit or prohibit slavery. A major proponent of this formula, Michigan Senator Lewis Cass was the Democratic presidential candidate in 1848, and in that campaign he pledged that he would veto the Proviso should it ever pass Congress. Throughout 1847, when the acquisition of Mexican territory was still hypothetical, northern and southern Whigs united behind an insistence that no territory whatsoever be seized from Mexico. Ratification of the Treaty of Guadalupe-Hidalgo and with it the huge Mexican Cession in March 1848 ended that dodge. Now Whigs had to face their party’s sectional polarization over slavery extension head on.

That fact mightily influenced Taylor’s nomination even while making it more controversial. On the one hand, the loss of the antiwar, anti-expansion issues while Democrats could claim credit for almost doubling the size of the country convinced a majority of Whigs at their national convention that the party needed to run a military hero to have any chance of winning the election. On the other hand, it deepened the hostility to Taylor by Northerners who loathed the prospect of slavery’s further western extension. It was not just that Taylor gave no public support to northern Whigs’ demand that slavery be prohibited from the Mexican Cession by congressional law. A resident of Baton Rouge, Louisiana, Taylor owned over a hundred slaves who worked plantations in Louisiana and Mississippi. To most northern Whigs this fact made Taylor seem a certain loser in their states. Hence, his eventual nomination appalled them.

Whigs’ selection of a large slaveholder and Democrats’ nomination of a man who pledged to veto the Proviso prompted the most fervent antislavery men in both parties to bolt to a new Free Soil party that would capture 14 percent of the North’s popular vote in 1848. Eliminating the rationale for this new party, one of the “conflicting interests” he mentioned, was thus one of the achievements Taylor hinted at in his inaugural address.

In the 1848 campaign Whigs brazenly ran a two-faced campaign. In the South they promised that Taylor as a slaveholder and fellow Southerner would never allow the insulting Wilmot Proviso to become law. In the North, in contrast, Whig campaigners seized on Taylor’s pledge not to veto congressional legislation. The best way to stop slavery’s extension they avowed, much to the frustration of Free Soil campaigners, was to elect a northern Whig majority to Congress. They would pass the Proviso and Taylor, quite unlike Lewis Cass, would sign it into law.

Whigs’ doubled-faced tactic worked in 1848. Taylor carried seven of fifteen northern states and eight of fifteen slave states. Free Soil incursions into both major parties’ ranks varied from state to state. They helped Whigs carry New York while giving Ohio to Cass. But the dodge worked only because Congress had as yet failed to do anything about organizing territories in the newly acquired Mexican Cession upon which Congress might impose the Proviso. Nor was Congress able to do so in the short session between Taylor’s election and his inauguration even though Whigs were now desperate to spare Taylor from having to make a decision that would give the lie to what Whig campaigners in one section or the other had promised he would do.

Although Taylor had told a confidant that he would sign the Proviso should Congress ever enact it, few people knew what he intended to do when he delivered his brief inaugural address. Despite his professed confidence about Congress’s ability to find a mutually satisfactory solution for slavery extension, he and his administration quickly decided to bypass Congress altogether by avoiding any formal organization of territorial governments upon which Congress might act. Instead, they tried have California and New Mexico immediately enter the Union as states without any territorial phase whatsoever. This solution, he promised in another rare public speech, would render any need for a Free Soil party moot. However sensible it was, the plan failed. But Taylor had died on July 9, 1850 before Congress replaced it with the famous Compromise of 1850 for the Mexican Cession.

The Last Whig: Millard Fillmore’s Announcement to Congress of the Death of President Taylor

by Claude Welch

Rankings of American Presidents generally place Millard Fillmore towards the bottom. Critics consider his approval of the Compromise of 1850 a major flaw. In fairness to him, we must recognize the delicate balance struck in this legislation. The most infamous part, the Fugitive Slave Act, formed part of a broader package of five bills. The Compromise temporarily defused a political confrontation between slave and free states that had existed since the republic’s establishment. On the positive side, various bills in the Compromise abolished slavery in the District of Columbia. California, Texas, and other states or territories acquired during the Mexican–American War became full-fledged states. Arguably, four positive actions, one negative.

Fillmore, a largely self-educated individual, prized cautious, lawyerly, and above all, constitutionally sanctioned actions. He had assumed the presidency upon the death of his successor, Zachary Taylor. On July 10, 1850, Fillmore delivered a short address acknowledging Taylor, which offered no insight into how he would govern as president. This became clearer nearly half a year later when he delivered his first major address to Congress on December 2, 1850 (quoted throughout). Fillmore, the 13th President, remained in the Presidency for two years and 37 days.

A political chasm existed between Taylor and Fillmore, Fillmore having been selected largely for geographic balance. Neither gave remarks filled with quotable material, unlike other presidents. Fillmore’s speech was ponderous, filled with long, complex sentences. Consider the following. “I trust, therefore, that it may not be deemed inappropriate if I avail myself of this opportunity of the reassembling of Congress to make known my sentiments in a general manner in regard to the policy which ought to be pursued by the Government both in its intercourse with foreign nations and its management and administration of internal affairs.”

Fillmore broke with the expansionist policies of James K. Polk, saying, “We make no wars to promote or to prevent successions to thrones, to maintain any theory of a balance of power, or to suppress the actual government which any country chooses to establish for itself.” In his first annual address to Congress, Fillmore also praised the treaty reached by the United States with Great Britain, “facilitating and protecting the construction of a ship canal between the Atlantic and Pacific oceans and for other purposes.” No, the passageway would not be located across the Isthmus of Panama, but across Nicaragua. On the other hand, Fillmore subsequently authorized Commodore Matthew Perry’s 1853 expedition to Japan, a clear exercise in gunboat diplomacy.

The 13th President personally opposed slavery. However, as Chief Executive, he believed himself bound to support the “peculiar institution.” As he stated, “In our domestic policy the Constitution will be my guide, and in questions of doubt I shall look for its interpretation to the judicial decisions of that tribunal which was established to expound it and to the usage of the Government, sanctioned by the acquiescence of the country.” Further, Fillmore pledged to “deprecate useless irritation among the several members of the Union and all reproach and crimination tending to alienate one portion of the country from another.” Implicitly, he showed himself willing to remain within the broad tradition demonstrated by the renowned Whig leader Daniel Webster. According to Fillmore, “without law there can be no real practical liberty; that when law is trampled under foot tyranny rules, whether it appears in the form of a military despotism or of popular violence.”

The infamous Dred Scott decision followed seven years later.

Fillmore was the last of the Whig Presidents, having been preceded by the aforementioned Harrison and Zachary Taylor. In terms of internal policy, the Whigs favored high tariffs to protect nascent domestic industries. As Fillmore stated, “All experience has demonstrated the wisdom and policy of raising a large portion of revenue for the support of Government from duties on goods imported. The power to lay these duties is unquestionable, and its chief object, of course, is to replenish the Treasury. But if in doing this an incidental advantage may be gained by encouraging the industry of our own citizens, it is our duty to avail ourselves of that advantage.”

Fillmore foreshadowed the 1862 creation of the Department of Agriculture, proposing “the establishment of an agricultural bureau, to be charged with the duty of giving to this leading branch of American industry the encouragement which it so well deserves.” He also recommended, “the employment of a competent mineralogist and chemist … [who would analyze] their respective elements and properties and their adaptation to useful purposes … and examine and report upon the qualities of different soils and the manures best calculated to improve their productiveness.” Fillmore further echoed Taylor’s 1848 recommendation to open “’a line of communication, the best and most expeditious of which the nature of the country will admit,’ between the Valley of the Mississippi and the Pacific.”

The Mexican-American war resulted in the incorporation of numerous Native Americans. Fillmore alluded to this dramatic change thus: “Texas and New Mexico are surrounded by powerful tribes of Indians, who are a source of constant terror and annoyance to the inhabitants. Separating into small predatory bands, and always mounted, they overrun the country, devastating farms, destroying crops, driving off whole herds of cattle, and occasionally murdering the inhabitants or carrying them into captivity.”

Internationally, Fillmore stressed facilitating imports of guano! “Peruvian guano has become so desirable an article to the agricultural interest of the United States that it is the duty of the Government to employ all the means properly in its power for the purpose of causing that article to be imported into the country at a reasonable price.” He called upon Spain and Great Britain to settle their boundary dispute in Hispaniola, which he called ‘St. Domingo’. “The proximity of that island to the United States and the delicate questions involved in the existing controversy there render it desirable that it should be permanently and speedily adjusted.”

Fillmore concluded his address with a final plea for reason. In his view. “It was hardly to have been expected that the series of measures passed at your last session with the view of healing the sectional differences which had sprung from the slavery and territorial questions should at once have realized their beneficent purpose. All mutual concession in the nature of a compromise must necessarily be unwelcome to men of extreme opinions.”

What lessons can one draw from this brief analysis of a single speech?

First, Fillmore saw his role as Chief Executive as one constrained by the Constitution, Acts of Congress, and major judicial decisions. As a largely self-educated lawyer who had received little formal schooling, he firmly defended the constraints imposed by the other branches of government.

Fillmore likewise did not stray from Whig orthodoxy. His support for significant domestic infrastructure improvements and industrial development, funded by tariff walls, remained constant. He thirdly viewed America's international role as largely an outgrowth of domestic policies, as witness the stress upon guano imports or his concern about Hispaniola, where boundary disputes threatened U.S. interests.

Finally, and most significant in the view of later historians, Fillmore “failed” largely due to one of the five bills contained in the Compromise of 1850. I would advance a contrary view, despite the fact that millions of slaves continued to experience the travails of the “peculiar institution” for several years more. During the interim between the Compromise and the outburst of the Civil War, the North’s industrial strength and population dominance grew. It entered the conflict even stronger than its Confederate adversary. Did the objective—additional years of peace—justify the means? That is a question readers of this chapter, and other parts of the publication, must weigh for every President. What they said in their inaugural addresses should be judged in terms of the words of the various Chief Executives relative to their subsequent records and to the verdict rendered later by history.

Handsome Frank: The Inaugural Address of Franklin Pierce

by Peter A. Wallner

After a campaign of mutual innuendo and charges by both candidates, on November 2, 1852, Franklin Pierce was elected 14th President of the United States by a landslide. Pierce won 21 of the 27 states that then constituted the Union. His opponent was the Whig candidate, Winfield Scott, who would serve as the Commander of the Army throughout Pierce’s term despite not getting along with Pierce’s choice for Secretary of War, Jefferson Davis. Despite this fact, he was able to choose a Cabinet, led by Davis and Secretary of State William L. Marcy, which stayed together for the next four years—the first time in U.S. history that a Cabinet remained intact for an entire presidential term, with no resignations. As Pierce’s secretary, Sidney Webster, wrote, “The elements of that Cabinet were such that, if left without a controlling chief, it would have broken asunder in a week.” What kept them together was their mutual respect, even fondness, for Pierce.

Less than two months prior to the inauguration, the event was marred by the death of the Pierce's only surviving child, 11-year-old Benny, in a train wreck. Pierce was unable to choose his Cabinet until after the funeral, and Jane Piece, who was always unstable mentally, was totally unable to resolve his death with her very fundamentalist religious views. Jane’s cousin wrote at the time, “you cannot but tremble for one who is always so depressed and now has such bitter cause.” There was concern that Jane would not rally to become a comfort to her husband in time for the inauguration, and, in fact, this was the case. The inaugural ball was canceled. She stayed in Baltimore with friends, and on March 2, her husband traveled to the city to read Jane his inaugural address. She seemed completely uninterested in the address and insisted that politics be forgotten for the moment. Instead, he left abruptly, and Jane was unable to share her feelings with him and to give him a lock of his son’s hair, which she hoped he would keep near him on Inauguration Day.

Inauguration Day was a cold, raw March day with light snow falling as Pierce prepared for the inaugural ceremonies. The procession to the Capitol began at City Hall and marched to Willard’s Hotel, where President Fillmore joined the parade in an open carriage. It was noon when Pierce left the hotel and climbed into the carriage next to the President. The two men rode down Pennsylvania Avenue, in the barouche, accompanied by Senators Bright and Hamlin. All the way down the Avenue, Pierce stood up in the carriage bare-headed and waved to the people gathered on both sides. There were an estimated 70,000 visitors in the city for the inauguration. The Vice-president elect, William Rufus DeVane King, was in Cuba in a vain attempt to restore his health; he suffered from tuberculosis and would die shortly after the inauguration. The preliminary ceremony of the swearing-in of the vice president was dispensed with, and Senator Bright led Pierce from the chamber to the east front of the Capitol, where he took the oath of office from Chief Justice Roger B. Taney. Pierce also broke precedent by affirming rather than swearing to uphold the Constitution.

The nation’s youngest President to that time turned and faced the crowd of some 15,000 who stood before him. In the confident manner of the “easy lawyer and speaker,” he began to address the crowd. Pierce spoke for the next 30 minutes entirely from memory. Though he kept the document by his side, he delivered his inaugural address from memory. He began with a statement he had added to the speech that morning, speaking of the recent death of his son: “My Countrymen. It is a relief to feel that no heart but my own can know the personal regret and bitter sorrow over which I have been borne to a position so suitable for others rather than desirable for myself.” The address was an eloquent summary of all that Jacksonian Democracy stood for. While it did not propose a specific agenda, the speech was generally praised by the press. The politically neutral Baltimore Sun wrote, “No similar document, that we remember, met with such general favor…” On reading the speech, H. R. French, a judge in New Hampshire, wrote, “The inaugural is first rate and pleases all parties. He has a wonderful gift of propriety in all his acts, and words, and writing. I should have written about such address as that had I been President.”

Fillmore accompanied the new president back to the White House and then took his leave. The new president received guests throughout the rest of the day. He stood for hours shaking hands with all comers before finally making his way upstairs to the family quarters. Since the Fillmore’s had not moved out completely, due to the illness of Mrs. Fillmore, the new president had to make due by assigning one room to his secretary, Sidney Webster, and retired to the other room.

The Inaugural Address of James Buchanan

by Jean H. Baker

Promptly at noon on the pleasant sunny day of March 4, 1857, James Buchanan, soon to take the oath of office as the 15th president of the United States, began his inaugural address to a distinguished audience of congressmen, judges, diplomats and residents of the District of Columbia. At sixty-five he was older than any of his predecessors and his snow-white hair, stooped shoulders and reedy voice suggested as much. Few actually heard what Buchanan had to say in an address of nearly 3,000 words; rather it would reach Americans in its printed version published in the nation’s newspapers. Buchanan was not feeling well. Since his arrival in Washington he had been suffering from the dysentery associated with the National Hotel where he was staying before moving into the White House. Still, the moment was a time of personal affirmation. After a long career in public service he had reached the pinnacle of his ambitions.

Born in Franklin County, Pennsylvania in 1791, Buchanan had begun his career in the Pennsylvania state legislature. He had served five terms in the U.S. Congress from 1821–1831. In 1834 he had been elected to the U.S. Senate where he served two terms. In addition, he had foreign policy experience, having served as U.S. minister to Russia and more recently, to the Court of St. James in Great Britain. And he had served in James Polk’s cabinet as secretary of state. There was no one in the United States who could boast of such a distinguished public career.

A loyal Democrat, Buchanan was popular in the South for his positions against the Republicans, the newly formed party whom he considered agitators. He had often taken the side of the South on issues relating to slavery. In historical terms he represented a doughface, that is, a northern man who supported southern interests especially as they related to slavery. Some Americans called him “Old Public Functionary,” but his service gave him confidence that he could solve the existential threat to the United States of what to do about slavery in the territories.

Buchanan began his address with what became staples for American inaugural addresses. He repeated the presidential oath of office; he invoked the God’s help and a fervent exponent of American exceptionalism, he proclaimed the United States the nation with the greatest “capacity of man for self-government.” In an unusual aside he promised he would not run again, though no one expected him to.

After these platitudes Buchanan addressed the issue of slavery in the territories west of Missouri and Iowa, an area known as Kansas and Nebraska that awaited organization. In 1854 new legislation supported by Illinois Senator Stephen Douglas upended the previous arrangement in the Missouri Compromise that banned slavery in the region. Instead the Kansas-Nebraska Act introduced the concept of popular sovereignty; the people, not Congress, should decide about slavery through their representatives in the territorial legislature.

Buchanan had been in London when the controversial Kansas-Nebraska Act accelerated the process of party decay and led to the formation of the Republican party. Despite northern opposition, Buchanan now saluted the arrangement as “a happy conception,” an acknowledgment of the self-government and the will of the majority that he saw as essential aspects of American greatness. In his address he took the southern position that Congress could not prohibit slavery during the territorial phase of preparation for statehood. Only when citizens were drafting a constitution could slavery be prohibited by their votes. In any case Buchanan insisted that the Supreme Court would settle this issue and “… to their decision I shall cheerfully submit.”

Buchanan referred here to the Dred Scott case which after years had reached the Supreme Court. What he did not say is that he already knew its outcome. In fact he had helped frame the decision. In an act of extraordinary impropriety as president-elect, Buchanan had put pressure on his friend, Justice Robert Grier of Pennsylvania, to join with the southern judges to embrace a broad ranging judicial decision that would end controversies over the extension of slavery into the western territories.

Two days after Buchanan’s inauguration the U.S. Supreme Court in Dred Scott v. Sanford ruled that Blacks had no rights of federal citizenship and that the Missouri compromise by prohibiting slavery in a part of national territory was unconstitutional. Slavery was nationalized; the newly emerging Republican party’s most important platform was overturned. Buchanan’s intervention had played a significant role in this accommodation to southern interests.

From Buchanan’s point of view the decision emboldened him to believe that he would be the chief executive who put to rest “this agitation”: “May we not, then, hope that the long agitation on this subject is approaching its end, and that the geographical parties [by which he meant the Republicans] to which it has given birth … will speedily become extinct?” Having dealt with the most divisive issue of his time in four paragraphs, Buchanan moved on to other matters in the rest of his speech. But as president he soon learned that the Dred Scott decision rather than creating the sectional harmony he anticipated had only deepened the sectional divide in the nation. Kansas became a flash point, and with little sensitivity to northern positions, Buchanan’s prosouthern handling of its governance doomed his presidency.

Having dispensed with the issue of slavery in the territories, Buchanan next celebrated the familiar principles of midcentury rhetoric—the Constitution and Union. The nation’s economic success came from its large free trading area “conducted on railroads and canals, on noble rivers and arms of the sea which bind together the North and the South, the East and West, …” So successful was this financial union that there was a surplus in the U.S. Treasury that the president-elect proposed could be used to pay down the public debt and shore up the U.S. Navy as well as the nation’s seacoast defenses. Among the blessings of America, he asserted, was its vast inheritance of public lands. In an obvious slap at the rival nativist political party, the Know Nothings or American party, Buchanan saluted the contributions of “those exiles from foreign shores … who have done so much to promote the growth and prosperity of the nation” by settling on western lands.

As a self-avowed strict constitutionalist Buchanan nevertheless promoted the importance of a military road across the territories to the Pacific. And he spent as much of his speech on justifying such an extension of constitutional authority as he had on the issue of slavery in the territories. In fact during his presidency he would have little time or energy to promote such a road.

Finally, drawing on his experience as a minister abroad, Buchanan offered his thoughts on diplomacy. It should be “frank and direct” and conducted in a spirit of “Christian benevolence,” avoiding the entangling alliances that President Washington had warned about. In the final paragraph of his inaugural address Buchanan offered an astounding review of previous American foreign policy. Americans, he said, had never extended their control over the continent by force. Rather their territorial expansion had come through “fair purchase.” He did not consider any dispossession of the Native Americans, and as for the recent acquisitions in Mexico, they had come through purchase in a peace treaty.

After this James Buchanan took the oath of office. His inaugural address had included some boiler plate concerns of the Democratic party, such as strict construction of the Constitution and support of immigration and territorial expansion. But his address also previewed a split in the party as Buchanan embraced southern interests in the matter of slavery in the territories. Expecting that the courts had solved the issue, he expected his presidency to deal with other matters. But his inaugural forecast proved incorrect as the United States drifted toward civil war, in part because as president James Buchanan failed to consider the legitimate interests of the North.

The First Inaugural Address of Abraham Lincoln

by David S. Reynolds

Abraham Lincoln delivered his first inaugural address during the worst crisis in American history. Between November 6, 1860, when Lincoln won the presidency in a four-man race, and March 4, 1861, when he gave the inaugural address, seven Southern states seceded from the Union institution and formed what they called a separate nation, the Confederate States of America, with its own constitution, president, and legislature. The inaugural address, Lincoln knew, must be very cautiously worded. It must affirm the federal government’s resolve to save the Union without pushing the South so hard that reunion became impossible.

In the inaugural address, Lincoln repeated several points he had made in previous speeches: secession was impossible, because a minority cannot overrule the majority; the North would not invade the South without provocation; his administration would leave slavery alone where it existed and would enforce the Fugitive Slave Act as long as the suspected runaways received due process.

Lincoln’s answer to Southerners who used states’ rights to defend secession was that there is a “universal law,” or “organic law,” that is “the fundamental law of all national governments.”

No nation, he pointed out, was formed with its own destruction in mind. Perpetuity was the goal of any nation. “It is safe to assert,” he said, “that no government proper, ever had a provision in its organic law for its own termination.” In America, Lincoln said, national consolidation originated with the Articles of Association (1774), was made perpetual by the Declaration of Independence (1776) and the Articles of Confederation (1781), and then was codified by the Constitution (1787). The Constitution proclaimed that the aim of the people of the United States was “to form a more perfect union.” Secession, which creates a Union that is “less perfect than before” was thus “absurd.”

While emphasizing the broader law of nations, Lincoln in the inaugural did not lose sight of the moral law that motivated him and other antislavery reformers. He said, “One section [of the nation] believes slavery is right, and ought to be extended, while the other believes it is wrong, and ought not to be extended.”

To subvert the South’s position, he deployed clever rhetorical weapons. “Physically speaking,” he said, “we cannot separate. We cannot remove our respective sections from each other, nor build an impassable wall between them.” The continent—the very earth itself—bound the parts of the nation together. Separation violated the law of nature.

He fused religion with democracy: “If the Almighty Ruler of nations, with his eternal truth and justice, be on our side, or on yours, that truth and that justice will surely prevail, by the judgment of this great tribunal, the American people.” The North and the South, he was saying, each believed that its view was supported by God. Which side was correct must be finally decided by the “great tribunal”: the people. In the 1860 election, the people had decided against slavery. In democratic America, the people’s judgment was equivalent to God’s judgment.

Lincoln named two great dangers to the nation: despotism and anarchy. Despotism would result from an overbearing federal government that ignored the constitutional rights of states or individuals. Anarchy, on the other hand, resulted from secession, or an overemphasis of states’ rights. “Plainly,” Lincoln declared, “the central idea of secession, is the essence of anarchy.” If a group of states separates from the Union, why cannot one or two states, by the same principle, separate from the newly formed confederacy? Other divisions would follow. Centrifugalism would reign.

A respect for majority rule, Lincoln argued, can hold the sections of the nation together. “Whoever rejects it,” he declared, “does, of necessity, fly to anarchy or despotism.”

Lincoln had worked on the address for several weeks prior to March 4 and had distributed it among friends for their comments. Two, Orville Browning and William Seward, softened his tone. Browning thought Lincoln’s declared intention to “reclaim” US forts taken over by the rebels made the federal government sound too aggressive. Lincoln removed the word, saying, more mildly, that the federal power would be used “to hold, occupy, and possess the property, and places belonging to the government, and to collect the duties and imposts.” Seward suggested thirty-three changes, twenty-seven of which Lincoln accepted, some in modified form. By far the most important was Seward’s suggestion to replace the militant closing line of the original, in which Lincoln left the question of “peace, or a sword” up to the South, with a charitable final paragraph that, in Lincoln’s reworking, became one of the most memorable passages in American oratory.

Here is Seward’s version of the paragraph:

I close. We are not we must not be aliens or enemies but [“countrym” deleted] fellow countrymen and brethren. Although passion has strained our bonds of affection too hardly they must not [“be broken they will not” deleted], I am sure they will not be broken. The mystic chords which proceeding from [“every ba” deleted] so many battle fields and [“patriot” deleted] so many patriot graves [“bind” deleted] pass through all the hearts and [“hearths” deleted] all the hearths in this broad continent of ours will yet [“harmon” deleted] again harmonize in their ancient music when [“touched as they surely” deleted] breathed upon [“again” deleted] by the [“better angel” deleted] guardian angel of the nation.

Here is Lincoln:

I am loth to close. We are not enemies, but friends. We must not be enemies. Though passion may have strained, it must not break our bonds of affection. The mystic chords of memory, stre[t]ching from every battle-field, and patriot grave, to every living heart and hearthstone, all over this broad land, will yet swell the chorus of the Union, when again touched, as surely they will be, by the better angels of our nature.

Besides streamlining Seward’s bumpy language, Lincoln emphatically called for national unity on the basis of common culture. The “mystic chords” connecting the dead with the living evoked spiritualism, the influential movement that deeply affected Mary Todd Lincoln and millions of other Americans. The connecting “chords” would remind many of Lincoln’s hearers of the electromagnetic forces that were then thought to form “spiritual telegraph” between the living and the dead. The joining of every “patriot grave” to “every living heart and hearthstone” drew from other sources of cultural unity: the shared worship of the founding generation, which negated sectional categories, and the imagery found in popular domestic literature. “This broad land” utilized political ecology in its suggestion of the American continent. “The chorus of union” referenced music, which Lincoln considered a key unifying cultural force. “The better angels of our nature” not only humanized Seward’s rather distant “guardian angel of the nation,” but it also drew from what was a common trope in sentimental literature of that era: the angelic nature of good people.

Lincoln’s revised version of Seward’s paragraph was a culturally representative passage offered to a divided nation in what was a massive rhetorical effort to repair the Union. The effort failed. Although Northern journalists generally saw the inaugural as a sensible, compassionate peace offering, Southerners took it as coercive declaration by a Black Republican president. Within eight weeks of giving the speech Lincoln was presiding over a war that would last for four years and would cost some 750,000 American lives. His masterly language could not stave off bloody civil war.

The Second Inaugural Address of Abraham Lincoln

by Richard John Carwardine

On the morning of Saturday March 4, 1865, Abraham Lincoln emerged from the Capitol building to address some 30,000 people gathered for the inauguration of his second term. For the first time on such an occasion his audience included thousands of African Americans. To music and cheers, he took his place on the platform. As he took the oath of office, the sun burst through the clouds: a symbol, it seemed to many, of divine approval and the recent turn in the nation’s fortunes.

Four years earlier, at his first inauguration, Lincoln had appeared vigorous; now he had, as one reporter put it, the look of a man “on whom sorrow and care have done their worst.” Yet he had reason to be buoyant. The war had entered its final phase. The political outlook, too, was encouraging. Vindicated by his re-election, Lincoln had successfully set about driving an emancipation amendment through Congress. Electoral triumph, military progress, and the death spasms of slavery gave Lincoln a greater sense of presidential authority than he had previously enjoyed.

Delivered in a strong, clear voice, Lincoln’s speech bespoke a powerful self-confidence. A fraction over 700 words, it was the shortest inaugural address in the history of the Republic. It began with a flat, matter-of-fact introduction: an extended review of political and military progress was unnecessary, he said, since the events were well-known to all. By contrast each of the three succeeding paragraphs was rich in concentrated meaning and striking rhetoric.

The first summarized the process by which the nation had fallen into war. It is notable for Lincoln’s broad even-handedness. He located the war’s origins in a dispute over the Union. One side wanted to save it, the other to destroy it. Although “destroy” is a not a neutral term, Lincoln does not assign blame for the armed conflict: “all sought to avert it … Both parties deprecated war.”

The next paragraph–the longest–moved on from a summary narrative of the coming of war to a causal explanation of the conflict. Southern slavery “constituted a peculiar and powerful interest. All knew that this interest was somehow the cause of the war. To strengthen, perpetuate, and extend this interest was the object for which the insurgents would rend the Union even by war, while the government claimed no right to do more than to restrict the territorial enlargement of it.” The war, Lincoln reflected, had developed into a struggle whose dimensions and duration “neither party expected. … Each looked for an easier triumph, and a result less fundamental and astounding.”

Then followed a sentence that launched the speech in a direction that few expected: “Both [parties] read the same Bible and pray to the same God, and each invokes His aid against the other.” The religious turn makes the speech unique amongst presidential inaugural addresses. Successive generations have marveled at the depth of Lincoln’s theology, especially about God’s will and His divine judgment on the American nation. In this address he mentions God fourteen times, quotes four times from Scripture, and talks about prayer on three occasions.

As the historian Douglas Wilson has shown, the president grew increasingly ambitious in the themes he sought to convey in his wartime public utterances. With a Union victory now likely, he sought a way of conveying that the war had been about the violation of the inalienable rights set out in the Declaration of Independence, and that complicity in the offense of slaveholding was not confined to the Confederacy.

Delivering this hard message, Lincoln judged, could be best achieved through religious language and ideas familiar to an audience that comprised mostly Protestant Christians, and amongst whom he was viewed as a man of faith–as “a sort of half way clergyman,” as one admirer put it. They would not have been surprised by the tenor of the speech, nor Lincoln’s appeal to the book of Genesis and Jesus’s sermon on the Mount: “It may seem strange that any men should dare to ask a just God’s assistance in wringing their bread from the sweat of other men’s faces, but let us judge not, that we be not judged.”

Lincoln here used a well-known oratorical technique: emphasizing something by purporting not to intend it. Although he implies that the “strange” stance of slaveholders was a form of hypocrisy, this was less a sly dig at the South than a prelude to a statement that formed the theological center of the speech: “The prayers of both [contending sides] could not be answered; that of neither has been answered fully. The Almighty has His own purposes.”

By these means Lincoln prepared his audience for a wrenching passage that implicated both North and South in the sin of slavery. “The bond-man’s two hundred and fifty years of unrequited toil” was an offense against “a living God” who had to be recognized as a force in human affairs. If it were God’s will that “the scourge of war” should continue, “until all the wealth piled by the bondsman’s two hundred and fifty years of unrequited toil shall be sunk, and until every drop of blood drawn with the lash, shall be paid by another drawn with the sword, as was said three thousand years ago, so still it must be said ‘the judgments of the Lord are true and righteous altogether’ ” (Psalm 19).

This national complicity in the sin of slavery opened the way for Lincoln’s memorable concluding paragraph, the core political purpose of his speech. Here he echoed the words of Malachi, invoking God’s judgment against the oppressors of the widow and the fatherless:

With malice toward none, with charity for all, with firmness in the right, as God gives us to see the right, let us strive on to finish the work we are in, to bind up the nation’s wounds, to care for him who shall have borne the battle, and for his widow, and his orphan, to do all which may achieve and cherish a just and a lasting peace among ourselves and with all nations.

Lincoln was a kindly man, who by his own estimate probably had “too little” of the feeling of personal resentment. He saw the irony that, as someone who did not bear a grudge, he had found himself at the center of so profound a conflict.

The address was designed to prepare the way for a post-war reconciliatory reconstruction incumbent on the whole nation. The institution described as “peculiar” to the South owed its introduction and continued existence to the whole nation’s moral deficiencies. At no point does Lincoln call the South “the enemy,” “rebels,” or even “Confederates”; his language is inclusive. He understood that the self-righteousness that had inflected wartime Unionism would not serve the nation well in peacetime.

The president’s shocking assassination deprived the nation of a Lincolnian scheme of reconstruction, so we can only speculate on what would have constituted a course that he wanted to see shaped by “firmness in the right, as God gives us to see the right.” On April 11, four days before his death, he addressed a crowd that had gathered outside the White House to celebrate the Confederate surrender at Appomattox. We may see this speech as Lincoln’s opening position in a debate with Congress. He declared his preference that the vote be conferred on two categories of African Americans: “the very intelligent, and … those who serve our cause as soldiers.” Was this a step towards the radical minority who wanted full suffrage for freedmen and the confiscation of rebels’ land? We cannot know for certain, since in the crowd there was one who was determined the president should not have the opportunity to act. John Wilkes Booth took Lincoln’s words to be heralds of a world turned upside down.

Frederick Douglass, invited by Lincoln to the White House reception after the ceremony, told the President that the address was “a sacred effort.” Lincoln was undoubtedly pleased. But he was aware, too, of the risk he had run in delivering a speech that broke so completely with public expectations. It was in both its religion and its politics a startling, challenging, and potentially transformative document. Lincoln fully understood this. He wrote to a fellow Republican:

I expect the [inaugural address] to wear as well as—perhaps better than—any thing I have produced; but I believe it is not immediately popular. Men are not flattered by being shown that there has been a difference of purpose between the Almighty and them. To deny it, however, in this case, is to deny that there is a God governing the world. It is a truth which I thought needed to be told; and as whatever of humiliation there is in it, falls most directly on myself, I thought others might afford for me to tell it.

Andrew Johnson

Address Upon Assuming the Office of President of the United States

Monday, April 15, 1865

Gentlemen: I must be permitted to say that I have been almost overwhelmed by the announcement of the sad event which has so recently occurred. I feel incompetent to perform duties so important and responsible as those which have been so unexpectedly thrown upon me. As to an indication of any policy which may be pursued by me in the administration of the Government, I have to say that that must be left for development as the Administration progresses. The message or declaration must be made by the acts as they transpire. The only assurance that I can now give of the future is reference to the past. The course which I have taken in the past in connection with this rebellion must be regarded as a guaranty of the future. My past public life, which has been long and laborious, has been founded, as I in good conscience believe, upon a great principle of right, which lies at the basis of all things. The best energies of my life have been spent in endeavoring to establish and perpetuate the principles of free government, and I believe that the Government in passing through its present perils will settle down upon principles consonant with popular rights more permanent and enduring than heretofore. I must be permitted to say, if I understand the feelings of my own heart, that I have long labored to ameliorate and elevate the condition of the great mass of the American people. Toil and an honest advocacy of the great principles of free government have been my lot. Duties have been mine; consequences are God’s. This has been the foundation of my political creed, and I feel that in the end the Government will triumph and that these great principles will be permanently established.

In conclusion, gentlemen, let me say that I want your encouragement and countenance. I shall ask and rely upon you and others in carrying the Government through its present perils. I feel in making this request that it will be heartily responded to by you and all other patriots and lovers of the rights and interests of a free people.

On Opposite Ends
Andrew Johnson's Address Upon Assuming the Office of President of the United States

by Michael Les Benedict

It was one of the worst days in American history. Abraham Lincoln had been shot the night before. Vice President Andrew Johnson had been targeted as well, but the assassin had lost his nerve. Johnson had rushed to Lincoln’s side but he soon left. He did not want to look like he was hovering in anticipation of the worst, which clearly was coming. He returned to the hotel room where he had been lodging since arriving in Washington for his inauguration. That had not gone well. Sick and feverish after his long trip to the capital, he had fortified himself with whiskey, no more than what usually braced him but too much for someone who was ill. He had been unsteady, disorganized. He had slurred his words. Lincoln took it calmly, but others had been shocked. Mortified, Johnson had retreated to the estate of his friend Frank Blair, Sr. He had only recently returned to the hotel. Now, he knew he would become president. He awaited the dreaded notification.

Members of Lincoln’s cabinet, a few senators and representatives, Johnson’s friend Frank Blair, and his son Montgomery silently filed into Johnson’s room. Chief Justice Salmon P. Chase somberly administered the oath of office specified in the Constitution. Johnson repeated it gravely, “very distinctively and impressively,” to the relief of any who worried he might repeat the earlier fiasco. “May God support, guide, and bless you,” Chase said earnestly.

Johnson had no time to prepare a speech. His response was only 360 words—a few more than Washington had said at his second inauguration and a bit longer than Millard Fillmore’s statement following the death of President Zachary Taylor. He was not prepared to say anything about the most pressing matter before him—the mode of restoring the Confederate states to the Union. That “must be left for development as the Administration progresses.” He could only point to what he had done in the past as the best guarantee of the future. He had worked all his life to do what was right, “to establish and perpetuate the principles of free government.” He had always worked to secure the “popular rights” of “the great mass of the American people.” “This has been the foundation of my political creed,” he said.

Johnson had harkened to the basic myths of American political identity—“free government” and “popular rights.” But rarely has a statement of public principle been so vague. The only way to guess how Johnson would apply such general principles was to take his advice and look at what he had said and done.

Johnson had not said much in Congress. He had seemed a typical proslavery southern senator, blasting abolitionists and warning northerners to respect southern rights. But he had never taken up reams of paper like other southerners to define his notion of slaveholders’ rights. He agreed that Congress could not exclude slavery from the territories, but he had not been outspoken against or in favor of Stephen A. Douglas’s idea of leaving the matter to settlers in the territories. Nor had he endorsed Jefferson Davis’s demand that Congress establish a slave code in the territories. He had spent most of his energy trying to pass a law giving homesteads to western settlers—a concrete manifestation of his concern for ordinary Americans.

He never questioned slavery before the war, but he had stood for the interests of yeoman, farmers against those of large planters and cotton merchants. He reflected the views of his strongest constituency—the hill-country farmers of East Tennessee. Like them, he was inclined to fight for southern rights within the Union. After Lincoln’s election in November 1860, most southern opponents of secession claimed to favor delay until all southerners could cooperate to resist clearly intolerable northern demands. Johnson scorned such equivocations. He would defend the Union until northerners took concrete actions against slavery. He was sure his eastern Tennessee constituents felt the same. When other southern senators resigned from the Senate as their states seceded, Johnson was the only one who remained, promising to hang the traitors if he got the chance. At the same time, he co-authored the congressional resolution declaring that the war was to preserve the Union and nothing more.

After federal troops occupied central and western Tennessee, President Lincoln appointed Johnson military governor, with the assignment of organizing loyal Tennesseans to establish a government that adhered to the Union. In that capacity, Johnson had exercised sweeping authority. From the beginning he knew he had to break down the disloyalty that blocked the establishment of a loyal government. “Traitors should be punished and treason crushed,” he declared when he arrived. He repeated that mantra again and again. He vacated municipal offices and appointed loyal replacements, jailed and exiled those who refused to take loyalty oaths, forced disloyal newspapers to close. He demanded a stricter loyalty oath than Lincoln required. Conservative unionists organized to oppose his draconian measures. Radical unionists organized to back him. When Lincoln finally made emancipation a war issue, Johnson and his radical unionists endorsed him. But he was not very sympathetic to the former slaves; abolition of slavery would free the white masses from the despotism of slaveholding aristocrats, he argued. He required that the courts treat former slaves as “free persons of color,” not as citizens.

Johnson had toured the North delivering fiery Union speeches and endorsing emancipation. Lincoln and the Republicans saw him as a symbol of the loyal South, and a Democrat as well. Desperate to create a cluster of southern loyalists upon which to build loyal states, Lincoln and other party leaders seized on Johnson as a representative example, nominating him as their vice-presidential candidate on what they called the Union ticket. By nominating him, Johnson had said, the Union party affirmed “that the rebellious States are still in the Union, that their loyal citizens are still citizens of the United States.” It was a crucial question. No matter what the government of a state did, those who remained loyal to the Union remained American citizens, with the rights of American citizens.

A radical Republican like Ohio’s Senator Benjamin F. Wade should have foreseen the problem. Like many radical Republicans, Wade thought secession had disrupted southern governments and their relations with the federal Union. They would not be entitled to restoration until Congress said they were. That meant that their citizens, even those who had remained loyal to the Union, were not entitled to representation in Congress. Along with Representative Henry Winter Davies, Wade had authored a reconstruction bill that reflected that understanding. He was furious when Lincoln refused to sign it. What Wade saw in Johnson’s record was that he was more determined than Lincoln to keep southern government out of the hands of traitors. “Johnson, we have faith in you,” Wade told him as he took office. “There will be no trouble now in running the government.”

It turned out that Republicans had misjudged him. He had always insisted that loyal citizens had retained all their rights despite the treason of their state governments. Johnson’s denunciations of the disloyal, his arrests, had always been designed to coerce loyalty. He had allowed exiles to return once they took the required oaths; he had let traitors out of jail. During the war, few had taken up his blandishments. They would not betray allies who were still fighting for southern rights. But once the war ended, that consideration evaporated. Johnson did require leading Confederates to seek individual pardons from him personally rather than simply take a loyalty oath. But, to his amazed gratification, nearly all applied. All that remained was to re-establish loyal governments and let the revitalized states resume their places in the Union, with their now loyal citizens once again represented in Congress. Ratify the Thirteenth Amendment abolishing slavery, amend state constitutions to do the same, nullify the secession ordinances, and repudiate the debts incurred to sustain the rebellion, he demanded. Those actions would demonstrate renewed loyalty. That the restored states would decide the status of the freed slaves did not trouble him in the least. This program would restore the republican self-government to which he had dedicated his career. In a society without slaves, the masses whose interests he had always championed would be free of a slaveholding aristocracy. It became clear that he had never included black southerners among “the great mass of the American people.” The “American people” were white, and racial equality threatened their interests.

Through the years of turmoil that followed, Johnson always believed he was staying true to the principles he had articulated in his brief address upon taking office. The Republicans who broke with him, including most of the radical Unionists in Tennessee, violated the principles undergirding popular government. In his view, keeping southern states out of the Union in a fanatic effort to protect the rights of freed slaves was a flagrant violation of constitutional democracy. Sure of his ideals, he would fight the Republicans as vigorously and as vehemently as he had fought the secessionists.

The First Inaugural Address of Ulysses S. Grant

by Joan Waugh

Thursday, March 4, 1868 dawned cold and cloudy. Citizens had already been pouring into Washington, D.C. to witness the inauguration ceremony of the 18th president of the United States, Republican Ulysses S. Grant. The crowds viewed a parade featuring thousands of marching soldiers and despite the weather, were in a festive mood. Roughly 50,000 citizens gathered at noon to watch Chief Justice Salmon Chase administer the oath of office to the 43-year-old Grant on the east portico of the Capitol building. Unaccustomed to public speaking, President Grant read his brief handwritten speech of 1,127 words to the expectant crowd, who strained to hear his softly spoken words. Grant’s famous campaign slogan, “Let Us Have Peace,” which stated his desire for the country’s peaceful reconciliation and promised to help secure it “calmly, without prejudice, hate or sectional pride.” While offering the olive branch to the ex-Confederates, General, now President Grant, also made plain that the United States’ victory in the Civil War was to be secured on Northern terms. That meant restoring the rights and privileges of citizenship of white southerners, but also protecting the rights and establishing the citizenship of the freed people. He affirmed, “This requires security of person, property, and free religious and political opinion in every part of our common country, without regard to local prejudice,” adding, “All laws to secure these ends will receive my best efforts for their enforcement.”

Indeed, 1868 was the first presidential campaign in which the issues of Reconstruction predominated, mirroring an intense debate among Americans over the struggle for the meaning of the Civil War: was it primarily about saving the Union with a focus on restoring white harmony or was it about ensuring the fruits of emancipation and racial justice? Could both be accommodated? After briefly mentioning his other major goals for the country—building a prosperous economy, paying down the war debt, accomplishing Indian reform, earning prestige on the international stage, and passing the Fifteenth Amendment that would grant suffrage for black men—Grant made his case for healing the bitterness of wartime animosities. He began this part of his speech by asserting, “The country having just emerged from a great rebellion, many questions will come before it for settlement in the next four years which preceding Administrations have never had to deal with,” then calling for all citizens to meet those questions, “calmly, without prejudice, hate or sectional pride, remembering that the greatest good to the greatest number is the object to be attained.”

More prosaic than poetic, Grant’s first inaugural address offered a clear and pleasing pledge to reunify the broken nation inspired by the principles of Abraham Lincoln’s Republican Party—Union, free labor for all, economic progress, and American security abroad. Neither the press nor the people expected the “silent” general to suddenly emerge as a great orator, yet praise for the address was nearly universal, the New York Times declaring that Grant “said it strongly and well.” The newly sworn in president might have assumed that he had a mandate from northern voters to rise above politics to heal the country. Yet his inaugural remarks indicate that he expected to meet some resistance. A brief examination of the contest that preceded the inaugural festivities will shed light on the challenges beyond the election.

The search for a Republican candidate took place against the backdrop of President Andrew Johnson’s impeachment trial. In February 1868 The House of Representatives voted to impeach the nominally Republican Johnson, failing by one vote to win the necessary Senate majority needed for removal. Moderate Republicans thus gained traction over the selection process as the Party prepared for the 1868 presidential election. Worried that none of the current crop of politicians held the national stature to secure the nomination, Republican leaders turned to the popular Union hero Grant. As general, he planned and executed military campaigns, presided over occupation of the southern population and territory, and formulated and implemented polices and practices that constituted wartime reconstruction. After the Appomattox surrender, he remained a powerful presence serving as general-in-chief and overseeing the military part of reconstruction policy for President Johnson. He, perhaps as much as anyone in the United States, had an investment in helping to establish a permanent and solid peace between North and South.

The majority of Republicans viewed Grant as a solid moderate. He had backed congressional reconstruction without embracing radical proposals of land redistribution or immediate social equality between the races, although he pledged support for both the Fourteenth (passed 1866, ratified 1868) and Fifteenth amendments. The fact that he was not a career politician did not seem to matter. In fact, it might have been a plus to the voter, part of the generation who lived through a period of extraordinary political turmoil. No ordinary candidate exuded the strength, the authority, and the power of Grant; no other candidate held the reputation or the successes. No other candidate’s legacy was more at stake. He was the obvious, inevitable choice for the Republican Party.

The ensuing Republican campaign and its candidate sought to unify a divided, diverse country around the symbols of nationhood—the Founding Fathers, the flag, religion, economic opportunity, and above all, the shared sacrifice of the Civil War. Following tradition, Grant stayed at his home in Galena, Illinois, where he received groups of supporters. A few years later, he described the stakes for the 1868 campaign: “I believed that if a democratic president was elected there would be little chance for those who fought for the Union.” The Democratic Party accused the Republicans—“the Radical party”—of violating the constitutional rights of the Southern states and of subjecting them to “military despotism.” Their Democratic platform, while accepting emancipation, blamed Republicans of planning to elevate the interests of the freed people above those of the white population. Party leaders, such as their presidential candidate, Horatio Seymour of New York, attacked Grant as an uncouth, simple-minded, unprincipled, “Negro-loving” tyrant. As Republicans marched in parades, Democrats taunted them with signs proclaiming: “Grant the Butcher,” and “Grant the Drunkard,” the latter referring to his alleged weakness for alcohol.

The Republicans returned fire, but highlighted a positive message, emphasizing their role as the Party that saved the Union, freed the slaves, and was peacefully reforming the South. Republican operatives in the former Confederate states targeted enfranchised freedmen with educative political pamphlets, provided black and white speakers with “Grant badges” to distribute, started political clubs, and organized barbecues, and other political entertainments. Violence entered directly into electoral politics with white supremacists launching terrorist attacks in every Southern state. Houses, churches, schools, printing offices, political clubrooms were attacked and sometimes destroyed. The lame-duck Johnson administration did nothing to stop this terror in which hundreds of black and white Republicans were killed.

When election day, November 3, arrived and the votes were tabulated, Grant scored a comfortable, but not a smashing, victory in the popular vote, 53% to Seymour’s 47%, while winning by a landslide in the electoral college, 214 to 80.The majority of electoral votes (157) came from states free of slavery before the Civil War; (Seymour carried just 3 of them), and 78% of the electorate participated, including for the first time in American history, an estimated 400,000––500,000 Black men.

No man other than George Washington came to the office with such high expectations as those that accompanied Ulysses S. Grant to his swearing-in ceremonies. Some Democrats worried aloud that Grant’s election meant that “militarism” would dominate government policy, but most Republicans thought his victory meant redemption for the Union Cause for which so many had fought and died and sacrificed for since 1861. They would agree with the judgment offered up by the influential journal Harper’s Weekly describing the election as the “final interpretation of the war.”

Ulysses S. Grant’s first inaugural speech prepared the country for his coming administration. He, and it, would be charged with, and judged by, implementing the Republican-dominated, interracial governments already present in most of the ex-Confederate States. Concluding, President Grant asked for a “patient forbearance one towards another throughout the land, and a determined effort on the part of every citizen to do his share towards cementing a happy union,” adding, “and I ask the prayers of the nation to Almighty God in behalf of this consummation.”

“Errors of judgement, not of intent”: The Second Inaugural Address of Ulysses S. Grant

by John Marszalek

Ulysses S. Grant was both the commanding general of the Union Army (1861-1865) and president of the United States (1869-1877). Since President Abraham Lincoln was assassinated in 1865, and his successor, Andrew Johnson, the vice president, was impeached in 1868, U.S. Grant became the nation’s most famous politician. From the time of Andrew Jackson (1829-1837) to the presidency of Woodrow Wilson (1913-1921), U.S. Grant was the only president for nearly a century to serve two full terms.

Grant was easily elected in 1868 and then re-elected in 1872. In the 1868 election, the Republicans met in Chicago and easily nominated Grant as their standard-bearer, with South Bend, Indiana’s Schuyler Colfax, his running mate. Grant won 26 of 34 states with an electoral victory of 214-80. His popular vote victory was only slightly more than 306,000 out of 5,715,000. It was the newly enfranchised blacks who elected him with a vote of over 500,000 in his favor.

In the election of 1872, the Republicans met in Philadelphia and chose their ticket of Grant for president and Henry Wilson of Massachusetts for vice president. This time Grant won 286-66 electoral votes over Democrat Horace Greeley. A number of third parties siphoned off just a few votes. In this election, too, Grant won by 763,000 popular votes. Ironically Greeley died on November 29, 1868, and vice-presidential candidate Wilson died in 1875. Therefore, Grant served most of his second term without a vice president.

When Grant ran and took office in 1869, he inherited many problems: Reconstruction, Greenbacks, Black Friday (or the attempt to corner the gold market), the Ku Klux Klan, Civil Service Reform, the New York City Tweed Ring, the Liberal Republican Movement, the issue of Santa Domingo, and the Credit Mobilier (with vice president Schuyler Colfax involved). Despite these first term difficulties, Grant ran again and won once more in 1873. This time he faced the “Crime of 1873” or the Coinage Act, making gold, not silver, the monetary standard; the “Salary Grab” or doubling the president’s salary (which was repealed in January 1874); the Panic of 1873; the Whiskey Ring; the impeachment of Secretary of War William Belknap; the disputed Hayes-Tilden presidential election of 1877; Custer’s Last Stand; and a variety of Indian problems.

Grant thus had to deal with numerous post-Civil War problems, and was often cited as being corrupt and running a corrupt administration. Though he never was implicated in any wrongdoing, his second inauguration proved to be more difficult than the first.

Grant’s second inauguration was one of the coldest in American history, with driving winds and a temperature near zero degrees. The weather was as horrible as it might be. Spectators lined up in the middle of Pennsylvania Avenue, standing on streetcar tracks with people and carriages traveling along the northern side of the avenue. Marchers tried to take advantage of the recent street improvements but still suffered wind-blown dirt in their faces. People took advantage of every piece of warm clothes they could wear, hoping to gain some warmth against the temperature and the wind. Still, the event was festive; every building was draped with majestic cloth and bunting.

The most impressive part of the entire day was the parade, which consisted of marching bands and military units, some 12,000 people in all. Even African Americans were included. Some of the marchers, for example, West Point cadets and Annapolis midshipmen, suffered severe frostbite. U.S. Grant joined the parade march from the White House, along Pennsylvania Avenue, wearing a thick overcoat, and riding in an open carriage pulled by four magnificent horses. Men and women cheered when they saw Grant, and a young boy all wrapped in warm clothes, briefly ran alongside the carriage, yelling “Hurrah for Grant.” When the president reached the Capital, he mounted the inaugural stand on the east side. At precisely 12:30 PM. Salmon P. Chase, the Chief Justice of the Supreme Court, swore Grant in, and the president gave his inaugural address. Few could hear him because of the howling wind. A photographer set up a tower and took as many pictures as he could. The crowd seemed pleased with his effort.

His address was not long, and the frozen audience must have been happy that Grant kept his rhetoric relatively brief. He wrote his own address, and his thoughts at that time were obvious. He was pleased to have won re-election. He was also happy that he could say something positive about the aftermath of the Civil War even though he recognized that three former states had not yet returned to the Union. He was overconfident when he indicated that all was going well within the United States during his first term, but he went too far when he insisted that the world was moving inexorably toward “republicanism” and that the United States was “destined to be the guiding star to all others.” He was obviously happy that the telegraph and steam power were pushing the nation into a union never before enjoyed.

Then, however, he quickly switched to the major problem that the nation was still suffering. Black people did not yet enjoy their rightful social equality. He did not want to overemphasize this phenomenon, although he did want to give the black man a “fair chance to develop what there is good in him, give him access to the schools, and when he travels let him feel assured that his conduct will regulate the treatment and fare he will receive.” The amazing fact was that Grant was saying these words in 1873, long before the nation was ready to guarantee such rights to black people. (And, he was proud that no federal force was being used on any of the former rebellious states).

President Grant also indicated that he would continue to support gold as the monetary standard and support international trade linking the world together. He clearly believed that the American Indian “be made a useful and productive member of society by proper teaching and treatment.” He hoped too that civil service reform would be made an essential part of the nation’s future.

The second term president wanted everyone within the sound of his voice (and because of the wind, few fit into this category) to know that he appreciated that the nation had given him the honor of its leadership. He promised that he would always do his best, and wanted everyone to realize that he never asked for any “place or position” and that he would never be “vengeful” toward the South or any individual within it. He promised, too, never to ask for “promotion or command.”

Finally, Grant reminded his listeners: “I have been the subject of abuse and slander scarcely ever equaled in political history.” But being the beneficiary of the nation’s good feelings as expressed in this presidency, he believed firmly that, “in view of your verdict. . .I gratefully accept this honor as my vindication.”

In short, therefore, U.S. Grant, in giving his second inaugural address, indicated his willingness to serve another term in office and to continue his good work for the benefit of the nation. The cold did not deter his great plans for the future, but it was certainly a bad omen for his second term.

The Inaugural Address of Rutherford B. Hayes

by Dustin McLochlin

When Rutherford B. Hayes gave his inaugural address on March 5, 1877, it was only three days removed from Congress confirming his victory over his opponent Samuel Tilden of New York. For four months the two parties fought over the returns, which initially appeared to show a clear victory for Tilden. But Republicans noticed that if Hayes carried the three close Southern states of Louisiana, Florida, and South Carolina, he would win the election by one electoral vote.

Once the Republican party halted the results, both parties sent delegates to the three states in question to find evidence for their side’s victory. Predictably, both determined their candidate had won. To break this stalemate, Congress created an Electoral Commission of 15 members. The Democratic party supported this in heavier numbers because they hoped the deciding member of the commission would be David Davis whom they believed would side with their party. But, he resigned the court and the deciding spot went to Joseph Bradley who sided with the Republicans. Upon looking at all of the state returns, the Commission voted strictly down party lines and determined Hayes was the victor.

Partly because of the drama that surrounded Hayes’s confirmation, Chief Justice Morrison Waite, through the direction of Ulysses S. Grant, swore Hayes into the presidency two days early in the White House on March 3. Hayes’s public inauguration on March 5, therefore, was truly ceremonial.

Since the Civil War ended, the major political topic was Reconstruction, and this election year had been no different. But, by the time of Hayes’s inauguration, the Reconstruction project had been ongoing for nearly 12 years, and the continued presence of federal troops in the South became increasingly tenuous as Southern states were readmitted into the Union, culminating in the seating of Georgia Senator Jonah Hill in February 1871. Despite the formal reintroduction of all of the rebellious Southern states, the use of Union troops remained in a limbo of questionable constitutional legality. The true tenuousness of this continued presence led to many climactic moments including in Louisiana when the Army moved to defend the Republican governor from a Democratic coup in 1874. Public opinion seemed to teeter between the federal government upholding state democratic institutions or allowing states to run their own affairs (which was a tacit acceptance of white dominance and disenfranchisement of black men). If the federal government no longer had the will of the people to oversee the actions of Southern states, then a new course needed to be charted. It was in this milieu that Hayes took the office, and his speech reflects this understanding.

A strong adherent to his interpretation of the Constitution, Hayes felt it was time the South was allowed “local self-government,” especially now that the nation had passed the Thirteenth, Fourteenth, and Fifteenth Amendments. We can see his insistence on the South abiding by those amendment as well as the rest of the Constitution when he argues for “accepting and obeying faithfully the whole Constitution as it is” (emphasis mine). His focus on the Constitution is especially purposeful here since he says “constitution” or “constitutional” seven times in his section on the South, only using the word to other times throughout the rest of his speech. But his hope for Southern adherence to these amendments was of little use without some plan for long-term sustainability. And, for Hayes, it was in the belief that the division along party lines in the South was based upon the racial question. He felt that once “bayonet rule” came to an end, then people would vote on other concerns. Southern former-Whigs who had more in common with the Republicans would, thus, abandon their Democratic allegiance and provide a larger umbrella of voters for the Republican party in the South. Implicit in this plan, was a further assumption that a Southern black man would also be free to vote Democratic if he felt it aligned with his beliefs, thus Southern white men would not feel compelled to terrorize these potential voters.

Hayes was attempting to chart a new course that was doomed for failure. Perhaps Hayes was naïve, or he was accepting a course and hoped for the best, despite his limited options. Regardless, to historians this election and the outcome in South Carolina and Louisiana would be an ending point to Reconstruction.

While the gravity of the racial question in the post-Civil War was the most pressing, and needed to be addressed directly, all of Hayes subsequent policy statements fed into his path forward beyond Reconstruction policies. First, through Civil Service reform, Hayes hoped to find an avenue into bridging the gap between the North and South (and, therefore, Republican and Democrat). He called for a “thorough, radical, and complete” reform, and felt on solid ground with this because “both the great political parties … gave a prominent place to the subject of reform of our civil service.” In is in this context that he made the statement that resonated the most with the nation, proclaiming “he serves the party best who serves the country best.” This line, mostly borrowed from his eventual Secretary of the Interior Carl Schurz, highlighted that reform was not a partisan issue that serving your country was a better means of upholding the honorability of your party, not attempting to maintain its dominance through political appointment. And, a means to combat this political machinery was perhaps through an amendment to change presidential appointments to a single, six-year term. Hayes had pledged a single term in his nomination letter, and this one-term pronouncement was an argument that, in his opinion, presidential first terms were merely used as a vehicle to establish enough of a machine for reelection.

Charting a course of Civil Service reform was not without its perils within his own party. Politicians like Roscoe Conkling of New York made a career working with the machine politics system. In fact, Conkling was a prominent name to potentially unseat James Blaine of Maine who was the front runner for the Republican nomination in 1876. Only through the split between Conkling and Blaine supporters did Hayes even ascend to the nomination since many Conkling supporters would rather take their chances with the unknown Hayes rather than accepting Blaine. When Hayes made his intentions clear on civil service, Conkling only half-heartedly supported Hayes over Tilden.

While Civil Service reform undoubtedly created rifts within the Republican party, which Hayes might want to avoid, his stance on the economy had the potential of creating rifts within the Democratic party, in which Hayes hoped. The economic panic, which started in 1873, showed signs of recovery by 1877, but discussing his belief in elimination “irredeemable paper currency” showed that he was attempting to win over the “hard money” element of the Democratic party who were most likely to be former Whigs. In fact, the Democratic ticket included the hard money Tilden, and the “soft money” Vice Presidential nominee Thomas Hendricks.

Hayes makes room for one more policy announcement before his closing remarks. But this pronouncement is much more a conciliatory note to Grant and his wing of the party than Hayes laying out his foreign policy objectives. While the statement itself says little other than Hayes’s intention to continue Grant’s policy of “submitting to arbitration grave questions in dispute,” Hayes had made a number of choices in his nomination letter that were seen as direct rebukes to Grant and his administration. His civil service pledge could be seen as an attack on Grant and his connection to Roscoe Conkling’s wing of the Republican party, and his call for a single term came after a time when many thought Grant would attempt a third term (which he did the following election). Hayes knew he needed to embrace Grant, and hopefully his wing, in some level during his inaugural address.

All of this was unquestionably in the backdrop of the dubious way upon which Hayes was confirmed as the president, and Hayes had to make some mention. Playing the role of the conciliator Hayes calls for everyone to move forward from the decision made by the electoral commission (he calls it the “tribunal”). In this discussion we see many conciliatory statements given to Democrats, and Southerners, that perhaps the Electoral Commission did err in its judgment. And, while can commend Hayes for sympathizing with the opposing party for its differing view on the outcome, we should also commend him for understanding the peaceful transfer of power and pointing out that regardless of the outcome there needs to be a general “acquiescence” to the outcome even if individuals may not like Hayes. This acceptance of democracy above personal ambition was an important element of this contentious outcome.

The Preacher President: The Inaugural Address of James A. Garfield

by Charles W. Calhoun

When the Republican Party tapped James A. Garfield for president in 1880, observers labeled him a dark horse nominee, but he had long occupied a place in the front rank of American politicians. Through seventeen years in Congress, he had positioned himself as an eloquent advocate of Republican doctrine, and, not unreasonably, he anticipated that a deadlocked national convention might turn to him. He was right. A prolonged struggle between supporters of former president Ulysses S. Grant and those of Maine Senator James G. Blaine ended when Blaine delegates swung to Garfield. Eventually, the party closed ranks, and he went on to victory in November. He was the only Republican from 1876 to 1892 to win a popular-vote plurality over his Democratic opponent.

Few presidents have approached preparing an inaugural with greater intellectual strengths than Garfield’s. Educated at Williams College, he had been a professor of ancient languages, ordained minister, college president, lawyer, and Ohio state senator–all before he turned thirty, at which age he became a general in the United States army. A scholar in politics, he carried on a lively correspondence with professors, literary figures, and leading political economists. He labored long hours researching and writing his speeches and essays, taking breaks to read his favorite Roman poets in Latin.

It is remarkable, then, that when Garfield set about writing his address, he fell into an almost crippling hesitation. After his fashion, he launched the task by studying all his predecessors’ speeches, but as weeks went by, his usual scholarly self-discipline abandoned him. He put no words to paper and allowed himself to be distracted by tedious consultations regarding patronage and other political matters. His procrastination was not entirely out of character, for at key points in his career Garfield had suffered spasms of indecision. Rather than being inspired by previous inaugural addresses, he considered them, except for Lincoln’s, “dreary reading,” and feared that “mine will be also.” Daunted by the responsibility of framing the most important utterance of his life, he grumbled that the inaugural genre had “so many limitations” that it left “little freedom in its composition.” More than once, he considered giving no address at all. Three days before the inauguration, he finally had a draft but was “so much dissatisfied with it” that he started all over again. He did not complete the speech until 2:30 in the morning of March 4, 1881, the day of its delivery.

In the end, Garfield fell back on a personal model for his address–the public letter he had issued accepting the Republican presidential nomination. In that campaign letter he had discussed the central issues confronting the American people, and he now reprised those questions in roughly the same order. He aimed to cultivate favor with both the Grant wing of his party, which emphasized continued support for civil rights, and the Blaine wing, which stressed economic issues. Eschewing high-flown rhetoric, he presented a clear exposition of the state of the Republic and where he wanted to take it.

Garfield began his address with a reverent yet monitory review of the Republic’s progress through the previous century. At the outset, he observed, the American Revolution represented not merely a violent withdrawal from the British Empire but the initiation of a “great experiment of self-government,” which formed the new nation’s quintessence. The American revolutionaries defied not only “the armies of a great nation,” but also “the settled opinions of mankind” in battling for the radical principle that “the supreme authority of government could be safely intrusted to the guardianship of the people themselves.” After a halting start, the Articles of Confederation gave way to the Constitution, establishing “a National Union, founded directly upon the will of the people.” Yet, despite the nation’s growth and success, doubts about the durability of its democratic project persisted, until the Civil War brought “the supreme trial of the Constitution.”

Although the war’s outcome secured the Union’s permanency, sixteen years after Appomattox, American democracy still remained contested. Garfield expressed the anxiety felt by many citizens, especially Republicans, that the nation could not finally secure the promise of the Founders’ design as long as it was held hostage by men who placed white supremacy above admitting Blacks to participate in self-government. “There can be no permanent disfranchised peasantry in the United States,” he declared. “To violate the freedom and sanctities of the suffrage is more than an evil. It is a crime which, if persisted in, will destroy the Government itself. Suicide is not a remedy.”

Still, Garfield suggested no revival of military Reconstruction, which neither Congress nor the nation would sanction. Conceding the validity of complaints about the ignorance of Black voters, he favored not denying them suffrage but instead improving their capacity for citizenship by a thorough program of education. But, he said, the problem of voter ignorance extended beyond the South. Decrying a rising “tide of illiteracy” in the country, he called for “all the constitutional power of the nation and of the States” to “meet this danger by the savory influence of universal education.” Again, he stressed the precariousness of the democratic experiment, warning that if the next “generation comes to its inheritance blinded by ignorance and corrupted by vice, the fall of the Republic will be certain and remediless.”

Turning to economic questions, Garfield hailed the nation’s prosperity after a half-decade of depression in the 1870s. He attributed the good fortune not only to bountiful harvests but also to government policies for the preservation of the public credit and the resumption of the payment of specie for greenback paper dollars issued during the Civil War. Subscribing to prevailing financial orthodoxy, he saw gold and silver as the “only safe foundation for a monetary system.” Paper notes such as the greenbacks were only “promises to pay money” and must be held at par with specie. Like gold, silver possessed intrinsic value, but its safe use as money depended on its coinage in equivalence with gold, preferably at a ratio set by international agreement. Garfield also called for refinancing the national debt at a lower interest rate.

As an economic nationalist, Garfield favored an expanded role for government in fostering prosperity. For farmers, he advocated programs to provide “the best lights of practical science and experience.” Over the years Garfield had shown less enthusiasm than many Republicans had displayed on behalf of a high tariff to protect American industry from foreign competition. The Republican campaign in 1880 had placed great emphasis on that policy, but Garfield omitted any specific mention of it in his address. Instead, he saluted the nation’s burgeoning manufacturers and said simply that their “steady and healthy growth should still be matured.” The vagueness of this locution in the passive voice suggested Garfield’s lingering affinity for freer trade and offered scant encouragement to his party’s protectionist wing.

In the interest of expanding trade, Garfield advocated the improvement of harbors and interior waterways and support to revitalize the American merchant fleet. He also favored further consideration of plans for a Central American ship canal and asserted that any such waterway should remain under American “supervision and authority.”

Since its first national platform in 1856, the Republican Party had decried polygamy, condemning it, like slavery, as a “relic of barbarism.” This issue centered in the Utah Territory, where adherents to the Mormon Church predominated. Garfield acknowledged the Constitution’s guarantee of “absolute religious freedom,” but he asserted that Congress had the duty to prohibit in areas under its jurisdiction “all criminal practices,” especially those that “destroy the family relations and endanger social order.” Again he warned of danger to America’s democratic experiment, denouncing the Mormon Church’s exclusionary political practices in the territory. No “ecclesiastical organization,” he insisted, could “be safely permitted to usurp in the smallest degree the functions and powers of the National Government.”

Finally, Garfield turned to civil service reform, an issue that had roiled politics for more than a decade. President Grant had first instituted a reform program in the early 1870s, but Congress had never confirmed it through legislation. Without statute law, Garfield argued, the civil service could “never be placed on a satisfactory basis.” But he did not call for a legislated mandate for competitive exams for appointments. Instead, he promised to ask Congress to prescribe the term-lengths for minor offices as well as the grounds for legitimate dismissal, thus hoping to protect upright civil servants from arbitrary removal for political reasons. As matters turned out, the most significant achievement of Garfield’s brief term came with his successful assertion of the power of the president to appoint officials despite the objection of state party bosses.

Though hardly a masterpiece, Garfield’s address won general praise. One Republican newspaper said his “admirable” speech justified the people’s “high confidence” in him. Yet, the paper added, “it still remains for him to show whether he possesses the rare tact, the patience, and the practical statesmanship to get things done.”

Four months later an assassin’s bullet denied him the chance.

Address Upon Assuming the Office of President of the United States

by Walter T. K. Nugent

As the election of 1880 drew near, the Republicans–dominant in presidential elections since 1860 but not lately in congressional contests–were divided into two large factions: the Stalwarts and the Half-Breeds. The Stalwarts hoped to nominate former president Ulysses S. Grant, whom they believed was a sure winner. But Grant had already served two full terms (1869–1877), and he was diffident about running again. The Half-Breeds were eager, both to capture the nomination and the election. Grant’s delegate votes stalled on the thirty-fourth ballot. The leader of the Half-Breeds, Senator James G. Blaine of Maine, was in second place but could not pull into the lead. The nomination soon went to a dark horse, long-term congressman James A. Garfield of Ohio.

The convention, for party unity’s sake, then turned to a Stalwart for the Vice-presidential nomination: Chester Alan Arthur of New York, an ally of the Stalwart leader, Senator Roscoe Conkling. Arthur was a Vermont-born New York City lawyer, known for his high-fashion dandified attire. He had also been a solid Republican since the late 1850s and was noted for two cases in which he successfully defended African-Americans, one a woman prevented from riding on the city’s public transit and the other a slave who claimed freedom after his owner brought him to New York. In 1871, President Grant appointed Arthur the Collector of the Port of New York, the most lucrative patronage job in the federal system overseeing a staff of a thousand at the Customs House. Arthur held this position until President Hayes, in a burst of reform zeal (which Arthur was then scarcely noted for), fired him in 1878. But by 1880, Hayes was without much influence, and Arthur was a Conkling ally. In the presidential election, Garfield and Arthur squeaked by the Democratic candidates, General Winfield Scott Hancock and Indiana congressman William English, by only 33,000 votes out of 8.86 million cast.

Garfield and Arthur swore their oaths of office on March 4, 1881. Garfield filled his cabinet with party leaders and faithful, with the eminent Blaine as Secretary of State. But not quite four months later, on July 2, Charles Guiteau, who has gone down in history as “a disappointed office seeker,” shot Garfield in the back and arm. The president lingered two and a half months. Physicians, as yet unaware of antisepsis, tried to dig out the bullet, but gave Garfield blood poisoning which, together with a weakened heart and other problems, killed him on September 19. Garfield had had little time to accomplish much. He had advocated civil service reform, but that and other ideas had to await his successor. Arthur took the presidential oath at his New York residence in the wee hours of the next day. He would serve out nearly a full term until March 1885.

Arthur did not have a formal inauguration nor a true inaugural address. But he did transmit his “Address upon assuming the Office of President” almost immediately, on September 22, 1881. Hardly any of it touched on policy or gave an indication of any legislation hr might propose. As the document shows, Arthur promised to “profit by his [Garfield’s] example and experience” and strive “to correct abuses, to enforce economy, to advance prosperity, and to promote the general welfare … ensure domestic security and maintain friendly and honorable relations with the nations of the earth.” Hardly radical, even anodyne. His aim, evidently, was to reassure the people that the road ahead would be smooth. “No demand for speedy legislation has been heard, “ no “unusual session of Congress” is occasioned.

Nonetheless, Arthur and his administration did achieve a number of things, which together form a more activist federal government–not a lot more, but visibly more–than the Hayes administration that preceded him. In less than three months after taking over, the entrepreneurial Blaine resigned, leaving foreign policy more clearly in Arthur’s hands. Nearly all of Garfield’s cabinet members would be replaced within a year. In early 1882, Congress passed two acts that restricted rights rather than extending them: In March 1882, the Edmunds Act, outlawing polygamy, an anti-Mormon measure; and in May 1882, the Chinese Exclusion Act, cutting off migration from China for ten years. (Arthur had vetoed a bill a few days earlier because its exclusion period was twenty years, but he signed the revised one. In 1892 and later, exclusion would be extended permanently.)

In the fall of 1882, Congress argued about civil service reform. The issue had come up in Hayes’ time, and pressure mounted for some form of action. First the Senate, and then the House, passed the Pendleton Civil Service Act in late 1882, and Arthur signed it into law on January 16, 1883. It is the one achievement for which the Arthur Administration is best–or at all–known for, mentioned in virtually every subsequent textbook of post-Civil War American history. Many have remarked on the apparent incongruity of Arthur, a preeminent spoilsman of the 1870s, signing the first broad act to limit or replace the spoils system with competitive merit examinations for holding office.

The spring of 1883 also brought a revision of the tariff, though levels changed very little as interests competed for protection. The act became known as the “mongrel tariff,” and it finally passed in December. Arthur also signed a generous bill to expand appropriations for the U.S. Navy, which he regarded as under strength. In so doing, he built a reputation as an expansionist, if not an imperialist. Another naval bill the next year cemented that reputation. So did the United States’ acquisition in 1884 of Pearl Harbor, in Hawaii, as a coaling station for American vessels.

Under Arthur’s watch, the United States in 1884 became a signatory to the International treaty establishing standard time, with a line running through the Greenwich Observatory in London as the “prime meridian.” In pre-railroad days, time zones were unknown and unnecessary. But by the 1880s, different railroad lines had run on different schedules, with sometimes lethal results. The standardization of time, into four zones across the United States, was an essential safety measure and an achievement of the Arthur years. The final significant legislation signed by Arthur was the Foran Act, outlawing contract labor, in February 1885.

Did his actions conform to, or reflect, his initial address (see above)? Vague as those were, he could hardly have missed. The civil service act did correct abuses, the tariff could be claimed to have advanced prosperity, and the naval appropriations ensured security, in its way.

By early 1885, Arthur had unsuccessfully sought renomination. Blaine became the Republican candidate for president in the 1884 election, only to be defeated by the Democrat, New York governor Grover Cleveland, by about as narrow a margin ad Garfield and Arthur had managed in 1880.

Arthur’s nearly four years in office were certainly not devoid of achievements, and the Pendleton Act was by no means the only one. Arthur became president only sixteen years after the end of the Civil War, and he left the office only sixteen years before the accession of Theodore Roosevelt and the onset of full-blown Progressive reform. In Arthur’s day, Jim Crow had not yet grown into its full malign maturity, but already many KKK atrocities and other terrorism were wreaked upon the former slaves. The Army and settlers continued to push back Indians from their tribal lands. Civil War issues and loyalties persisted strongly, in the South, in Supreme Court decisions, in the election of former Confederates to Congress and other offices. On the other hand, and looking forward, the Arthur presidency produced glimmerings of the kind of reforms that would soon mark the full-blown Progressive Era. Historians have traditionally called the years from the Civil War to World War I as “the Gilded Age and Progressive Era,” but were they so different, stodgy and corrupt on the early side, enlightened and filled with reform on the later? It’s not quite that simple. Many changes that we might think of as “progressive” really began in the so-called Gilded Age, the 1870s through the 1890s. But some of the actions that Arthur and the Congresses of his day give off more than a whiff of “Progressivism.” The more restrictive and, by today’s standards, illiberal side of Progressivism was manifest in the Chinese Exclusion Act and the Edmunds Anti-Polygamy law. Yet the more liberal kind of Progressivism was at the core of the Pendleton Civil Service Act, and the imperialism of Theodore Roosevelt was of a kind with Arthur’s naval up-grading and the franchise on Pearl Harbor.

All in all, Arthur and his Administration compiled not a bad record of achievements in those three and a half years, starting with the shock of Garfield’s assassination. It was an honorable and incorrupt record. Throughout those years, Arthur suffered from Bright’s disease–the modern name is glomerulonephritis–and he died of it about a year after he left the White House.

"A fine man, a grand man": The First Inaugural Address of Grover Cleveland

by Mark W. Summers

Prosy and free from a single memorable phrase, Cleveland’s first inaugural address was strikingly short: a thousand words less than Garfield’s, and 1,500 fewer than Benjamin Harrison’s. Perhaps that was because, rather than reading it, he memorized the whole thing and spoke it, hands clasped behind his back like an elocution student delivering a discourse. “God, what a magnificent gambler,” one Republican senator burst out.[21]

There was nothing of the gambler in “the faithful plodder”[22] who succeeded Chester Alan Arthur that March, nor in his style. His labored public documents expressed a duty-driven, sober workaholic, who had learned composition from his clergyman father and as a Buffalo lawyer had always been picked to write up obituary resolutions.[23] The first Democrat elected president since before the Civil War, Cleveland was well aware of how uneasily the Republican half of America greeted the change in the White House. Its congressional delegation bulging with “Rebel brigadiers,” the Democratic party was notoriously the home for Confederate diehards and violent white supremacists. They had made a “Solid South” by intimidation and fraud, and as far as their enemies were concerned, had won only by preventing a free, fair count in the onetime slave states. Associated as the Democratic party was with Tammany Hall’s scrofulous political machine, with Irish Catholicism, and with wide-open saloons, the Rev. Samuel D. Burchard blurted out what many believed, and many others feared, that Democratic ascendancy meant a win for “rum, Romanism, and rebellion.” As New York’s reform governor and a man whose political career really began a generation after the Civil War, Cleveland had won the presidential nomination because of how little he seemed to fit that stereotype. But could the leader of a party feared as sectional and agrarian be trusted with the nation’s industrial interests? Or would he follow so many of his fellow members in the South and West in supporting a currency supply inflated with the issue of additional silver coinage and a cut in the high protective tariff that would put factory workers at the mercy of low-earners’ goods from overseas? Might his party even reopen the postwar settlement to restore what they had once boasted was “a white man’s government”?

For that reassurance, Grover Cleveland did not need a long address—quite the reverse. Unlike his predecessor and successor, he would propose no laundry list of desirable legislation. Specifics were sure to stir controversy. In any case, Democrats leaned towards a cheap government that did as little as possible. Instead, the incoming president concentrated on setting a tone of safe, guarded reform under an executive determined neither to dictate to Congress nor to revolutionize the way things worked already. There would be no power-grabs like those that brought the last Democrat in the White House, Andrew Johnson, before the Senate on impeachment charges—no ambitions like those that Democrats had imputed to Ulysses S. Grant as a “Caesar” in the making. The President would maintain the 1883 Pendleton civil service law, with its hedges against any partisan scouring of the federal officeholders and its emphasis on the rewarding of merit, but not propose to widen its coverage. Unlike James Garfield, he would give no hint of tinkering with the monetary system, certainly not towards giving silver the same status as gold.[24] As for the protective tariff, Cleveland went no further than to urge that the revenue system be changed to prevent so much of the nation’s money supply being locked up in Treasury vaults beyond what the government could spend, and to hint that any alterations should guard the interests of industry and wage-earners.

Indeed, from the inaugural, one might easily conclude that Cleveland saw his office as purely administrative. Policy, apparently, was all Congress’s doing, and the chief executive would show “a cautious appreciation of [his] functions.” The promise to limit public spending might have meant nothing at all. Presidents always promised to see that the people’s taxes got spent responsibly and were held to the bare minimum needed. Cleveland meant it, though. Unlike Garfield, he looked askance at any national aid to public education; unlike Benjamin Harrison, he did not couple his thrifty sentiments with an endorsement of money to dredge rivers and harbors and subsidize the country’s merchant marine. Listeners could not know that the new President would go out of his way to veto bills providing relief to drought-stricken ranchers, private claims, and, most controversially, 228 individual pension bills for Union veterans whose claims he found undeserving.[25] Nor could they know that within three years, Cleveland had realized that when it came to the tariff, Congress had a gift for doing nothing (quite aggressively and at endless length) and that a presidential initiative must push them towards serious downward reform. Then he showed his other side, in one newspaper’s words, rushing at “big things as unhesitatingly as a rock out of a catapult at a plate glass window, smashing them all to pieces.”[26] (But then, if they had known that before the 1884 election, Cleveland certainly would have lost. That was why he had dodged the issue, while the Democratic platform faced both ways at once.)

At the same time, Cleveland needed to reassure Republicans that the change in the White House did not mean a Democratic ascendancy. There would be, as the Boston Advertiser remarked, “no backward look,” no “undoing.”[27] The election proved that whoever took power, the republic was in no danger. Elected by one party, the President saw himself as custodian for all the people, regardless of section or race. That his opponents allowed a smooth transition, he hinted, showed the excellence of free government—and to Democrats with bitter memories of the so-called “stolen election” of 1876, may have been the gentlest of swipes at another year when the apparent losers played nowhere so fair a game. His appeal for an end to rancor between North and South brought the loudest cheer of any in the audience. Some saw it as a rebuke to the Republican “bloody shirt” rhetoric, branding its opponents as once and future traitors; others saw it as a commitment to let the Reconstruction settlement stand, and Cleveland nailed down that impression by affirming that, however bitter past disputes had been, the emancipation and extension of rights to the freedpeople was no longer in dispute. Famous for a statement put into his mouth by another, Cleveland’s main point in his inaugural was to assert that public office was, indeed, a public trust, and not only for officers elected nationally, but at every level of government.

Government “is a matter of practical acts and not of glittering generalities,” the Philadelphia Press complained, “and when we look through what President Cleveland says to see what he will do, we do not find it.”[28] A fair complaint! Though, in retrospect, vague phrases would take on weight as ponderous as the incumbent’s own. He had been conspicuously silent about appointing officers on merit alone, as civil service reformers wanted. Sure enough, most Republicans whose fixed-term ended, would have Democrats replacing them.[29] In the South, that meant that the many black postmasters had white successors, even if Cleveland showed himself reasonably liberal for a member of his party in occasionally nominating an African American for a prominent patronage position (which made smart politics with a Republican senate uncomfortable about drawing the white line tighter than a Democratic president did). The mainstream press did not notice how, unlike his predecessor and successor, Cleveland spent no sentences denouncing the suppression of the black vote in the South. In any case, they very likely expected that the federal enforcement laws, giving nominal protection to nonwhite voters, would fall into what the President would have called “innocuous desuetude”—as indeed they did.[30] The Democratic South could proceed towards wiping out any opposition party without the least hindrance from Washington.

For labor, Cleveland offered no help, beyond calling for sterner enforcement of laws to keep “a servile class” “retaining habits and customs repugnant to our civilization” from settling in America. Nobody doubted who he meant: the Chinese, excluded under an 1882 law for ten years. The new administration would try to make the ban permanent and to prevent those who left the United States from re-entering it. Other immigrants the president had no word against, and not surprisingly. Any literacy or property requirement for newcomers would have cut deep into Democratic constituencies. So, not surprisingly, when Congress put through a literacy test, Cleveland would veto it.[31]

Cleveland’s inaugural did give hints of where his administration meant to go. On foreign policy, he called for an American presence friendly to all, allied to none. There would be no talk of countering foreign designs on the western hemisphere or negotiating commercial treaties. The emphasis on restraint may have been hinting at what a contrast he would be to the man he beat for president, James G. Blaine, whose aggressiveness in promoting American hemispheric influence earned him (not all that fairly) the nickname “Jingo Jim.” It certainly meant that the recently negotiated treaty looking to the building of an isthmian canal was no better than waste paper; by choosing the treaty’s fiercest enemy, Senator Thomas F. Bayard for Secretary of State, Cleveland made that doubly sure.[32]

Cleveland also spoke of the need for action against the land-grabbers out west. It was a promise his administration kept. Even some of his most generous campaign contributors found themselves forced to surrender lands claimed and forfeit because the conditions of the grants had gone unfulfilled.[33] The President’s assertion that Native Americans should be protected and helped towards full citizenship found its realization in moves to drive squatters off their land. In 1887, the Dawes Severalty Act aiming, however defectively, towards integrating the tribes into white society had Cleveland’s support, though he rightly worried that it would strip the nation’s wards of too much of their property too quickly, however benevolently the proceeds from selling it were used.[34]

“Ah, sure, he’s the greatest man I ever saw,” one visitor to the White House exclaimed. “He’s a fine man—a grand man. He wouldn’t promise to do one d—d thing I asked him!”[35] The country could have done worse than Cleveland in his first term. And it did—in his second! For Cleveland’s conscience left him with no flexibility about his principles. “Had he started out in 1893 with the deliberate purpose of killing off all of the few great men in the Democratic party and then destroying it beyond hope of repair, he could not have succeeded more admirably,” a reporter commented later.[36] But already, could one sense how confined the Democratic party’s concept of reform was? Conscientious, clean government Americans would get. To one partisan who chided him for slowness in advancing “the principles of the Democracy,” Cleveland snapped, “I suppose you mean that I should appoint two horse-thieves a day, instead of one.”[37] Nor was it necessarily a bad thing to be, in another associate’s words, “the kind of man who would rather do something badly for himself than to have somebody else do it well.”[38] Administrative restraint and modest promises cautiously carried out all gave the country a sense of security that it preferred and the Democrats the respectable reputation that they needed. But the problems of a country rapidly being transformed by a globalizing economy, by industrial power, and the untrammeled authority of those whose aim was democracy and had the shotguns to deliver it fatal rounds may have needed the boldness that a Cleveland could not give. Gilded Age America may not have been the gainer by a system where the president promised scarcely more than to be a good caretaker.

The Inaugural Address of Benjamin Harrison

by Allan B. Spetter

Benjamin Harrison, the only grandson of a president, William Henry Harrison, to serve as president as well, understood the difficult position he faced almost from the moment he took office. He took the oath of office 100 years after George Washington did so on April 30, 1789 in New York City. Harrison would be the “centennial president” and be compared unfavorably to Washington.

Furthermore Harrison had not won the popular vote. No individual would envy Harrison’s situation. Harrison, however, spoke confidently about what the nation had accomplished over the past 100 years and about the unlimited possibilities of the nation’s future. Harrison began by reviewing the remarkable movement of Americans into the vast spaces of the Great Plains in the quarter century since the end of the Civil War.

He pointed out that the Dakota Territory, so large that it would be split in half and admitted to the Union as two separate states in 1889, had a larger population, estimated at between 150,000 and 200,000, than all but one, Virginia, of the 13 original states according to the census of 1790. (Virginia’s population of almost 750,000 in the census of 1790 included almost 300,000 slaves).

Harrison, who fought with distinction in the Civil War and rose to the rank of brigadier general, emphasized that the end of slavery provided the south with the opportunity to participate in the tremendous growth of the nation’s industrial economy. He asked rather eloquently, “shall the prejudices and paralysis of slavery continue to hang on the skirts of progress?” He called for an improved pension program for Union soldiers and sailors and their widows and orphans. Congress would respond with the Dependent Pension Act of 1890.

It has been said that Harrison tried to do more for the civil rights of African Americans than any president in the 35 years between Lincoln and Teddy Roosevelt. He appealed to the men of the south to realize that a free ballot would benefit both whites and African Americans. He expressed the continuing belief of Republicans of that era that the men who had invested to build an industrial economy in the south would accept the black man as an ally in that effort.

Harrison devoted much of the rest of his Inaugural Address to his vision of the United States becoming a “great power.” To begin with, he made a very strong statement about any future canal linking the Atlantic and Pacific oceans. He said: “It is so manifestly incompatible with the precautions for our peace and safety … that a shorter waterway between our eastern and western seaboards should be dominated by any European Government.”

He went on to explain the foundations of what has been called the “new empire” of the United States. Harrison said: “the necessities of our Navy require convenient coaling stations and dock and harbor privileges.” Harrison engaged in a drawn out attempt to acquire a naval base in Haiti that would protect the Atlantic side of any future canal. Although Harrison believed that Haiti had promised to turn over the base he could not make the decision to use force.

Harrison tried to take the first steps toward creation of an American empire. Some scholars have suggested that the Pacific and the Asian continent should not be considered the Far East from the American perspective but the “Far west.” He reached out into the Pacific and agreed to share control of the Samoan islands with Germany. He attempted to annex Hawaii but would be thwarted by Grover Cleveland, the next president and an ardent anti-imperialist.

Harrison supported an ill-fated attempt by private interests to build a canal across Nicaragua as an alternative to a canal across Panama that would be under the control of French private interests. He realized that a canal and naval bases required a modern navy. Construction of the first modern warships built of steel began in the 1880s but that handful of ships consisted only of cruisers of varying size and two vessels described as second class battleships.

Harrison and his closest friend, Secretary of the Navy Benjamin Franklin Tracy, would oversee a giant leap forward for American naval power. Tracy waged an unrelenting campaign to persuade Congress to approve construction of the first three real battleships, the Indiana, the Massachusetts and the Oregon in 1890. Of more than 10,000 tons displacement, the ships would be dubbed “coastline” battleships to indicate their defensive purpose.

By 1892, however, Congress would approve construction of the first “seagoing” battleship, the mighty Iowa, of 11,400 tons displacement. Congress also approved construction of several larger cruisers. Construction material moved forward from steel to armor. Tracy had lamented that the United States had only the 12th most powerful navy in the world. Harrison and Tracy put the nation on the path toward becoming the sixth largest naval power in the world.

The nation seemed to fill in dramatically by the 1890s. Six new states entered the Union in 1889–1890: North Dakota and South Dakota, Idaho, Wyoming, Montana and Washington, more than in any other administration. The legendary historian Frederick Jackson Turner would declare in an essay written in 1893 that according to the census of 1890 the frontier had disappeared. Some Americans believed that there could be a new frontier, however, in the Pacific and even on the Asian continent.

Harrison did his best to further that idea. He may have been a bit premature. If he had won a second term the United States almost certainly would have annexed Hawaii before 1898. Near the end of his Inaugural Address Harrison stated confidently, “I do not mistrust the future.” His aggressive foreign policy initiatives prepared the United States for the challenges of the 20th century.

Neither Harrison nor any of his contemporaries could have imagined that the economy would plunge into the second worst depression in the nation’s history shortly after Harrison left office in 1893. The depression almost certainly resulted from too rapid expansion of the railroad system and the continuing overproduction of the agricultural sector. The economy would hit bottom in 1894 and slowly recover between 1895 and 1897.

Grover the Good
The Second Inaugural Address of Grover Cleveland

by Matthew Algeo

When I think of Grover Cleveland’s second inaugural address on March 4, 1893—which, to be honest, isn’t very often—I imagine myself standing in the crowd on the east side of the Capitol, shivering in the cold, snow swirling. Looking up at burly Cleveland bundled in his big black overcoat, standing at the front of the wooden stage erected at the bottom of the steps, the dome rising up above him in the gloomy gray sky, I strain to hear his oration. Cleveland was one of the most famous public speakers of his age, with a booming voice befitting his large size. He once gave a speech to twenty thousand people at the old Madison Square Garden and it was said that every single one of them could hear every single word.

But even a bellowing Grover Cleveland cannot overcome Mother Nature on this winter day, and, without the benefit of artificial amplification, his second inaugural address is swallowed up by the howling wind, audible only by those seated closest to him on the stage. Out among the throng huddled on the frozen lawn, Cleveland cannot be heard.

Which is too bad, because, as long-winded Gilded Age inaugural addresses go, Cleveland’s second wasn’t too bad.

A little background: Cleveland, of course, was the first and so far only president to win back the office after losing it. So March 4, 1893 really should have been a triumphant day for him—What a comeback!—but, alas, it was not an auspicious time to assume the presidency. Cleveland inherited a mess from Benjamin Harrison. The country was on the brink of an economic catastrophe that would come to be known as the Panic of 1893, the worst depression in the nation’s history until the Great Depression. The Reading Railroad had just gone bankrupt, the stock market was crashing, and unemployment and hunger were rising. So, in his second inaugural, Cleveland attempts to calm fears. He delicately refers to the crumbling economy as “our present embarrassing situation,” and promises to do everything in his power to “avert financial disaster.” He reassures the public that “prudent and effective remedial legislation” will address the crisis.

At the same time, however, Cleveland warns the people that they should expect little in the way of direct support from the federal government, saying: “The lessons of paternalism ought to be unlearned and the better lesson taught that while the people should patriotically and cheerfully support their Government its functions do not include the support of the people.” This was one of Grover Cleveland’s mantras. There would be no Government handouts. Americans would have to fend for themselves.

Several other themes emerge in the address, some of which sound archaic to us today: a disdain for tariffs, a commitment to “sound money,” opposition to “wild and reckless” pensions for Civil War veterans. But a few themes still resonate. Cleveland was a Democrat—the only Democrat elected between Buchanan and Wilson, in fact—and the Democrats, in the South at least, were the party of white supremacy. But Cleveland—who was from Buffalo—pointedly includes in the address a call for civil rights for African Americans.

“Loyalty to the principles upon which our Government rests positively demands that the equality before the law which it guarantees to every citizen should be justly and in good faith conceded in all parts of the land,” he says. “The enjoyment of this right follows the badge of citizenship wherever found, and, unimpaired by race or color, it appeals for recognition to American manliness and fairness.”

Cleveland also calls for the fair treatment of Native Americans, though in tones that sound a lot like the “paternalism” he earlier disdained. “Every effort should be made to lead them, through the paths of civilization and education, to self-supporting and independent citizenship,” he says. “In the meantime, as the nation’s wards, they should be promptly defended against the cupidity of designing men and shielded from every influence or temptation that retards their advancement.”

Cleveland was conservative—as that term was understood at the time—but he clearly did not believe in frugality when it came to words. A lawyer by training and profession, Cleveland wrote in a style that might charitably be described as cumbersome. Hence this paragraph, in which Cleveland uses seventy-six words to say, in effect: I have a lot of work ahead if me, but I’ll have plenty of help:

“Fully impressed with the gravity of the duties that confront me and mindful of my weakness, I should be appalled if it were my lot to bear unaided the responsibilities which await me. I am, however, saved from discouragement when I remember that I shall have the support and the counsel and cooperation of wise and patriotic men who will stand at my side in Cabinet places or will represent the people in their legislative halls.”

There’s something else in the speech that, in retrospect, is especially striking. At one point, Cleveland likens the looming financial crisis to an unseen malady:

“The strong man who in the confidence of sturdy health courts the sternest activities of life and rejoices in the hardihood of constant labor may still have lurking near his vitals the unheeded disease that dooms him to sudden collapse.”

Just weeks later, Cleveland himself would discover lurking near his vitals a disease that threatened him to sudden collapse: a cancerous growth on the roof of his mouth. The tumor would be removed in a secret operation on a friend’s yacht in early July.

Cleveland’s father was a Presbyterian minister, and Cleveland inherited his faith (if not his sobriety). He ends his second inaugural with a call for God’s blessing:

“Above all, I know there is a Supreme Being who rules the affairs of men and whose goodness and mercy have always followed the American people, and I know He will not turn from us now if we humbly and reverently seek His powerful aid.”

Much of Cleveland’s second term would be consumed by political disputes, sectional rivalries, and labor strife. His refusal to initiate bold government programs to counteract the effects of the depression did nothing to endear him to a public weary of the misery. He did not run for a third term in 1896. By then he was so unpopular that even his own party had repudiated him. At the Democratic convention in Chicago that year, delegates hurled more insults at Cleveland than at the Republican presidential nominee, William McKinley.

Grover Cleveland never wavered from his principles, and he paid the price.

The First Inaugural Address of William McKinley

by Christopher Capozzola

William McKinley stepped to the podium on the east front of the U.S. Capitol building in Washington, unfolded his handwritten speech, and addressed the crowd of 40,000 who had gathered that sunny March afternoon to watch the 54-year-old Civil War veteran take the presidential oath of office. McKinley spoke during the depths of the worst economic downturn America had experienced in its history: four decades later people would talk about the “Great Depression” to distinguish it from the one that followed the Panic of 1893. The last inaugural address of the nineteenth century looked backward, promising Americans the restoration of a better past. But as Thomas Edison’s newly invented “kinetoscope” recorded the inauguration—the first ever captured on film—the day’s events signaled the impending arrival of a modern, industrial, outward-looking, media-drenched age: the twentieth century.

William McKinley knew how to win an election. By 1896, he was an experienced former member of Congress, a popular governor of Ohio, and a natural at the glad-handing style and smoke-filled rooms of Republican Party politics. Born in 1843, McKinley saw combat during the Civil War (long after he retired his uniform, people still called him “The Major”) and built a successful legal career in Canton, Ohio, where he married Ida Saxton, who suffered medical problems throughout her husband’s career. In 1876, the young lawyer won election to the U.S. House of Representatives and served 14 years in Washington before taking the governor’s seat in Columbus in 1892.

Both Republicans and Democrats considered McKinley just a little more moderate than the rest of the GOP. They were right to think so. As a rookie congressman, he had voted for a compromise currency policy known as “bimetallism,” which would protect the gold standard that bankers loved while allowing for a modest increase in the quantity of silver-backed currency, a move that could help working families make ends meet. The Major also pushed through the McKinley Tariff of 1890, which raised tariffs on imports (helping American business) and permitted the negotiation of reciprocal trade deals to sell American factory goods abroad (aiding workers). McKinley trod a middle paths in cultural conflicts as well. As Ohio’s governor, McKinley had taken a modest stand against the nativist American Protective Association and the tide of anti-immigrant politics that swept the nation during the Panic of 1893.

After cruising to victory in the Republican nomination contest, McKinley faced a formidable opponent in William Jennings Bryan, a former Nebraska congressman. “The Great Commoner” electrified the Democratic convention in Chicago on July 9, 1896, with a speech that rallied delegates to a platform of free silver, intoning that “you shall not crucify mankind upon a cross of gold.” Bryan raised the stakes of the election, and in the midst of a national depression, put economic policy on the ballot.

By all accounts, Bryan had the upper hand on the campaign trail. A political outsider, he had youth, energy, oratorical skills, and a bold financial platform. And, thanks to Jim Crow laws and election day violence that had been steadily disfranchising African American voters in the South, the Democrats had a near-lock on the 112 electoral votes of the former Confederacy. But McKinley had an appealingly moderate image, strong support in the northeast and the cities, and knew the American people were tired of the Democratic Party that had given them eight (non-consecutive) years of President Grover Cleveland—a man who did little to relieve the depression and made no effort to appeal to ordinary voters. McKinley sat on a huge campaign war chest (despite McKinley’s slogan of “the people against the bosses,” wealthy industrialists were fully on his side), and had a shrewd campaign manager, Mark Hanna, to steward it.

While Bryan took to the rails for a grueling whistle-stop campaign, McKinley ran a quiet “front porch” effort that invited thousands of onlookers to his home in Canton, Ohio. (The maneuver also spared Ida McKinley the exhaustion that travel would have required.) On the issues, McKinley promised to bury the hatchet of the Civil War, hoping that sectional unity could pick off one or two states from the Solid South. Sensing the public’s hesitation about Bryan’s free silver crusade, and under pressure from party bosses, McKinley veered toward a more conservative embrace of the gold standard. His running mate, New Jersey Governor Garret Hobart, brought an eastern, industrial, big money balance to the ticket. At a time of social upheaval and economic crisis, McKinley was the electorate’s safe choice, and he won an easy victory of 271 electoral votes to 176 for Bryan.

Four months later, McKinley arrived in Washington. On the night before the inauguration, in a mood that he recalled as one of “settled sadness and sincerity,” McKinley dined with the outgoing president, Grover Cleveland, who warned his Republican successor that war loomed in Venezuela or Cuba. The next morning, dressed in an American-made woolen suit, McKinley traveled to Capitol Hill, and took the oath of office from Chief Justice Melville Fuller. Economic issues had determined the election, and the “depression in business and distress among the people” likewise dominated McKinley’s address. The new president acknowledged the crisis that had bankrupted so many (including, nearly, McKinley himself), promising to end the “prevailing business conditions entailing idleness upon willing labor and loss to useful enterprises.” No friend of organized labor, though, McKinley warned of “industrial disturbances,” or strikes, “from which speedy relief must be had.” The new president endorsed the tariff—calling it “settled policy … pursued from the beginning and practiced by all parties”—and called for Congress to meet in special session to increase tariff rates, which, in July 1897, they promptly did. Seeking to thread a moderate needle on the currency question, McKinley reiterated his call for an international conference to consider bimetallism, promising that such a commission would have “early and earnest attention” from his administration. In office, McKinley quickly abandoned that aim and fully embraced the gold standard, enshrining it in law in March 1900.

Taking his oath on a Bible presented to him by the bishops of the African Methodist Episcopal Church, a reminder of the war for racial equality that was rapidly fading from living memory, McKinley embodied the contradictions of white Republicans’ thinking on race. At a time when racist violence was at a national peak, McKinley asserted that “[l]ynchings must not be tolerated in a great and civilized country like the United States.” But he did not push matters too far, observing in his address that the election “demonstrated the obliteration of sectional or geographical lines.” Reaching out a hand of friendship to his former Confederate foes, while remaining largely silent on the aspirations of African Americans, McKinley proclaimed that “[t]he North and the South no longer divide on the old lines.”

On other political issues of the day, McKinley promised moderation. He called for reform of business trusts—though in no particularly detailed way—and endorsed civil service reform and the care of Civil War veterans, “that most deserving body of public creditors.” He urged reform of immigration and citizenship laws but insisted that to anarchists “our gates must be promptly and tightly closed,” a policy that would have done nothing to stop the American-born anarchist Leon Czołgosz, who assassinated McKinley in 1901.

In foreign affairs, the new president once again looked backward to reassure the American people. “We have cherished the policy of non-interference with affairs of foreign governments wisely inaugurated by [George] Washington.” McKinley suggested that the new administration wanted none of the headaches that had plagued his predecessor: no aim of annexing the Hawaiian Kingdom (overthrown with participation by U.S. troops in 1893); no wish for conflict with Britain over Venezuela (which had nearly brought the two nations to war in 1895); no interest in meddling in the Cuban war of independence. There was no sign of the future to come, as foreign affairs quickly displaced domestic issues during McKinley’s first term: the acquisition of Spain’s colonial empire, the brutal suppression of a nationalist independence movement in the Philippines, and the announcement of the Open Door Policy in China. Quite the opposite: “We want no wars of conquest,” McKinley insisted. “[W]e must avoid the temptation of territorial aggression.”

The national press praised the “peaceful, dignified, and practical temper” of McKinley’s address, while that same day William Jennings Bryan offered the press a statement of his own political views, not-so-subtly foreshadowing his plan to challenge McKinley four years later. McKinley’s inaugural address marked the beginning of decades of Republican dominance in the White House. As Americans watched aging Civil War veterans march, as they heard farmers cry out against an urban industrial economy, as political leaders brushed away the political claims of African Americans at home or of Cubans abroad, the United States stood at the end of a passing era, with a president poised to lead them into the twentieth century. On that afternoon in Washington, Thomas Edison’s cameras were there to capture it.

The Imperial Presidency: The Second Inaugural Address of William McKinley

by Christopher McKnight Nichols

In the campaign leading up to his first term, William McKinley often spoke of his hope to focus on pressing domestic issues such as the economic recession that began with the Panic of 1893, the politics and economics of the gold standard and bimetallism, as well as protective tariffs. However, that was not to be. Currency, the economy, and tariffs were significant factors in his first term but McKinley was mostly consumed with foreign relations—including the U.S.’s first war with a European nation in over eighty-years.

A popular rebellion in Cuba, one of many over the past generation, heightened tensions with Spain exploded when the USS Maine did, sinking in Havana Harbor in February 1898; this helped to precipitate war in April of that year, not just in the Caribbean but also in the Pacific. In the aftermath, the U.S. annexed Hawaii, Puerto Rico, and Guam, and also acquired the Philippines and protection over Cuba. One result of such actions is that the U.S. became embroiled in a deadly counter-insurgency war in the Philippines against the very same revolutionaries the U.S. had come to fight with against Spain. The struggle continued through the election of 1900, until the second war in the Philippines formally ended in 1902, although resistance by Filipinos continued. Thus, the politics of the presidential election in 1900 and for a second term revolved largely around foreign policy concerns.

McKinley’s resounding “rematch” victory came over William Jennings Bryan, a “fusion” candidate of the Democratic and Populist Parties, who ran with Vice Presidential nominee Adlai Stevenson. McKinley was on the ticket with war hero “rough rider” New York Governor Theodore Roosevelt because Vice President Garret Hobart died in November 1899, making him the sixth VP to die in office. McKinley garnered nearly a million more votes than Bryan, carrying twenty-eight states and 292 electoral college votes to Bryan’s 17, most of which were in the “solid” Democratic South. It was the rapid victory in what came to be known as the “Spanish American War” combined with an economic recovery that propelled McKinley and the Republicans to a sweeping victory. After wins in the Senate and some losses in the House during the midterm elections of 1898, after 1900 Republicans now held the “trifecta” of power—controlling the White House, the Senate, and the House of Representatives. In short, election to a second term at a moment like this amounted to a mandate. McKinley’s second inaugural therefore focused largely on foreign policy successes and areas remaining to be resolved, while also touching on the major economic and revenue progress made in his first term. He also hinted at changes to tariff and tax policies that he hoped to achieve, as well as international relations goals, all of which would go unfulfilled as he was assassinated in September 1901.

In just the second ever filmed presidential inaugural address, William McKinley paraded to the Capitol on Monday, March 4, 1901. It was an overcast day with clouds and rain overnight. It was dry during the procession to the Capitol and temperatures reached a relatively balmy mid-to-upper 40s by noon. Light rain returned throughout the ceremony that day, but McKinley and those in the audience continued undeterred. With the economy heating up and a successful war against a European nation, the future seemed bright for the president, the Republican Party, and the nation.

“When we assembled here on the 4th of March, 1897,” began McKinley from a stage in front of the capital festooned with flags and surrounded by an enormous crowd, “there was great anxiety with regard to our currency and credit. None exists today,” he proudly declared.

As with most inaugural addresses, McKinley outlined the current state of the U.S. He noted with satisfaction the many success of his first term. In particular, he mentioned settling issues related to currency (by staying on the gold standard), securing more tax revenue, increasing production, and reaching markets and home and abroad. The essence of that message was epitomized by his statement that the “national verdict of 1896 has for the most part been executed.”

So, what next? McKinley noted that in his new term he would adhere to what had worked well in the past one, namely “sound business methods and strict economy in national administration and legislation” without becoming “reckless.” In other words, the people could count on McKinley and the Republicans to continue delivering business-oriented policies to seek more prosperity, limit appropriations, and avoid “waste and extravagance.” He pushed for more reciprocal treaties with other nations to keep promoting prosperity.

Another element of his speech was emblematic of the times and of tensions in the Republican Party. What had been the so-called “party of Lincoln” was beginning to fracture regarding how to grapple with rising Jim Crow segregation, atrocities against Black people, and the role of Democrats in building up systematic disfranchisement in the American South. Yet, in the seventh paragraph, in the middle of the speech, McKinley paused to reflect on the major challenges of the nineteenth century and to declare them overcome: “sectionalism,” he asserted, “has disappeared.” His campaign and the 1900 electoral college map undermines such a claim. Nevertheless, McKinley laid out a case for unity, in essence agreeing to the end of Reconstruction and not making any strong claim for racial justice at the federal level. He avoided explicit discussion of the injustices, such as rampant lynching and acts of violence, that were purging Southern voting rolls of African Americans, themselves stalwart Republican voters. “Division on public questions,” he said, “can no longer be traced by the war maps of 1861.” As in the campaign of 1900, McKinley argued for sectional harmony; he connected prosperity and national greatness to expansion abroad. In the inaugural, he implicitly linked the challenges of ensuring equal protection after the end of slavery given entrenched racism to the advance of American democracy abroad. McKinley tried to ameliorate the numerous concerns of fellow citizens and Republicans by arguing that “our institutions will not deteriorate by extension, and our sense of justice will not abate under tropic suns in distant seas.” But such claims rang hollow to persecuted Black Americans rapidly losing hard-fought citizenship rights as well as to those now subject to U.S. rule in the Caribbean and Pacific.

In keeping with that emphasis on “extension,” much of his speech focused on the foreign policies that helped to cement McKinley’s reputation. Noting that the U.S. “stood on the brink of war” four years earlier, he first made clear that he did his best to avoid war but when conflict became “inevitable,” a bipartisan Congress brought the nation to war reluctantly. The result, he triumphantly declared, was an honorable course of action and victory. He boldly clarified that the U.S. had no interest in ruling Cuba and he assured domestic and international audiences that the U.S. would be a benign protector of the Cuban people (unlike the Spanish). While some in his party and across the nation hoped the U.S. might eventually annex Cuba, and others were adamantly opposed to remaining there, even as protectors, in the speech, McKinley laid out his vision of U.S. objectives: to help get the Cuban people “with all practicable speed” through the stages to establish “a free and independent government.”

McKinley also hinted at a national first at the intersection of commerce, diplomacy, and military policy when he mentions “thrilling scenes in China.” The U.S. had issued what we now know as the “Open Door Notes” in 1899 and 1900, making a worldwide claim that American goods and businesses would not be prevented access to markets in China. To buttress the Open Door pronouncement, in a historic first, McKinley had deployed U.S. marines and naval forces to fight, for the first time alongside European militaries, in China, to rescue their citizens and agents and defend the foreign legation district in Beijing during the Boxer Rebellion (1899-1901).

McKinley concluded the speech by addressing an area of uncertainty. He was expressing his hopes for a peaceful resolution to the ongoing insurgency in the Philippines and articulated a vision much at odds with events on the ground at home and abroad. A robust group known as the Anti-Imperialist League had formed in June 1898 to oppose U.S. expansionism. They particularly rejected the U.S. annexation and rule of the Philippines. Their ranks were remarkably heterogeneous, making it the most diverse large foreign policy lobby in U.S. history and included such figures as Mark Twain, Andrew Carnegie, William James, Grover Cleveland, Jane Addams, Samuel Gompers, and W.E.B. Du Bois, among others. In the campaign of 1900 and at the time of the inaugural address, they pushed back against U.S. occupation policies in the Philippines as an anti-democratic, imperialist project unbecoming of a republican nation born in revolutionary struggle to achieve self-rule. They asked: “is the U.S. a republic or an empire?” William Jennings Bryan echoed aspects of their critique of McKinley’s expansionist policies of ruling peoples “against their will,” but the war was popular, patriotism and nationalism were potent, and the charges did not stick. Still, the facts were difficult to contest. In 1899 U.S. troops had turned on the Filipino revolutionaries and the first democratic government that they had formed. In McKinley’s inaugural address, however, he dismissed this criticism. The U.S. was “not waging war against the inhabitants of the Philippines Island … [rather] a portion of them are making war against the United States.” He concluded his inaugural address by laying out key American aims in the Philippines: pledging to support and protect the Islands and its peoples, which acquired through the Treaty of Paris with Spain (ratified 1899), to end the bloodshed, to guarantee “order” as well as “security for life, property, liberty, freedom of conscience, and the pursuit of happiness.”

A “civilizing” mission was the central cog in the ideological machine of U.S. expansionism, as McKinley and fellow Republican advocates of a “large policy” of U.S. expansionism, such as Massachusetts Senator Henry Cabot Lodge, Roosevelt, and future president William Howard Taft saw it. Taft, hand-picked by McKinley, was then serving as head of the First Philippine Commission (running the government there), soon to be U.S. Civil Governor of the Philippines, advocated a project of tutoring those in the Philippines (as well as Cuba and Puerto Rico) through stages to ascend to the ability to build up and maintain what McKinley called in the speech a “government of liberty.” Taft, at McKinley’s instruction, aimed to create new civil society institutions, representative government, and public education in the Philippines similar to American models.

Many Filipinos, including much of the leadership of the revolutionary armies that had been seeking freedom against Spain, did not see shifting to the protection of the U.S. as a tolerable culmination of their efforts; they continued to fight against those they perceived as a new occupation army, through a series of losses that resulted in a peace treaty in July 1902. In the course of this conflict, both sides committed heinous acts, and the U.S. adopted widely despised techniques of interrogation, such as water-boarding and population control, grouping people into camps, as the Spanish had. Ultimately the U.S. lost far more in the war in the Philippines than in Spain (nearly 5,000 U.S. troops, with Philippine casualties and famine killing as many as 200,000, by some estimates). Sporadic hostilities against the U.S. continued for over a decade. The islands did not achieve independent self-rule until 1946.

McKinley’s speech was hailed as a success. One headline read “Chief Champion of Prosperity Inaugurated for a Second Term.” The presence of foreign diplomats newly recognizing the U.S.’s international power in the wake of war with Spain was widely noted in contemporary accounts, as were the cheers that McKinley received from the crowds that had gathered despite the rain and overcast day.

Though McKinley did not have the great charisma of his VP and successor, Theodore Roosevelt, he was affable and well aware of the importance of his speeches and messages. In his first term, with help from Ohio Republican Senator and arch-strategist Mark Hanna, and especially several exceptional aides, McKinley built up the White House’s first-ever real press operations team. As several scholars have observed, he was essential in the “modernization of presidential press relations.” He held press conferences, offered scoops to favored journalists, provided office space in the White House of correspondents, established routines for monitoring the press and releasing statements, including enforcement against media and journalists who published information before it was agreed they do so. Notably, McKinley built a “war room,” as commander-in-chief to manage the conflicts in the Caribbean and Pacific in near-real time via telegram and telephone, heralding a new era and the dawn of the “imperial presidency,” setting the stage for the Roosevelt presidency’s masterful efforts at public relations.

Where was McKinley headed? From his speech, it seems clear that balancing streamlining federal government operations, promoting business while keeping an eye on individual opportunities, enhancing domestic production, and advancing foreign market access were key areas McKinley hoped to take the nation over the next four years.

It is impossible to know what might have happened if McKinley had not been assassinated on September 14, 1901, at the Buffalo, NY Pan-American Exposition by anarchist Leon Czołgosz. Shot twice in the abdomen on September 6, McKinley had a modest recovery and then lingered as gangrene set in, dying in the early morning on September 14. He was the third president to be assassinated, all in under forty years (including Abraham Lincoln in 1865 and James Garfield in 1881). His killing by a self-professed, unrepentant anarchist, in an era of labor unrest, hyper-nationalism, and Americanism, following a “splendid little war” (as John Hay famously put it), shook the nation. In turn, the McKinley assassination helped to consolidate federal power and propelled anti-radical thought and police action.

Nevertheless, McKinley’s inaugural speech provides some clues as to the aims he might have pursued. In that address and subsequent speeches before his death, he hinted at the desire to push for reductions in tariffs and to advocate for more reciprocal and bilateral trade deals. He had the credibility and support to have accomplished that given his success in championing the major tariff increase (some as high as 49 percent) in 1890 that bore his name, “the McKinley Tariff.” Roosevelt was uninterested in promulgating major tariff changes. Nevertheless, some historians suggest that much of what happened under Roosevelt would have happened under McKinley, such as the Panama Canal, moderate lawsuits and trust-busting efforts, and the settlement of boundary issues with Canada.

On the other hand, Theodore Roosevelt’s policies of pushing for conservation and national parks, his “square deal” approach to the federal government as central mediator in business-labor disputes, U.S. mediation in the Russo-Japanese War, and perhaps some of his later progressive reform tendencies were less likely under McKinley. Roosevelt welcomed Booker T. Washington to the White House in October 1901, a gesture in keeping with Lincoln’s invitation to Frederick Douglass in 1863. This caused great consternation from Southern whites, but Roosevelt held his ground. One cannot imagine McKinley doing so.

After McKinley died, Roosevelt, in his first address to Congress, vowed that government must do more clean up industrial America; to protect individuals, workers, women, and children; to limit working hours, and to prevent the exploitation of natural resources. He also pushed to keep out immigrants who would not be exemplary citizens (by this, he was rejecting radicals like Czołgosz). He also proposed building up the army and navy to help spread U.S. ideals worldwide and solidify the nation’s position as a world power. At the very least, had McKinley lived, some of the most radical of these policies would have been put off until a possible Roosevelt presidency, which could not have happened until 1908. That said, fellow Republicans were calmed by the relative lack of radicalism from the immensely popular and head-strong Roosevelt, something that they had feared when he joined the ticket in 1900.

In turn, had McKinley served two terms and so had Roosevelt, then the ruptures of the Republican Party and the contested four-way election of 1912 likely would not have happened. The election of 1912 drove a wedge between incumbent William Howard Taft and his former mentor and ally Roosevelt, who split off from the Republicans and started his own party, the Bull Moose, which in turn made room for Democrat Woodrow Wilson to pull out a narrow victory, aided also by the remarkable showing of Socialist Eugene Debs. In turn, this suggests another astonishing counterfactual: Roosevelt, not Wilson, might well have been president during World War I. Given Roosevelt’s advocacy of intervention in the war and a League to Enforce Peace, it is entirely possible Roosevelt might have led the U.S. into the Great War sometime after summer 1914 and before April 1917, when a confluence of factors pushed Wilson to declare war as an “associate power” aiming to “make the world safe for democracy.” How might the war have been different if the U.S. had intervened in 1915 or 1916? What might that have meant for the Bolshevik Revolution? The dissolution of the Russian, Ottoman, Austro-Hungarian, German, and other empires? How might a Roosevelt and U.S.-led international organization have been part of the peace-making? The possibilities are endless, and the results unknowable.

The Bully Pulpit: The Inaugural Address of Theodore Roosevelt

by Jean Yarbrough

Although Theodore Roosevelt served as President of the United States for seven and a half years, he delivered only one inaugural address, in 1905. Roosevelt had been tapped to serve as William McKinley’s running mate in 1900, and after McKinley’s assassination in September of the following year, Roosevelt ascended to the Presidency. He was then 42 years old, making him the youngest person ever to serve in that office. During his first term, Roosevelt was determined not to antagonize the Republican Party power brokers so as not to jeopardize his nomination for a second term. To that end, he retained the slain president’s Cabinet and hewed to his policies. But when in 1904 he won a landslide re-election, Roosevelt felt free to chart his own course.

Several things stand out about Roosevelt’s 1905 inaugural address. First, he wrote it himself. It was not until the Harding Administration that presidents began to employ others to help them compose their speeches. Second, for someone whose previous Annual Messages ran to fifty or more pages and who in campaign mode was never at a loss for words, his inaugural address is surprisingly short. The entire address consists of four paragraphs, each with its distinctive theme.

The theme of the first paragraph is American exceptionalism, ending with a challenge. As others before Roosevelt had noted, America was singularly blessed in laying the foundations for its experiment in republican self-government on a new and fertile continent. Unlike the nations of Europe, which had been compelled to fight against “alien races” for their very existence, the United States faced no such mortal foes. In his histories, Roosevelt had celebrated the triumphs of his countrymen over the Mexicans to the south and the French to the north, as well as their victories over the Native American tribes. But compared to the Europeans, none of these contests posed existential challenges to American survival.

Americans were also exceptional because they could profit from the accumulated wisdom of the ages, but they were not weighed down by “the dead hand of a bygone civilization.” This last point is telling because although Roosevelt had praised the work of the more nationalist Founding Fathers and would continue to do so, he would find himself during his second term (and afterward) on a collision course with the principles of liberal republicanism they embraced. In this respect, Roosevelt sounded like no one as much as Thomas Jefferson, who also had inveighed against “mortmain,” insisting that “the earth belongs to the living” and that constitutions should be remade every generation to take into account the progressive character of political science. Yet, Roosevelt “cordially despised” the third President because, in his view, Jefferson’s policies had simultaneously provoked the British into attack and left the United States defenseless against it. As he had explained in his well-received first book,

The Naval War of 1812

, Jefferson’s reliance on citizen-militias and a defensive naval fleet had led the fledgling nation to the brink of disaster. Only in recent years had the United States begun to recover from the disastrous effect that Jefferson’s policies and misguided theories had foisted upon the new republic. Despite these egregious errors, Americans had prevailed and were now poised to take their rightful place on the world stage. The challenge facing the country at the beginning of a new century was whether America could show to the world that a free government could provide for both “the things of the body and the things of the soul.”

This last phrase speaks to one of the twenty-sixth President’s most enduring themes. As a rising Republican reformer, Roosevelt had inveighed against the crass vulgarity of the Gilded Age. “Purely commercial ideals,” he warned in an 1895 essay, were “mean and sordid,” producing timid and fearful men “incapable of the thrill of generous emotion” and lacking in the capacity for heroism and greatness. “American Ideals,” he insisted, must rest on “nobler grounds” than “mere business expediency.” Although his inaugural address had referred only vaguely the “things of the soul,” Roosevelt’s aim was to turn Americans away from their preoccupation with rights, especially the soft and easy enjoyment of the property rights of the wealthy and to reorient them to their duties. Righteousness, rather than rights, would speak to these loftier spiritual needs. As his British friend, Arthur Lee Hamilton, wrote in his introduction to Roosevelt’s biography of Oliver Cromwell, Roosevelt was “essentially a preacher,” who “was not ashamed to invoke the Sword of the Lord and of Gideon.” But in keeping with the teachings of the Social Gospel, Roosevelt directed his energies toward combatting the vulgar materialism of America’s commercial ideals and fighting for a “Square Deal” for America’s working men and women.

From this opening, Roosevelt moved on to foreign affairs, warning that a great nation could not afford to “shirk” its duties or shrink from its responsibilities. His policies aimed at the lofty ideal of national greatness, which required both military might and the cultivation of the manly virtues. In the inaugural address, Roosevelt confined himself to the articulation of general principles, expressing his desire for “sincere and cordial friendship” toward all nations. But in the background, his audience no doubt recalled a number of crises that arose during Roosevelt’s first term, which hit close to home. One of the key issues that emerged early in his presidency involved the application of the Monroe Doctrine. When faced with a crisis in the Dominican Republic, he announced what became known as the Roosevelt Corollary to the Monroe Doctrine. Whereas the original doctrine had opposed territorial aggrandizement by non-American powers, under the Roosevelt Corollary, the United States would now do what it would not allow the Europeans to do: intervene in the domestic politics of other American nations to keep Europeans out. This, Roosevelt suggested, was as much to recognize the rights of our weaker southern neighbors as it was to make sure that our own interests were not threatened. “We wish peace, but we wish the peace of justice, the peace of righteousness.” His noble sentiments, however, may have been belied by his bullying treatment of Colombia in obtaining the territory on which he later oversaw construction of the Panama Canal. Looking beyond the New World of North and South America, Roosevelt’s national greatness agenda ran into trouble in the Philippines. Not all Americans were reconciled to the idea of their democratic republic extending its empire over foreign and far-away peoples.

Roosevelt then turned to domestic affairs, observing that the problems Americans faced in his day could not possibly have been foreseen by “our forefathers.” When the authors of

The Federalist

defended the large democratic republic, they never imagined “administering the affairs of a continent.” The advent of the Industrial Revolution following the Civil War encouraged Americans to apply their initiative, energy, and self-reliance to improve their standard of living. But, he implied, the vast wealth and power generated by that revolution also produced “care and anxiety” that the architects of the commercial republic had not anticipated. Echoing the sentiments of one of his heroes, Abraham Lincoln, he warned that upon the success of the American experiment hinged not only the welfare of his countrymen but also the “welfare of mankind,” and not only for today but for “generations yet unborn.” He counseled resolve and confidence but offered no specific policies.

In his final paragraph, Roosevelt returned to the theme that the problems confronting his generation were entirely novel. He urged Americans to face up to them in the same “spirit” that their forefathers had brought to their problems. In particular, he singled out “the qualities of practical intelligence, of courage, of hardihood, and endurance, and above all the power of devotion to a lofty ideal.” What he did not say is that he was devoted to preserving and advancing the same ideals as our forefathers, that is, to the protection of each individual’s inalienable rights to life, liberty, and the pursuit of happiness, secured by an energetic but limited federal government. In his second term, Roosevelt would demonstrate through his policies and pronouncements that the lofty goal to which he aspired was in fact quite far removed from the ideals of the Founders he claimed most to admire.

Between Giants
The Inaugural Address of William Howard Taft

by Jonathan Lurie

March 4, 1909 found Washington D.C. in the grip of a horrific blizzard, so severe that Taft’s inauguration was shifted inside to the Senate Chamber. The night before, Taft and his wife had stayed at the White House, as the guests of outgoing President Theodore Roosevelt amid an atmosphere replete with apparent tension between the two men. It was, apparently, the first night for the incoming president and the last for the outgoing chief executive who for the remainder of his life appears never to have returned to the Executive Mansion. In the wake of his triumphant re-election in 1904, Theodore Roosevelt had pledged that under no conditions would he accept re-nomination for a second full term in 1908. (He became President in September, 1901 upon the assassination of William McKinley)

During much of Roosevelt’s tenure after 1904, Taft served in the cabinet as his Secretary of War. From 1900 until he joined the Roosevelt cabinet, he had been in the Philippines, where he ultimately become the Governing General. Admittedly a close friend of Roosevelt, Taft declined two offers from him of appointment to the Supreme Court, insisting that he needed to remain in his post on the Archipelago. By 1904, however, Roosevelt persuaded him to return home, even as popular commentary began to link him to the presidency, Roosevelt’s chosen successor in the 1908 election. By any measure a tough act to follow, Roosevelt had been a dynamic, effective and skillful political figure, adept at making use of “the bully pulpit ” But Taft was a very different public figure than Roosevelt. Conservative in outlook, ponderous and deliberative (if not phlegmatic]) in manner, he never was at home in politics. With the exception of a successful 1888 campaign for a judicial seat in Ohio, all of his numerous offices had come to him through appointment rather than election. Politics had no appeal for him. Indeed, “politics. when I am in it makes me sick.” Given a nomination he had not really desired, Taft gamely campaigned in the fall of 1908, always with a concerned Roosevelt cajoling, critiquing, and commenting in the background. He need not have worried, as Taft ended up with more than a million vote majority over William Jennings Bryan.

As Roosevelt”s term wound down, from his cabinet post as Secretary of War Taft observed that increasingly the President became enamored with progressive causes, such as conservation, matters of public health, or ant- trust regulation. Working with the well established conservative Republican congressional leadership, throughout his tenure, Roosevelt had not hesitated to use the issue of tariff reform as a bargaining chip. In return for cooperation in getting other regulatory legislation passed, he made sure that tariff reform somehow never received presidential attention. As president-elect, Taft had to decide how far he would emulate Roosevelt’s neo progressive policies which had tended to split the GOP, as the 1908 election came and went. The answer emerged in his inaugural address, delivered before a packed Senate chamber whose guests included the former President.

Speaking for about an hour. Taft immediately distanced himself from Roosevelt even though he repeatedly lauded the former President’s accomplishments. Taft promised to call Congress into special session specifically to confront the tariff issue, with the result (hopefully) of the “reduction of rates in certain schedules [plus] … the advancement of few, if any.” Pointing to a projected million dollar federal deficit, he added that if import duties (tariffs) do not secure an adequate income, “new kinds of taxation must be adopted, and among these I recommend a graduated inheritance tax.” Before the ensuing congressional battle over the tariff had ended, Taft would propose three new constitutional amendments, dealing with direct election of senators, the franchise for women, and a graduated income tax. All would be adopted. The “scope of a modern government,” added Taft, “has been widened far beyond the principles laid down by the old ‘laissez faire’ school of political writers, and this widening has met with popular approval.”

Taft emphasized the accomplishments of Roosevelt even as he repeatedly called for “further legislative and executive action.” He believed “that the amendments to be proposed are just as necessary in the protection of legitimate business as in the clinching of the reforms which properly bear the name of my predecessor.” If his address thus far had reflected some aspects of progressive thought, its remainder revealed more conservative nuances. Thus Taft referred to the admission of Asiatic immigrants “who cannot be amalgamated with our population,” and hoped that “we may continue to minimize the evils likely to arise from such immigration without unnecessary friction.” Further, he devoted an unusual amount of space—more than any other topic covered in his address—to the South and the issue of racial integration.

In 1909, there could be no doubt concerning two salient facts in American political life: a) that in terms of national politics the South voted a solid Democratic bloc, and b) that especially in the first decade of the 20th century, racial discrimination was widespread throughout the United States, not just in the South. Taft did not seek “to effect a change in the electoral vote of the Southern States,” as much as “an increase in tolerance of political view of all kinds and their advocacy throughout the South.” In other words, a viable Republican Party presence. As to the fifteenth Amendment that supposedly protected the ‘Negro race’ from “any deprivation of the privilege to vote,” it “never will be repealed and it never ought to be repealed, ” even though “if it had not been passed, it might be difficult now to adopt it.” Nevertheless it is now within our fundamental law, and “so long as the statutes of the States meet the test of this amendment, … it is not within the province of the Federal Government to interfere with the regulation by Southern States of their domestic affairs.”

Appointment of a Black to federal office, however, represented a far different matter. In a single convoluted sentence, Taft revealed his innate racial bias: “It may well admit of doubt whether, in the case of any race, an appointment of one of their own to a local office in a community in which the race feeling is so widespread and acute as to interfere with the ease and facility with which the local government business can be done … is of sufficient benefit … to outweigh the recurrence and increase of race feeling which such an appointment is likely to engender.” Further, while it seems outlandish today, in 1909 Taft could believe that “the exercise of political franchises by those of this race who are intelligent and well to do will be acquiesced in, and the right to vote will be withheld only from the ignorant and irresponsible of both races.” In the meantime, echoing Booker T. Washington, Taft hoped that “a still greater improvement of the [Blacks] on the farm, and in the shop, and in other occupations may come.”

Finally, Taft noted and strongly rejected the current progressive proposals to restrict the power of the federal courts to issue injunctions in industrial labor disputes. “As to that, my views are fixed.” Such action “would create a privileged class among the laborers and save the lawless among their number from a most needful remedy available to all men for the protection of their business against lawful invasion.” Indeed, “the proposition that business is not a property or pecuniary right which can be protected by equitable injunction is utterly without foundation in precedent or reason.” The secondary boycott, against which injunctive relief was often directed, “is an instrument of tyranny, and ought not to be made legitimate.”

As has generally been true of his presidency, so too Taft’s inaugural address has not fared particularly well at the hands of historians who, finding much to praise in the tenure of Theodore Roosevelt jump immediately to that of Woodrow Wilson and his “New Freedom.” And again, Roosevelt would have been a hard act to follow for any successor, and all the more so for Taft who differed so markedly from Roosevelt in his approach to politics. “I cannot be more aggressive than my nature makes me. … If the people don’t like that kind of man then they have got to take another.” His address pointed to the forthcoming and tragic triumph of segregation throughout the South, as well as the inability of organized labor to withstand pressure from the federal courts. As an indicator of what was to come, his inaugural speech was all too accurate. On the other hand, Taft’s administration had some positive results as well that were mentioned, albeit all but barely hinted at, in the address. Taken in its entirety, the Taft inaugural address reflected both the prejudices of his time and the potential for change within its context.

The Schoolmaster: The First Inaugural Address of Woodrow Wilson

by Robert A. Enholm

Woodrow Wilson is the most consequential American president in the period between Abraham Lincoln and Franklin D. Roosevelt.

Why should we reexamine President Woodrow Wilson’s first inaugural address? Why do we study history at all? Is it to help explain how we got to the present? Is it to help us understand human nature? Is it to expand our range of experiences and help us to imagine the possibilities of our lives and of society?

In fact, events and personalities from history are constantly reevaluated and reinterpreted in light of prevailing concerns and understandings. Thus one cannot discuss President Woodrow Wilson today without acknowledging that he has become a symbol of the white supremacy that prevailed in and deﬁned his era. A consideration of Wilson’s first inaugural address written ten years ago might not have mentioned his racism, and one written in the future might ﬁnd another point about Wilson’s life to highlight.

So, what are we to say about Woodrow Wilson? In what ways was he merely emblematic of his times? What ideas did he advance that constituted what we today might call “progress”? What events from his biography surprise us or cause us to reconsider our opinion of him or even to reconsider our opinions about ourselves?

Perhaps what history provides is context. Nearly a century after Wilson’s death in 1923, our world is very diﬀerent from his own. How did his thinking and his decisions aﬀect us for good and ill? How did he, raised as a child during the American Civil War, grow to understand and address the changing world he inhabited? How do we grow to understand and address our changing world? In reading his first inaugural address, what can we see there, what is missing, and what can we learn?

Before turning to Woodrow Wilson’s first inaugural address, a brief biography will provide some perspective. Wilson was born in 1856 in Staunton, Virginia, and raised during the American Civil War and Reconstruction Period in Augusta, Georgia and Columbia, South Carolina. Wilson was the son, grandson, son-in-law, and nephew of Presbyterian ministers and theologians. Unique among American presidents, all four of his grandparents were born outside of the United States. His ancestors were Scottish, English, and Irish.

Wilson attended college for a year at Davidson College, in North Carolina, before transferring to the College of New Jersey (later to become Princeton University). Wilson studied law at the University of Virginia and received his master’s degree and PhD at Johns Hopkins University in Baltimore. After teaching brieﬂy at Bryn Mawr College (in Pennsylvania) and Wesleyan University (in Connecticut), he joined the faculty at Princeton University in 1890, where he would spend the rest of his academic career. Wilson was considered an excellent orator and was a prominent and popular professor at Princeton. In 1902 he became Princeton’s President.

As Wilson was wrapping up his graduate academic work, in 1885 he married Ellen Axson. Sadly, she would die of kidney disease as First Lady in the White House in 1914. They had three daughters born in the 1890s.

Wilson’s rise in politics was as improbable as it was unprecedented. He went from university president in 1910, to Governor of New Jersey, for two years, to election as President of the United States in 1912. William Jennings Bryan had been the Democratic Party nominee in three of the four most recent presidential elections. At the 1912 Democratic Party Convention, Wilson did not receive the nomination until the 46th ballot. Bryan eventually supported Wilson at the Convention and was appointed Secretary of State in Wilson’s initial cabinet.

The 1912 Presidential Election was one of the wildest and most unusual in American history. Wilson competed against William Howard Taft, the incumbent President, Theodore Roosevelt, the former President, and Eugene V. Debs, the perennial Socialist Party candidate. Wilson won an Electoral College landslide (435 out of 531) with only 42% of the popular vote. Wilson won because he was well-spoken, a novel ﬁgure in American politics, a Northern governor with Southern roots, and he supported policies that were progressive for his time.

Wilson was the ﬁrst Democrat elected president since Grover Cleveland in 1892 and was the ﬁrst Southern-born president since the Civil War. He was (and remains) the only president to have earned a PhD. In the 1912 election, as Wilson mentions in his first inaugural address, his Democratic Party retained control of the House of Representatives and gained control of the Senate. When Wilson took oﬃce in 1913, there were several Civil War veterans (Union and Confederate) in the Congress.

Reexamining President Woodrow Wilson’s first inaugural address today, we notice several things. First, he uses his lofty oratory to elevate our thinking. The hallmark of Woodrow Wilson’s rhetoric was his exhortation to great ideals and his invocation of universal principles. Wilson begins by acknowledging the success of the Democratic Party, but he immediately pivots to say that his aims transcend partisanship and serve national goals, even humanity itself. “The success of a party means little except when the Nation is using that party for a large and deﬁnite purpose.” The invocation of higher principles is, of course, seen later in Wilson’s speeches in support of the League of Nations. At his First Inauguration, he exclaims, “This is not a day of triumph; it is a day of dedication. Here muster, not the forces of party, but the force of humanity.”

Second, Wilson sets forth a list of practical goals that he intends to achieve. Sometimes in history, the most remarkable innovations are accepted and become so ordinary that the innovation becomes obscured. This may be true of Wilson’s exercise of presidential leadership. He consciously brings to Congress an agenda of desired actions. In his speech, he alludes disparagingly to the tariﬀ system which underpinned the ﬁnances of the federal government. The Sixteenth Amendment to the Constitution had recently been ratiﬁed (after the November election and before the March Inauguration), enabling a reduction in tariﬀs whose revenue to support the federal government would be replaced by revenue from a newly approved progressive federal income tax. The tariﬀ reduction would help the economy and the burden of a progressive tax would be carried principally by the wealthy. The Revenue Act of 1913 was Wilson’s ﬁrst order of business for the new Congress, and its passage fulﬁlled a long-held wish of progressive Democrats.

Similarly, Wilson disparaged the current “banking and credit system,” and before the end of his ﬁrst year in oﬃce, Wilson would push through Congress the Federal Reserve Act, which established a national bank in the United States for the ﬁrst time in over seventy years. The Federal Reserve System remains the foundation of the American banking system today.

In his inaugural address, Wilson also targets the “industrial system,” and during his ﬁrst term as president, Wilson oversaw the passage of both the Clayton Antitrust Act and the Federal Trade Commission Act to strengthen federal regulation of anticompetitive business practices and to help trade unions. The Federal Farm Loan Act and the National Park Service Act, both of 1916, are also anticipated in Wilson’s inaugural address. Wilson’s ﬁrst term in oﬃce achieved the greatest outpouring of progressive federal legislation until the New Deal, a generation later.

The ﬁnal observation to be made about Wilson’s first inaugural address is that it is animated by progressivism, a movement in both Republican and Democratic politics in this era associated with good government, antitrust, conservation of natural resources, eﬃciency, workers’ rights, and product safety. In the progressive tradition, Wilson is not calling for revolution. He identiﬁes and criticizes short-comings of capitalism, but he reassures, “Our work is a work of restoration.” Wilson did not have the advantages of communicating by television or radio. He spoke and wrote in relatively long and complex sentences that lent themselves to being read in newspapers. The progressive spirit is evident: “There can be no equality or opportunity, the ﬁrst essential of justice in the body politic, if men and women and children be not shielded in their lives, their very vitality, from the consequences of great industrial and social processes which they can not alter, control, or singly cope with.”

So, what did Woodrow Wilson overlook? A century later, we have the advantage of history to look back and see what Wilson did not say at his First Inauguration. This takes us into the realm of subjective or normative history (if there is such a realm). We can look back and consider what we think Wilson’s concerns should have been. To a great extent, we must allow ﬁgures in history to be of their own time. The broader question might be to what extent can political leaders get ahead of their people? There are many examples in history of leaders who did unpopular things and yet have come to be regarded as far-sighted. Many other leaders failed for being “ahead of their time.” What did Wilson fail to foresee?

Obvious oversights by Wilson would include international issues. Today Wilson is well known for leading the United States through the First World War and thereafter for leading the establishment of the League of Nations, for which he would receive the Nobel Peace Prize for 1919. But in 1913, the thunderclap that would be the eruption of the First World War was not foreseen.

Similarly, Wilson is silent about the growing Suﬀragist Movement that would lead in less than seven years, during his second term, to the adoption of the Nineteenth Amendment to the Constitution, securing for women the federal constitutional right to vote. Wilson came into oﬃce skeptical of the wisdom of a federal constitutional amendment on the subject. He supported state laws favoring women’s suﬀrage, and in 1915 voted as a citizen for such a law in his home state of New Jersey (it did not pass). Over the course of his presidency, seeing the sacriﬁces American women made for the war and receiving lobbying attention from suﬀragists, Wilson evolved and ultimately gave decisive support to the Nineteenth Amendment.

But from a modern point of view, Wilson’s greatest oversight in his first inaugural address is his silence on the plight of Black people and the segregation and racism that prevailed in his time. We who study the Progressive Era recognize and regret that progressivism in this era did not embrace racial justice. American history includes decades of racial segregation, institutionalized racism, Jim Crow laws, and racial discrimination. Students of history may wish that President Wilson possessed and exhibited more enlightened views on race, but the historical fact is that he did not. This reveals much about him and his contemporaries.

Few in 1913 America were expecting Woodrow Wilson to make progress in dismantling the white supremacy that characterized and dominated so many institutions at this time. The problem of racism was much bigger than any single President. And unfortunately, most Americans did not recognize it as a problem at all.

Some modern observers will accept as suﬃcient to understand Wilson’s racism an explanation that Wilson was from the South. History commands us to see that Wilson’s unenlightened views on race were held more broadly in early 20th century America, even among educated, religious, and socially prominent people, in all regions of the country.

Over the past several years, historians have drawn their attention to Woodrow Wilson, the racism of his Administration, and particularly his perpetuation of and acquiescence to segregation. That scholarship is too voluminous and fast-developing to be summarized here. The problem of racism in America challenges historians. Those who study this era do not want to suggest that they approve of the prevailing racism and do not want their writings to be interpreted as justiﬁcations for racism or apologies for those who perpetuated it. On the other hand, to speak plainly about this era is to describe a time when racial discrimination of the rankest sort, including segregation, was tolerated, accepted, and commonplace.

What can be said is that Wilson did not publicly display the hostile racist animus that was exhibited by many of his contemporaries. But it is clear that Wilson acquiesced to the racist activities and segregation practices of his subordinates, including several cabinet members. Wilson, and much of America, was blind to the problem. It remains the task of historians to explain why. History can help us imagine the challenges that faced civil rights advocates in an era before “civil rights” was even broadly recognized as a term.

The Eve of War
The Second Inaugural Address of Woodrow Wilson

by John Milton Cooper

For if the trumpet give an uncertain sound, who shall prepare himself for the battle>

First Corinthians 14:8, King James & Geneva Bible

As the son, grandson, nephew, and later son-in-law of Presbyterian ministers, Woodrow Wilson would have heard and read those words many times. As a practiced orator and scrupulous stylist, Wilson would never have spoken in that fashion. Yet that was what he did when he delivered his second inaugural address on March 5, 1917. He did that because he believed he had no choice.

Wilson’s first words hinted at the kind of address he would rather have given. “The four years which have elapsed since last I stood in this place have been crowded with counsel and action of the most vital interest and consequence. Perhaps no equal period in our history has been so fruitful of important reforms in our economic and industrial life or so full of significant changes in the spirit and purpose of our political action.” At the risk of bragging, the president could fairly point to the consequential, sometimes monumental domestic legislation he and his party had enacted during those years. More than anything else, those achievements had secured his re-election, to become the first Democrat since Andrew Jackson to win a second consecutive term. But, as he immediately conceded, he could not dwell on those accomplishments because “other matters have more and more forced themselves upon our attention, matters lying outside our own life as a nation and over which we had no control.”

Wilson meant foreign affairs, specifically the titanic conflict raging across the Atlantic. A few days after he was first elected in 1912, he had remarked to a friend, “It would be an irony of fate if my administration had to deal chiefly with foreign problems; for all my preparation has been in domestic matters.” Even before the outbreak of the world war in 1914, “foreign problems,” particularly the revolution in Mexico, had intruded on his time and attention. The sinking of the Lusitania in May 1915 by a German submarine had brought the war in Europe home to Americans, and it had required Wilson to become more of a diplomatist. It was remarkable that he was still able to accomplish as much as he did at home. Even more remarkably, through a combination of patient and daring diplomacy and luck, he got the Germans to rein in their submarines, thereby lifting the threat of being drawn into the war. The president and his party did play the peace card in the 1916 election, with the slogan “He Kept Us Out of War,” but by the time the campaign got under way that appeal referred more to Mexico than to Europe.

This happy state of affairs came to an abrupt end only a month before the inauguration when the Germans unleashed their submarines. “We have been deeply wronged upon the seas, but we have not wished to wrong or injure in return; have retained throughout the consciousness of standing apart, intent upon an interest that transcended the immediate issues of the war itself.”

What hurt Wilson most about this German move, even more than having to set aside his domestic program, was that he had been seeking to end the war and begin to build a new international order. As soon as he knew he had won another term, he had mounted a peace offensive. First, he had dispatched a public call to the belligerents, asking them to state their aims, with a view toward mediating the conflict. Then, just over a week over the Germans’ submarine move, he had gone before the Senate to unveil his vision of a non-punitive, brokered peace, which he called “peace without victory,” to be guaranteed by a league of nations with enforcement powers, which the United States would join. This was Wilson’s fondest wish, to become peacemaker-in-chief to the world.

Now, the Germans had blasted that hope. Arming American merchant ships was his present policy. Yet, he conceded, “We may even be drawn on, by circumstances, not by our purpose or desire, to a more active assertion of our rights as we see them and a more immediate association with the great struggle itself.” Whether or not that came to pass, there was no way to evade involvement with what was happening on and across the seas. “We are provincials no longer. The tragical events of the thirty months of vital turmoil through which we have just passed have made us citizens of the world. There can be no turning back. Our own fortunes as a nation are involved whether we would have it so or not.”

Wilson insisted that America must remain true to the vision he had so recently laid out of a just and lasting peace. He elaborated on a set of propositions he had sketched in his “peace without victory” address: equality of nations, great and small; an end to the balance of power; governments based on consent of the governed; freedom of the seas; limitation of armaments; mutual non-interference in internal affairs. Less than a year later, Wilson would reiterate these ideas and tie them to specific territorial matters in his Fourteen Points. But that would come only when he spoke as the leader of a belligerent nation, who was arrogating to himself the leadership of an armed coalition.

Despite his previous warning in the inaugural address, Wilson did not propose to go down the road to war yet. “I pray to God I may be given the wisdom and prudence to do my duty in the true spirit of this great people. … The shadows that lie dark upon our path will soon be dispelled and we shall walk with the light all about us if we can be but true to ourselves—to ourselves as we have wished to be known in the counsels of the world and in the thought of all those who love liberty and justice and the right exalted.” Noble ideals and soaring rhetoric—qualities for which Wilson was already renowned and would become still more famous—but there was no escaping the uncertain sound from the trumpet he was sounding in this inaugural address.

The sound was uncertain because his mind was likewise uncertain. Wilson would spend another month watching events unfold, reassessing the practicality of armed neutrality, questioning how he could best pursue the kind of peace and world order he envisioned—done mostly in solitary, thoughtful, prayerful, agonizing reflection—before he decided what to do next. Ultimately, he would choose war, and he would do it in the spirit he had shown in this address. In his eloquent speech to Congress on April 2, 1917, Wilson would point again to the propositions he had laid down in the inaugural address, and he would proclaim, “The world must be made safe for democracy.” That sentence would often be misquoted because many wanted to see Wilson’s decision as a clarion call to a crusade. The note he sounded was not a resounding blare; it was a careful, sometimes muted call to fight for something beyond military victory. It was a call to take up the task of building a more just and peaceful world. His trumpet’s sound would have mixed notes, but it would no longer be uncertain.

Return to Normalcy: The Inaugural Address of Warren G. Harding

by James D. Robenalt

“Mankind needs a benediction of understanding,” Warren Harding said on March 4, 1921, when he was sworn-in as the nation’s 29th president. “It is needed among individuals, among peoples, among governments, and it will inaugurate an era of good feeling to make the birth of a new order.”

When he assumed the presidency, nothing was more important than the blessing of peace and the birth of a new order in a world torn apart by a monstrous, barbaric war and rocked by the deadliest pandemic of all time. Harding understood that grave threats remained—resumption of war, famine and starvation, worldwide Bolshevik revolution, economic collapse, and the advent of costly and endless weapons races. The disruption had been incalculable—tens of millions died in the war and fifty to a hundred million perished from the Spanish flu (675,000 in the U.S. alone).

For the United States, these forces of chaos had been met by a leaderless national government. President Woodrow Wilson, the man who headed the executive branch, had suffered a series of debilitating strokes in September and October 1919 as he stumped the country in a desperate attempt to gain acceptance of his view of a new order—the League of Nations. His strokes left Wilson incapable of performing his job, at first physically and later emotionally. His hovering spouse, Edith Wilson, allowed few visitors to his sickroom and his condition was largely blinded to the American public.

Thus, for nearly a year and a half before Harding’s inauguration, things were allowed to drift aimlessly in what was perhaps one of the most precarious times of humankind. The economy was supercharged from the war and it hit overdrive in the year following the end of the war, but then collapsed in the spring of 1920. Soldiers returning from Europe could not find jobs. Rapid inflation was followed by ruinous deflation. War taxes weighed down the economy that had to survive to save the world, prostrate from its war indebtedness.

He took the oath on the East Portico of the Capitol at 1:18 p.m. “under a brilliant sky and in a keen atmosphere,” per the New York Times. Woodrow Wilson rode with Harding from the White House to the Capitol, but then turned back, lacking the strength to witness the swearing-in of his successor. He was driven inauspiciously to his new home on S Street. Chief Justice Edward D. White, black-capped and gowned, a massive man, administered the oath on a Bible used by George Washington in his first inaugural. Harding had it opened to Micah 6:8, his favorite verse: “What does the LORD require of thee but to do justly and to love mercy and to walk humbly with your God?”

This was the first inaugural where an electronic amplification system was employed, with speakers hidden under a huge flag in the roof of a kiosk of Corinthian architecture built on the Capitol steps for the ceremony. In previous inaugurals, one had to be within shouting distance to hear the speaker. On this day, a large crowd could hear Harding’s words in resonant tones echoing in front of the speaker’s platform.

They cheered for certain lines, mainly those directed against the League of Nations and in favor of national sovereignty. “A world supergovernment is contrary to everything we cherish and can have no sanction by our Republic,” he said, drawing heavy applause according to Times.

But Harding surprised many with speech. While he sought to protect America’s sovereignty and any decision to use its power, he was solicitous of those who believed that the United States had a sacred mission in the world. America might avoid unnecessary “entanglements” with other nations of the world, but it would not remain aloof.

He built on the theme that the United States alone was the guiding example of a representative form of government, one that had selflessly thrown itself into a war to end what had devolved into a ferocious contest that threatened civilization itself. “In the beginning the Old World scoffed at our experiment,” he said. “Today our foundations of political and social belief stand unshaken, a precious inheritance to ourselves, an inspiring example of freedom and civilization to all mankind.”

He warned that the United States, while it would allow no other governments to decide its fate, would not shrink from challenges to the international order: “We want to do our part in making offensive warfare so hateful that Governments and peoples who resort to it must prove the righteousness of their cause or stand as outlaws before the bar of civilization.”

These warnings delivered, he turned to higher calls for associations among nations, a code word that made reservationists and irreconcilables in his party edgy. “We are ready to associate ourselves,” he declared, “with the nations of the world, great and small, for conference, for counsel; to seek the expressed views of world opinion; to recommend a way to approximate disarmament and relieve the crushing burdens of military and naval establishments.”

Disarmament, in fact, would be one of the great achievements of his administration. The Washington Naval Conference he called in 1921, resulting in the world’s first arms’ limitation treaty, would lead to his nomination for the Nobel Peace Prize (unawarded in 1923 after he died, as Nobel rules discouraged posthumous honors).

As importantly, he recommended the U.S. join the World Court, a suggestion that never came to pass because of deep isolationists sentiment in the country.

Having addressed international concerns, Harding turned to his plans for the United States, recognizing that unless America put its house in order, the world could never recover from the war wreckage; indeed, events could have turned to revolution and anarchy. This task of reconstruction, he warned, was complicated and would not be easy. Burdens would fall unfairly on some. He sought the cooperation of all, management and labor. “Our people must give and take,” he pled.

Two areas required immediate attention: reducing government expenditures and taxes. He avowed: “We can reduce the abnormal expenditures, and we will. We can strike at war taxation, and we must.” To accomplish these complex tasks, Harding insisted that the government had to be placed on a budget for the first time. He would create the first Bureau of the Budget, today the Office of Management and Budget. He spoke, he said, for “administrative efficiency, for lightened tax burdens, for sound commercial practices, for adequate credit facilities.”

His tactics worked. After a worsening period economically, the United States recovered and helped undergird some precious measure of economic stability in the world.

He welcomed women, who had voted for the first time in federal elections in 1920, into their rightful place as citizens. He addressed wounded veterans brought over from Walter Reed Hospital. “A generous country will never forget the services you rendered,” he said. His administration would create the first Veterans’ Bureau (today the Department of Veterans Affairs) to care for those wounded and maimed in the war.

He even winked at a sort of New Deal concern for the unemployed and those in poverty. “Wealth is not inimical to welfare,” he observed, “it ought to be its friendliest agency.” He explained: “There can never be equality of rewards or possessions so long as the human plan contains varied talents and differing degrees of industry and thrift, but ours ought to be a country free from the blotches of distressed poverty.”

Presaging Franklin Roosevelt, he pondered, “We ought to find a way to guard against the perils and penalties of unemployment.”

He concluded by imploring “the favor and guidance of God in His Heaven.” Knowing his task too great for any one man, he took comfort in the fact that a hundred million Americans would share his responsibility.

Returning to Micah, “to act justly, and to love mercy, and the walk humbly with thy God,” Warren Harding ended by promising, in an old-fashioned way, “This I plight to God and country.”

Cool Cal: The Inaugural Address of Calvin Coolidge

by Amity Shlaes

How a citizen becomes president can tell us much about the presidency that follows. In the case of Calvin Coolidge, that “becoming” was unusual. Coolidge didn’t win an election to become president. He became president rather because of a tragic event: the death of President Warren Harding in August, 1923. Coolidge, then vice-president, happened to be vacationing in the hilly village where he was born, Plymouth Notch, Vermont. His father John woke him in the middle of the night to tell him the awful news. His father, a notary, was the only legal authority present at the moment. Yet, everyone in the small house understood the importance of a quick swearing-in. Each minute they delayed was a minute that the United States went without a president. Coolidge dressed and said a prayer. He consulted by telephone with Washington on what he might do. There was no time to dress up in tuxes, or gowns. At 2:47 a.m. Coolidge’s father swore the president into office before the family bible under a kerosene light. Only a few people witnessed the events of that historic night: Mrs. Coolidge, a local congressman, and a newspaper man.

The next day the Coolidges boarded the train in Rutland and traveled south to Washington so that Coolidge might take the greatest office in the land. Coolidge gave no real speech. Out of respect for the law—but not conceding that the inauguration of Plymouth was invalid—Coolidge was sworn in once again in Washington. But the Homestead Inauguration of America’s thirtieth president was so special that to this day each August the Coolidge Foundation and the State of Vermont gather a small crowd to reenact it at Plymouth Notch. Coolidge descendants often play the roles of the new president or Mrs. Coolidge.

In 1924, Coolidge won election in his own right—and with a powerful mandate. He delivered his first and only presidential inaugural address at the usual March ceremony. The themes he emphasized in that address were the very same the astute observer could have picked up at that initial, improvised inauguration in Plymouth.

The first of these themes is the importance of the divisions of government—not only the three branches in Washington but also the division of government between Washington and the states. Coolidge understood that the tension between the centralized and the local was, as he put it, evidence of “matchless wisdom that is enshrined in our Constitution.” Just as on that night in Plymouth, America must always balance the needs of the nation with respect for the local authority, even if that authority is a mere notary. America’s constitutional structures, Coolidge said in 1925, “need constant effort and tireless vigilance for their protection and support.” National government, as he liked to refer to it, became tyranny if it did not “faithfully observe the rights of persons. Under our institutions their rights are supreme.” Those rights include the right to hold property. But individuals also had duties. Coolidge also recalled: “all owners of property are charged with a service.”

In his Washington inaugural, Coolidge also emphasized another preoccupation of that Plymouth night: “obedience to the law.” Coolidge elaborated: “those who want their rights respected under the Constitution and the law ought to set the example themselves of observing the Constitution and the law.” Further, Coolidge added that “those who disregard the rules of society are not exhibiting a superior intelligence, are not promoting freedom and independence, are not following the path of civilization…”

What must the American government do to respect its citizens? Coolidge laid that out in his inaugural of 1925 as well. For Coolidge, that respect was best shown when government restrains itself and leaves Americans to lead their own lives. Toleration was a key principle. Though we all may feel differently on important issues, “the fundamental precept of liberty is toleration.” Free speech and free thought are important for “the mind of America must be forever free.”

The best way for the government to do that, Coolidge said, was to practice “economy in public expenditure with reduction and reform of taxation.” Tax policy sounded mundane, Coolidge said, but it was not. The government should collect only enough revenue to meet “public necessity.” Federal spending amounting to more than that was “legalized larceny.” The president elaborated: “I favor the policy of economy, not because I wish to save money, but because I wish to save people. The men and women of this country who toil are the ones who bear the cost of Government.”

A final theme of Coolidge’s inaugural address was religious faith. The American empire he said, was not one of “blood and force.” America’s strength, the president said, was to lead by example. “The higher state to which she seeks the allegiance of all mankind is not of human, but of divine origin.”

What to make of Coolidge’s words, at once so familiar and so strange in our current context? At a time when our nation seems so very imperfect, and differences almost insurmountable, Coolidge can offer consolation. America has lofty principles, but it can be imperfect, just as the makeshift inauguration of 1923 was imperfect. “The encouraging feature of our country,” Coolidge said in 1925, “is not that it has reached its destination,”—it hadn’t then, just as it has not now. Rather what mattered was that “it has overwhelmingly expressed its determination to proceed in the right direction.” Let us express such determination today.

The Inaugural Address of Herbert Hoover

by Kendrick A. Clements

In his memoirs, written nearly twenty years after he left the White House, Herbert Hoover admitted that the inaugural address he delivered on March 4, 1929, was not the speech he would have liked to give. As Secretary of Commerce for eight years in the Harding and Coolidge administrations, Hoover had been an activist on the model of pre-World War I progressives like Theodore Roosevelt. But the postwar Republican Party was dominated by small-government conservatives and isolationists like Warren Harding and Calvin Coolidge. Harding was willing to give the secretary considerable leeway to pursue his ideas, but Coolidge, who derided Hoover as “wonder boy,” resisted or obstructed his efforts to expand the functions of the federal government to serve the growing population of an increasingly industrialized nation in an inter-connected world.

Election to the presidency seemed to give Hoover an opportunity to press forward his ideas for expansion of the federal role, but when he sat down to write his inaugural address he was keenly aware that “certain differences” between his and Coolidge’s “points of view” cast a chilling shadow over his ambitions. Given Coolidge’s great popularity in the country and especially in the Republican Party, he risked splitting the party if he suggested taking the country in a dramatically different direction from his predecessor.

The question, then, was what he could propose to do. In the end, he decided that he had to confine himself mainly to uncontroversial generalities—to “American ideals and aspirations,” as he put it in his memoirs. That was not a prescription for a stirring speech. Never a particularly good public speaker, and always better at dealing with the specific details of a problem than at enunciating broad principles or inspiring his listeners, Hoover began with some vague observations about a tricky issue, foreign policy. The country, he declared, had not only recovered from the war but had contributed to “the recovery and progress of the world,” giving “renewed hope and courage to all who have faith in government by the people.” Having thus staked a claim to world leadership without challenging his party’s isolationism, with which he privately disagreed, he slipped away from that difficult topic with more platitudes about how the world had come to respect America’s “influence and high purposes.”

From foreign policy, Hoover moved on to the main theme of his 1928 campaign: the national prosperity for which Republicans had happily taken credit. The nation, he proclaimed, had achieved greater “comfort and security than ever existed before in the history of the world,” a victory over “widespread poverty” that assured Americans “a higher degree of individual freedom than ever before.” Although slightly less sweeping than his claim in his speech accepting the Republican nomination on August 11, 1928, that the United States was on the threshold of a “final triumph over poverty,” the contrast between his assumption of permanent prosperity and the grinding poverty of the Great Depression would forever shape Americans’ memories of the thirty-first President.

Hoover devoted the longest section of his speech to a discussion of lawlessness that had grown out of popular opposition to the eighteenth amendment to the Constitution, which had made the sale and consumption of alcoholic beverages illegal. Probably he would have preferred to avoid the topic. His friends remembered that when he lived in Europe before the war he enjoyed a martini before dinner and sometimes drank a glass of wine, but he was neither strongly against nor for Prohibition. When the law passed, he declared that while Secretary of Commerce he would neither serve nor drink alcohol. He found personal abstention easy, but as a presidential candidate in the deeply divided America of 1928 the issue was inescapable. Al Smith was an outspoken advocate of repeal, which created a dilemma for Hoover. He doubted that complete enforcement of Prohibition was possible, but he was unwilling to simply concede to Smith the votes of the “wet” cities on the East and West coasts. Accordingly, he attempted to find a middle position that might pacify both sides. In the end, he issued a statement describing Prohibition as “a great social and economic experiment, noble in motive and far-reaching in purpose” and promising “the efficient enforcement” of the law.

His statement was widely ridiculed during the campaign as an attempt to straddle the problem, and Hoover apparently felt compelled to explain in his inaugural that he actually had a specific policy in mind. Ignoring the issue of repeal, he identified the central problem as “disregard and disobedience of law.” As long as Prohibition remained the law, he declared, individual Americans must respect and obey it, the states must make good faith efforts to enforce it, and even more important, “the entire Federal machinery of justice” must be overhauled to make enforcement swifter and more efficient. His only specific proposal, however, was the appointment of a “national commission” to study “the whole structure of our Federal system of jurisprudence” and to present recommendations for reform. To those listening to the speech, it appeared that the mountain had labored and brought forth a mouse.

Having thus attempted to divert the torrent of debate about repeal into the dry channels of legal reform, Hoover then turned for the remainder of his address to a laundry list of proposals he had been advancing throughout the previous decade. They included self-regulation of business (with strict government oversight), promotion of education, a strengthening and extension of public health programs, the assertion of American leadership in advancing “the reign of justice and reason toward the extinction of force” in the world, and the promotion of what has come to be called the “good neighbor policy” toward Latin America. Most of these ideas were vague enough to elicit broad but shallow support. A reiteration of President Harding’s 1923 recommendation that the United States join the Permanent Court of International Justice, however, was sufficiently specific to awaken extreme isolationists and never won the approval of the Senate. A promise to call a Special Session of Congress to deal with the agricultural depression that had been haunting the country, and to reform the tariff, though offered in the optimistic atmosphere of prosperity, would evoke very different responses in the post-Crash atmosphere of late 1929. As the Depression deepened, a forgettable speech would be buried by more pressing issues.

While Hoover spoke, the skies opened and cold rain poured down. Both the President and First Lady were soaked and shivering by the time the event concluded. Hoover closed with an assurance that the country’s future was “bright with hope,” but the weather was a better omen for the fate of his administration than his optimistic words.

The First Inaugural Address of Franklin D. Roosevelt

by Cynthia M. Koch

On Inauguration Day, March 4, 1933, Washington was cold and overcast. Homeless men wandered the streets. Flags hung at half-mast in memory of Senator Thomas J. Walsh, who had died while en route to Washington to serve as attorney general.

The president-elect and his family, Cabinet members, and close associates attended a precedent-setting prayer service at St. John’s Episcopal Church directly across Lafayette Square from the White House. The Reverend Endicott Peabody, headmaster of Groton School (which FDR had attended as a boy), officiated. When the service ended, FDR remained on his knees in silent prayer.

At the Capitol, with his legs encased in steel braces, the president-elect steadied himself on the arm of his eldest son James as he made his way to the rostrum. He placed his hand on the ancient Roosevelt family bible, printed in Amsterdam in 1686. It was open—as it always was when FDR was sworn to office—to St. Paul’s First Epistle to the Corinthians: “And now abideth faith, hope, charity, these three; but the greatest of these is charity.” Breaking another tradition, he repeated word for word the solemn oath administered by Chief Justice Charles Evans Hughes. Then, as the crowd grew quiet, Franklin Roosevelt offered hope to a desperate people with bold words that still reverberate in public memory. “This great nation will endure as it has endured, will revive, and will prosper. … [T]he only thing we have to fear is fear itself.”

The address was delivered in one of the nation’s darkest hours, at a time when many objective observers felt Americans had plenty to fear. The country was in the third year of the worst economic depression in its history. By the end of 1932, fifteen million workers—one out of every three—had lost their jobs. U.S. Steel’s payroll of full-time workers fell from 225,000 in 1929 to none in early 1933. In the steel town of Youngstown, Ohio, unemployment was 78 percent—more than three times the national average of 25 percent.

People were hungry. Ninety percent of the population of the coalfields of West Virginia and Kentucky suffered from malnutrition. In the cities, where there were some social services, only about one in four unemployed workers received any assistance from a patchwork of local government aid and charity. Long lines for bread and soup snaked through city streets.

Farm income fell from $12 billion in 1929 to $5 billion in 1932. The price of a bushel of Iowa corn was worth less than a package of chewing gum. In the South thousands of acres of cotton rotted in the fields, not worth the cost of harvest. Farmers could not meet their mortgage payments or taxes. Between 1929 and 1933, a third of all American farmers lost their farms.

By early 1933 nearly half of the $20 billion in home mortgages was in default. More than a thousand homeowners were foreclosed daily. Renters were evicted. People thrown out of their homes gathered in shantytowns derisively called Hoovervilles. Schools were closed as state and local governments ran out of money to pay their teachers.

Violence was in the air. In Iowa and Nebraska, a group known as the Farm Holiday movement announced a farmers’ strike. They blocked highways leading to the agricultural markets in Omaha, Sioux City, and Des Moines. They dumped milk into ditches. They turned back cattle. When forty-nine picketers were arrested in Council Bluffs, Iowa, a thousand farmers assembled to break them out of jail.

A group of 43,000 desperate World War I veterans and their families arrived in Washington from all over the country in the summer of 1932. Known as the Bonus Army, they demanded early payment of bonuses due them for military service. Their camp was forcibly dispersed under orders from President Hoover, resulting in the death of two veterans.

The Interregnum

Roosevelt was elected on November 8, 1932, but the Twentieth Amendment—which changed Inauguration Day from March 4 to January 20—would not be in effect until 1937. In the sixteen long weeks before March 4, 1933, conditions grew even more desperate as a new banking crisis gripped the nation. On inauguration morning the New York Stock Exchange suspended trading, as did the Chicago Board of Trade. Thirty-eight states, including New York and Illinois, had already closed their banks.

It was an age of dictators and democracy was in peril. For many Mussolini’s Italy and Stalin’s Soviet Union seemed preferable to the dysfunction in the United States. Hitler’s rise to power on January 31 only confirmed belief in the efficiency of the totalitarian state. Former New York Governor Al Smith, once a political mentor to FDR and now a critic, compared America’s plight to the crisis of war. “What does a democracy do in war,” he asked. “It becomes a tyrant, a despot, a real monarch.” In World War I, he declared with exaggeration, “[W]e took our Constitution, wrapped it up and laid it on the shelf and left it there until it was over.” Alf Landon, Republican governor of Kansas who would be Roosevelt’s opponent in 1936, declared, “[E]ven the iron hand of a national dictator is in preference to a paralytic stroke.” Visiting Roosevelt in Warm Springs, Georgia, in January, the respected columnist Walter Lippmann told FDR, “The situation is critical, Franklin. You may have no alternative but to assume dictatorial powers.”

In February the country almost lost the president-elect to an assassin’s bullet. After Roosevelt spoke from an open car to a crowd in Miami on February 15, gunshots rang out. An out-of-work anarchist named Guiseppe Zangara fired five bullets at FDR from close range. A bystander deflected his hand, but Zangara wounded four people and fatally shot Chicago Mayor Anton Cermak. Roosevelt’s calm and courage in the face of the attack gave confidence to a badly shaken nation.

Inaugural Address

Roosevelt began working on his Inaugural Address as the banking crisis deepened. On February 27 his advisor Raymond Moley arrived with a draft at the Roosevelt home in Hyde Park, New York. FDR began to rework it (ultimately there were four drafts) and completed it the next day—except for the reference to fear, which was added after an introduction from Louis Howe arrived on February 28 containing the phrase “We have nothing to fear but fear itself.” FDR added it to his speech and elaborated on it. The origins of the phrase are murky and Sam Rosenman, FDR’s advisor and speechwriter, linked it to Henry David Thoreau’s “[N]othing is so much to be feared as fear,” but Moley—who was with FDR at the time—discounts the connection. Scholars have noted that the concept has a long history; Francis Bacon said essentially the same thing in the early seventeenth century.

Roosevelt made one last change before delivering the nineteen-minute speech: the opening line “[T]his is a day of consecration,” which he added by hand while waiting in the Senate Committee Room of the Capitol before the inauguration. In delivering the speech, he added one more crucial word: “This is a day of national consecration.” This change encapsulates the intermingling of religious faith and patriotism that gives the speech its power.

In the famous opening paragraph, Roosevelt embellished the “fear” phrasing with a reassuring reminder of the nation’s history. “This great Nation will endure as it has endured, will revive and will prosper.” The memorable statement “So, first of all, let me assert my firm belief that the only thing we have to fear is fear itself—nameless, unreasoning, unjustified terror which paralyzes needed efforts to convert retreat into advance” introduces the speech’s war theme. “In every dark hour of our national life a leadership of frankness and vigor has met with that understanding and support of the people themselves which is essential to victory.”

FDR was summoning people to a holy war against “false leadership.” The present crisis, he assured them, “comes from no failure of substance. We are stricken by no plague of locusts.” At fault are the “unscrupulous money changers, ” who have now been driven from “their high seats in the temple of our civilization. We may now restore that temple to the ancient truths.” And those ancient truths are “social values more noble than mere monetary profit.”

The body of the speech describes his proposals for “action and action now”: jobs for the unemployed, “treating the task as we would treat the emergency of a war” with the workers “accomplishing greatly needed projects to stimulate and reorganize the use of our natural resources”; national planning to address the “overbalance of population in our industrial centers and … to provide a better use of the land for those best fitted for the land”; and “two safeguards against a return of the evils of the old order,” … “strict supervision of all banking and credits and investments” and … “provision for an adequate but sound currency.”

Again, he returned to the martial theme. “These are the lines of attack,” he assured his listeners, while pledging that he will use the instruments of democracy. “I shall presently urge upon a new Congress, in special session, detailed measures for their fulfillment, and I shall seek the immediate assistance of the several States.”

He dismissed Hoover’s focus on international trade as secondary to “first things first,” that is, “putting our own national house in order and making income balance outgo.” In terms of international relations, FDR spoke of dedicating the nation to “the policy of the good neighbor—the neighbor who resolutely respects himself and, because he does so, respects the rights of others.”

Approaching his conclusion, Roosevelt introduced “interdependence,” an idea that would be repeated throughout his presidency. “[I]f we are to go forward, we must move as a trained and loyal army willing to sacrifice for the good of a common discipline.” He called upon Americans to embrace “the larger purposes [that] will bind upon us all as a sacred obligation with a unity of duty hitherto evoked only in time of armed strife.”

He then moved to his peroration, a declaration that Eleanor Roosevelt said “was very solemn and a little terrifying.”

I am prepared under my constitutional duty to recommend the measures that a stricken Nation in the midst of a stricken world may require. These measures, or such other measures as the Congress may build out of its experience and wisdom, I shall seek, within my constitutional authority, to bring to speedy adoption. But in the event that the Congress shall fail … I shall ask the Congress for the one remaining instrument to meet the crisis—broad Executive power to wage a war against the emergency, as great as the power that would be given to me if we were in fact invaded by a foreign foe.

The speech electrified the nation and was soon followed by the remarkable legislative accomplishments of the First Hundred Days. The economic success of Roosevelt’s declaration of war against the Great Depression is debated by historians, but one thing is clear from this speech and the leadership that followed: Roosevelt rallied the people and restored confidence in democracy at a time when its very survival was at stake.

"One-third of a Nation..."
The Second Inaugural Address of Franklin D. Roosevelt

by David M. Kennedy

Franklin D. Roosevelt’s Second Inaugural Address, the first to be delivered in the newly established inaugural month of January, is one of the most richly instructive of all such addresses. Its anaphoric litany of national failings, culminating in the famous declaration about “one third of a nation ill-housed, ill-clad, ill-nourished,” has echoed down the decades. But though frequently misunderstood, not least because of that resonant passage, if read carefully the address amounts to one of the American republic’s great state papers, and bears comparison with Abraham Lincoln’s storied Second Inaugural.

Like Lincoln’s in 1865, Roosevelt’s address in 1937 was a model of concision and the compelling eloquence of simple, unadorned language. Like Lincoln, Roosevelt framed his remarks around moral as well as political precepts. Most importantly, both speeches open windows into the respective presidents’ souls and their most deeply held philosophical values, even while brilliantly illuminating the transformative historical episodes of the Civil War and the Great Depression.

Like many second-termers, FDR began by comparing the (improved) state of the nation on the instant occasion with the (parlous) moment when he had taken office four years earlier. Then, thirteen million workers were jobless, some twenty-five percent of the labor force; national income had plummeted to half its 1929 level; virtually all banks had shuttered their doors. On Inauguration Day in March 1933, Roosevelt had memorably begun the work of bracing up a despairing people when he intoned that “the only thing we have to fear is fear itself.” There followed the out-pouring of reforms that history knows as the New Deal. The Depression still weighed heavily on the land in 1937, but Roosevelt justifiably boasted that even as he spoke the economy was measurably recovering, while the national mood had markedly improved.

But Roosevelt devoted fewer than 100 of the address’s 1,812 words to that familiar kind of self-congratulatory, political boiler-plate.

Instead, he invoked a different historical reference point altogether, not the Depression’s abysmal depth in 1933, but “the one hundred and fiftieth anniversary of the Constitutional Convention which made us a nation.” He then launched into an exemplary presidential civics lesson, mounting a vigorous defense not simply of his own record, but of the whole concept of the positive, activist state as a legitimate, even necessary, feature of democratic governance.

Though many listeners at the time may not have fully appreciated it, Roosevelt proceeded to offer a commendably succinct summary of the critique of legacy political institutions and practices as well as laissez-faire economic nostrums that the Progressive generation of FDR’s youth had struggled to articulate. Government was not simply a necessary evil, as Thomas Paine had preached in the Revolutionary Era and generations of Americans had ritually repeated (as some still do). Democratic government, said Roosevelt, also had the “power to do good.” Like his predecessors, distant-cousin Theodore Roosevelt and scholar-in-politics Woodrow Wilson (in whose administration FDR had served as Assistant Secretary of the Navy), FDR championed the positive role of the state as the instrument of society’s collective will and citizens’ shared purposes—and as counterpoise to the enormous accretions of power that had taken root in the modern industrial economy. That aspirational notion had galvanized an earlier generation, but it was Roosevelt’s New Deal that finally brought to fruition many of the older Progressives’ ambitions for reforms like capital market regulation, secure old-age pensions, unemployment relief, protections for labor-union organization, facilitation of home ownership, electrification of the countryside, conservation of landscapes and natural resources, and huge nation-building infrastructure investments like the dams and hydroelectric installations that jump-started the economic and social modernization of the South and sparked a second westward movement into the arid regions of the United States. “The Constitution of 1787,” Roosevelt summed up, “did not make our democracy impotent.”

It’s worth noting that Roosevelt cast this robust assertion of government’s proper scope in language appropriate to the substance of his argument. He used the word “we” no fewer than 70 times, “our” another 30 times, and the perpendicular pronoun “I” no more than a dozen times, five of them in the widely quoted passage about “I see one-third of a nation …”

In due course Roosevelt returned to the ambient circumstances of 1937. “Our progress out of the depression is obvious,” he said. “[W]e have come far from the days of stagnation and despair.”

But then there followed one of the most remarkable statements in the annals of presidential addresses, Inaugural Addresses included, to which FDR singularly attached an exclamation point: “Such symptoms of prosperity may become portents of disaster!”

One will look long and in vain for a comparable remark by any politician, anytime, anywhere. Here was a president in the very act of celebrating his electoral triumph, justifiably crowing about the progress made in his first administration. Why in the same breath would he appear to undercut that upbeat message with the highly unorthodox—even heretical—assertion that prosperity amounted to disaster?

The answer to that riddle lies in the passage immediately following FDR’s extraordinary lamentation about the dangers attendant on prosperity. It was here that Roosevelt turned to the plight of the “one-third of a nation,” the “tens of millions” of Americans who were denied “what the very lowest standards of today call the necessities of life.”

Casual students of the Roosevelt era might be forgiven for assuming that when the president rehearsed the fate of that suffering one-third, he was referring to the victims of the Great Depression. But a closer reading compels a different conclusion altogether. By early 1937, FDR and others believed—mistakenly, as it turned out—that the worst was behind them, that the New Deal had broken the back of the Depression and put the nation on the road to recovery. But Roosevelt knew that “our present gains were won under the pressure of more than ordinary circumstances.” The return to “normalcy,” to business as usual, might well mean returning to politics as usual, to the kind of stasis that was purpose-built into the American constitutional architecture of checks and balances. The window of opportunity might slam shut well before Roosevelt’s larger vision was fully realized.

That vision was capacious indeed. “We are going to make a country,” FDR once said to Labor Secretary Frances Perkins, “in which no one is left out.” The long-excluded one-third of American citizens who were Roosevelt’s concern in 1937 conspicuously comprised rural Americans, black and white alike, as well as the enormous immigrant communities that had arrived around the turn of the century.

Rexford Tugwell, a Roosevelt confidant and policy adviser, once described Roosevelt’s vision as “a better life for all Americans, and a better America to live it in. I think it was that general. There were items in it, but only a few he saw as fixed. One of these was security; if Europeans could have that, so could Americans. Another was a new framework for industrialism, and still another was a physically improved country.” Later, on the occasion of his 1944 State of the Union Address, Roosevelt elevated his vision to the level of a sweeping philosophical principle: “necessitous men are not free men,” he said, adding that “people who are hungry and out of a job are the stuff of which dictatorships are made.”

It’s important to emphasize the character and reach of Roosevelt’s vision, because he is often wrongly accused of having none. Far too many accounts of Roosevelt’s presidency mistakenly argue that his program had no internal coherence, that it amounted to little more than an opportunistic hodge-podge of ill-conceived policies with no over-all pattern. But as his second Inaugural Address makes clear, his deep commitment to the positive state, and to bringing that excluded one-third of his fellow citizens into the full richness of American life, gives the lie to such gross misunderstandings.

Pathbreaker: The Third Inaugural Address of Franklin D. Roosevelt

by Michael Kazin

The headlines reminded everyone that no other president had ever been inaugurated three times. But browsed quickly or heard on the air, Franklin D. Roosevelt’s address of just 1,380 words may have seemed to strike only familiar, if rather abstract, chords of congratulatory patriotism. He invoked the examples of Washington and Lincoln and lauded the democratic “spirit” instilled in iconic documents from the Mayflower Compact to the Declaration of Independence and the Constitution to the Gettysburg Address. That same spirit, FDR claimed in a nod to the immigrants and their children who had again helped elect him, was “born in the multitudes of those who came from many lands.” He concluded with a pledge: “We do not retreat, We are not content to stand still. As Americans, we go forward, in the service of our country, by the will of God.”

The address was delivered with his usual flair. Roosevelt’s moral urgency and his knack for dramatic pacing helped make him one of the greatest presidential orators. Yet, the throng that day of close to half a million appeared largely unmoved by his rhetoric, and Roosevelt later confessed his disappointment at the lukewarm reception. Arthur Krock, influential Washington Bureau Chief of the

New York Times

, commented that “the spiritual tone” of the address given before a bevy of “silk-hatted politicians” and an audience shivering in 24-degree weather was “not calculated to bring forth great displays of popular enthusiasm.”[42]

However, if read closely, the speech was more a call to defend the ideals of a system faced with “great perils never before encountered” than an anodyne hymn to the nation’s past achievements. There was loose in the world that winter an evil and mighty force which the President was urging Americans to resist, even if he never named it in his speech. As he spoke, the armies of Nazi Germany and their Italian Fascist ally were occupying most of Europe. Only Great Britain, under the leadership of Prime Minister Winston Churchill, held off the totalitarian enemy, thanks to the Royal Air Force’s defeat of the German Luftwaffe the previous fall. But Adolf Hitler’s desire to conquer the island nation and its farflung empire burned as brightly as ever.

A month earlier, in the wake of his third victory, Roosevelt had announced that the United States should be an "Arsenal of Democracy"—producing and selling the weapons of war to Britain and Canada. He knew a majority of Americans opposed throwing troops into the cauldron of war but also did not want Hitler and Mussolini to triumph. The impressive display of tanks and troops marching in close formation that dominated the Inaugural Parade served as a fitting response to anyone who doubted the administration’s determination to prepare the public for the sacrifices that might be required of them in the near future.

And near the beginning of his speech, Roosevelt made clear that ideological combat was vital to defeating the (unnamed) menace abroad. Some men “believe that democracy, as a form of Government and a frame of life, is limited or measured by a kind of mystical and artificial fate” and that “tyranny and slavery have become the surging wave of the future.” He quickly asserted, “But we Americans know that this is not true.” FDR’s boundless confidence in the “spirit” of democracy he elaborated in the rest of the short address was bounded with a warning: if citizens do not believe in their right and ability to govern themselves, they will never vanquish their sworn enemies.

As with all paeans to American exceptionalism, Roosevelt’s speech was not free of hyperbole. The democratic system he claimed “enlists the full force of men’s enlightened will” did not allow most Black Americans who lived in the South then run almost exclusively by politicians from FDR’s own party to enjoy the “equal protection of the laws” or to vote—both of which the Constitution guaranteed. And he made no effort to explain how democracy could be in such danger if it were, at the same time, “still spreading on every continent—for it is…in the end the most unconquerable of all forms of human society.” It is a bit odd that none of the speechwriters or the President who labored on an address that went through some six drafts noticed the contradiction.

Just two weeks before, Roosevelt had delivered a speech to a joint session of Congress whose significance has always overshadowed that of the Third Inaugural. In that State of the Union Address, he warned, similarly, that “the democratic way of life is at this moment being directly assailed in every part of the world… either by arms or by secret spreading of poisonous propaganda” and called for “a swift and driving increase in our armament production.” But what made that speech so memorable was FDR’s bold statement that the world could be made “secure” only if it were “founded upon four essential human freedoms”—of speech, of worship, from want, and from fear. The Four Freedoms swiftly became the equivalent of war aims for a nation that had not yet been attacked (but would be eleven months later); it rendered the inaugural address something of an anticlimax. As desires both specific and universal, they infused the “democratic spirit” with a weightier, more appealing import. Perhaps that’s one reason why the vast audience did not give FDR’s speech on the 20th of January the emotional ovation he expected. They had so recently heard or read a better one dedicated to the very same end.

Unprecedented: The Fourth Inaugural Address of Franklin D. Roosevelt

by David B. Woolner

At approximately 11:50 a.m. on Saturday January 20, 1945, US President Franklin D. Roosevelt took the arm of his son James, and with his steel braces locked in place, made his way carefully through a small crowd that had gathered on the South Portico of the White House to a chair that had been placed there for him as the inaugural ceremony that would see FDR take the oath of office for the fourth and final time got underway. With the nation at war, FDR had insisted that his unprecedented fourth swearing-in should be a brief, straightforward affair. There would be no inauguration day parade and no elaborate event on the steps of the capitol. He also planned to keep his inaugural remarks short and to the point. Like the rest of the nation, FDR was tired. Tired of the war, tired of the great sacrifices the war demanded, and—as he only admitted to his most intimate confidants—tired of being president.

Given the situation that the United States and its Allies faced at the beginning of 1945, FDR had good reason to feel fatigued. It had taken many weeks of hard fighting for the Western Allies to recover from the massive counter-offensive that Hitler launched in the Ardennes on December 16, 1944. And even though the Allies had managed to halt the German advance, it was now clear that in spite of the stunning success of the Allied drive across France in the wake of the Normandy invasion, the war was by no means over. Indeed, US battle casualties for the month of December alone were the highest of the war. Worst still, these figures arrived at the very moment when the country faced a severe shortage in manpower, not only to fill the ranks of the Armed Forces, but also to maintain the critical levels of industrial production that were required to keep the offensive operations in Europe and Asia moving forward.

Equally important, FDR also had to worry about a growing sense of dissension among the three major Allied powers as the war entered its final phase, and the concomitant disillusionment among the American public that accompanied it. To many observers it was becoming more and more apparent, for example, that the Soviet Union was intent on exerting direct control over Poland, and just as obvious that Churchill’s government was intent on establishing a conservative pro-British regime in Greece—even at the cost of armed conflict with Britain’s former allies, the anti-monarchist and largely communist Greek resistance. Given these developments, some members of Congress argued that the much-heralded principles that had been articulated in the 1941 Atlantic Charter were being crucified in the current Polish and Greek crises. But the most serious issue confronting the President concerned the impact internal Allied tensions might have on the main reason FDR had decided to run for a fourth term: the fate of the United Nations.

All of these questions weighed heavily on FDR’s mind as he prepared to take on the responsibility of another four years in office. To meet these challenges, FDR had already agreed to make the long journey to the Soviet resort town of Yalta, on the Crimean Peninsula, to converse with his British and Soviet counterparts. Here, the three leaders hoped to solidify their strategy for the final assault on Germany and Japan and come to an understanding over such outstanding issues as the future status of Poland and the structure of the United Nations.

Of course, the need for security meant that FDR could not divulge the fact that he would be leaving for the Yalta conference a mere two days after he was sworn in as President. But in light of the growing uncertainly in the public’s mind about the direction of the war, he planned to use the occasion of his fourth inaugural as a means to stress the need for Allied unity, and not let the differences that had begun to emerge as the specter of victory appeared on the horizon blind the American people to what he previously termed the “important common and continuing interests in winning the war and building the peace.”

January 20 was a cold day, with a fresh dusting of snow glistening on the leaves of the nearby magnolia trees. On the steps below the portico, looking up in admiration and wonder, stood all thirteen of the President’s grandchildren, and below them, the hundreds of official guests who filled a special section marked by a canvas spread on the ground to cover the snow. The President had also insisted—in a fitting reminder that the nation was still at war—that amid the crowd of diplomats, governors, members of Congress, and other representatives of Washington officialdom, a space be reserved for a group of fifty wounded servicemen, many of whom, like their Commander-in-Chief, were confined to wheelchairs.

The first to take the oath of office was Vice President Truman. Then it was FDR’s turn. After making his way to the podium with the help of James and a secret service agent, FDR placed his right hand on his family Bible, and discreetly gripping the reading podium with his left, turned to face US Chief Justice, Harlan Stone. He then swore to faithfully execute the office of President of the United States and to preserve, protect, and defend the nation’s Constitution, “so help me God.”

With the sight of the Jefferson Memorial glimmering in the distance, FDR began his fourth inaugural address by reminding the American people of the many trials they had yet to face as they struggled to bring the war to an end. The United States and its Allies were passing through “a period of supreme test,” he said, “a test of our courage—of our resolve—of our wisdom—of our essential democracy. If we meet this test—successfully and honorably” he continued, “we shall perform service of historic importance which men and women and children will honor throughout all time.”

In short, winning the war was not going to be easy. Nor would the transition from war to peace be achieved without a great deal of effort and the occasional setback. Although we may “strive for perfection,” he said, “we may make mistakes” along the way. Still, as his “old schoolmaster, Dr. Peabody, said in days that seemed to us to be secure and untroubled,” we should remember that “Things in life will not always run smoothly. Sometimes we will be rising toward the heights—and then all will seem to reverse itself and start downward.” But the great fact to remember is that “the trend of civilization is forever upward; that a line drawn through the middle of the peaks and valleys of the centuries always has an upward trend.”

And then, no doubt thinking about the structure of the peace to come, FDR reflected on the character of the American Constitution. It “was not a perfect instrument,” he said; indeed, “it is not perfect yet. But it provided a firm base upon which all manner of men, of all races and colors and creeds, could build our solid structure of democracy.” Having learned through the experience of war that we “cannot live alone at peace,” and that we must be “citizens of the world community,” he urged his fellow countrymen to recognize a lasting peace could not be founded on suspicion or mistrust or fear. Instead, what was needed was the confidence and the courage that flow from conviction, “the conviction that the only way to have a friend is to be one.”

FDR then closed his address with the observation that the Almighty had blessed the United States in many ways, “He had given our people stout hearts and strong arms with which to strike mighty blows for freedom and truth,” as well as “a faith which has become the hope of all peoples in an anguished world.”

In many respects, FDR’s fourth inaugural address represents a brief reiteration of the much longer remarks he delivered on the State of the Union on January 6, 1945. On this occasion, FDR not only spoke forcefully about the specific requirements needed to bring the war to a successful conclusion, but also about the critical need for the American people not to lose faith in the process involved in laying the foundations for the future peace of the world, including the creation of the United Nations. His greatest fear was that the American people might turn away from their international responsibilities and revert to the destructive pattern that had followed the last war. Here, his warning about the importance of not expecting “perfection” in his fourth inaugural is of special interest, for as he explained in his State of the Union address, “Perfectionism, no less than isolationism or imperialism or power politics,” might obstruct the paths to international peace. “Let us not forget that the retreat to isolationism a quarter of a century ago was started not by a direct attack against international cooperation but against the alleged imperfections of the peace. In our disillusionment after the last war,” he said, “we preferred international anarchy to international cooperation with Nations which did not see and think exactly as we did. We gave up the hope of gradually achieving a better peace because we had not the courage to fulfill our responsibilities in an admittedly imperfect world. We must not let that happen again,” he continued, “or we shall follow the same tragic road again—the road to a third world war.”

FDR would not live long enough to see the Allied victory, and the successful establishment of the United Nations that followed. And he was certainly correct when he warned about the numerous imperfections that might well accompany the transition of the world from war to peace. But the post-war international structure he helped establish has not only led to a period of unprecedented economic expansion, it has also helped the world avoid the onset of a new and even more destructive world war. Viewed from this perspective, FDR was surely correct when he argued that the American people should never forget that they “cannot live alone at peace,” and will forever remain “citizens of the world community.”

The Inaugural Address of Harry S. Truman

by Andrew E. Busch

Harry S. Truman took the oath of office on January 20, 1949 after having been elected in one of the most dramatic political upsets in American history. He had served nearly all of what would have been Franklin Roosevelt’s fourth term after Roosevelt’s death in April 1945. He had big shoes to fill, and the consensus by political prognosticators—and more than a few ordinary citizens—was that he was falling short. Labor unrest, inflation, shortages, and remaining wartime restrictions added up to a challenging environment for the incumbent.

In the 1946 midterm elections, Republicans made big gains, winning majorities in the House and Senate for the first time since 1930. Even Democrats were so convinced of Truman’s impending doom that Arkansas Senator William Fulbright suggested that Truman appoint a Republican Secretary of State and then resign, a maneuver that would have given Republicans the presidency under the order of presidential succession in place at the time. In domestic policy, Truman and the new Congress clashed repeatedly, with Congress passing a large tax cut and the Taft-Hartley Act, hated by organized labor, over Truman’s veto. His proposed civil rights program and other reforms designed to complete the New Deal languished. At the same time, Truman worked closely with Republicans to obtain passage of the Marshall Plan to rebuild Western Europe, aid to Greece and Turkey, and the National Security Act of 1947 creating the Defense Department, the Joint Chiefs of Staff, the Central Intelligence Agency, and the National Security Council.

In 1948, Truman was nominated by Democrats to serve another term as president, but the party was split. On one side, Strom Thurmond ran as a “States Rights Democrat”—or Dixiecrat—hoping to punish Truman for his civil rights stand by winning enough Southern electors to throw the election into the House of Representatives. On the other side, former Vice President Henry Wallace ran as the candidate of the Progressive Party, a coalition of far-left Democrats and communists. Wallace sought to punish Truman for his policy of anti-communist containment by siphoning off Democratic votes in northern and western states.

Polling, which was in its infancy, showed Truman far behind Republican challenger Thomas Dewey, the Governor of New York. Dewey played it safe, relying on vague platitudes and a leisurely speaking schedule. Truman was fiery and energetic (some said demagogic). He called Congress into special session and dared it to pass a number of liberal measures endorsed by Dewey, exploiting the longstanding rift between the Republicans’ presidential wing and their more conservative congressional wing. When Congress failed to act, he slapped the label of the “Do-Nothing 80th Congress” on it and campaigned for a change on Capitol Hill.

In the end, Truman won despite the unanimous prediction of the “experts.” It was not a huge win, but it was solid. Truman won 49.6 percent of the nationally-aggregated popular vote to Dewey’s 45.1 percent; Thurmond and Wallace each won 2.4 per cent. More importantly, Truman held a 303 to 183 advantage in Electoral Votes. Thurmond’s 39 in Southern states was not enough to derail the President. When he returned to Washington after voting in Missouri, Truman gleefully held aloft the blazing, premature headline of the Chicago Tribune: Dewery Defeats Truman. His fight against the GOP Congress was also successful, as Democrats regained their majorities in both House and Senate.

Harry Truman’s inaugural address contained some historically-typical features. One was an appeal to unity after a contentious campaign. “The tasks we face are difficult,” Truman said, “and we can accomplish them only if we work together.” Another was frequent appeal to God, an important element of American political culture found in almost every presidential inaugural address since 1789.

What made Truman’s address unique to that point—though less unique after—was the fact that it focused almost entirely on the world. It is easy to understand why he adopted that focus. The Cold War with the Soviet Union was underway in earnest. Since 1945, the Soviets had incorporated into their empire the countries of Eastern Europe, most recently through a communist coup d’etat engineered in Czechoslovakia in early 1948. Even as Truman spoke, Berlin was under siege, its land corridors to the West cut off by the Soviets. The free part of the city was now completely dependent on a massive airlift. Some in Washington had counseled preventive war while the U.S. still had a nuclear monopoly, but Truman had resisted.

Looking out at the world, Truman perceived that “It may be our lot to experience, and in large measure to bring about, a major turning point in the long history of the human race.” The first half of the century, Truman noted, had seen unprecedented assaults on human rights and destructive warfare never before seen; thus, “The supreme need of our time is for men to learn to live together in peace and harmony.” Of course, Truman himself had witnessed firsthand the destruction of the First World War, in which he served as an artillery officer, and he had borne the heavy responsibility of decision regarding the use of atomic bombs to end the Second.

The president held that the foundation for America’s efforts abroad would be its religious and civic faith, “that all men have a right to equal justice and equal opportunity to share in the common good…that all men have the right to freedom of thought and expression. We believe that all men are created equal because they are created in the image of God.” To this summation of the Declaration of Independence, Truman contrasted the regime and the ideology which opposed not just the United States but people around the world who wanted to be free. Communism, Truman observed, opposed self-government, crushed the individual, and embraced violence as the only route to justice and war as the inevitable solution to international disputes. The actions resulting from the communist ideology “are a threat to the efforts of free nations to bring about world recovery and lasting peace.”

Truman touted the Marshall Plan as an example of what the United States was already doing in cooperation with others to advance the cause of recovery and peace. “We are ready,” he added, “to undertake new projects to strengthen the free world,” falling under four “major courses for action:”

“continue to give unfaltering support to the United Nations and related agencies;”

“continue our programs for world economic recovery;”

“strengthen freedom-loving nations against the dangers of aggression;” and

“embark on a bold new program for making the benefits of our scientific advances and industrial progress available for the improvement and growth of underdeveloped areas.”

Truman briefly elaborated each point. The most potentially-controversial was point number 3, which Truman explained by reference to a new North Atlantic security arrangement he would soon be proposing to Congress. That arrangement was, of course, the North Atlantic Treaty Organization (NATO), based on the principle that an attack upon one is an attack upon all. NATO would become a key piece of the American strategy of collective security up to the present day. As Truman put it. “If we can make it sufficiently clear, in advance, that any armed attack affecting our national security would be met with overwhelming force, the armed attack might never occur.”

After laying out his goals, Truman expanded upon the superiority of democracy, which alone could provide the dynamism and growth necessary for progress among nations. In his one brief nod to domestic affairs, he acknowledged that “If we are to be successful in carrying out these policies, it is clear that we must have continued prosperity in this country and we must keep ourselves strong.”

The president wrapped up his address by returning to the theme with which he began:

Events have brought our American democracy to new influence and new responsibilities. They will test our courage, our devotion to duty, and our concept of liberty. But I say to all men, what we have achieved in liberty, we will surpass in greater liberty. Steadfast in our faith in the Almighty, we will advance toward a world where man’s freedom is secure. To that end, we will devote our strength, our resources, and our firmness of resolve.

Truman’s inaugural address wound up being a serviceable blueprint for the next four years. Except for an important amendment to the Social Security Act, not much happened in domestic affairs; the administration was as focused on the world in practice as Truman had been rhetorically. In 1950, Truman committed the United States to the defense of South Korea after it was invaded by its communist neighbor to the North—a devotion of national strength, resources, and resolve that ultimately saved South Korea and established the seriousness of the containment policy but also consumed the remainder of the Truman presidency.

More broadly, Truman’s address marked the triumph of liberal, anti-communist internationalism as something resembling the consensus foreign policy of the United States for the next two decades. America First isolationism was out, as was the Henry Wallace Popular Front with Stalin. Not until Vietnam was the consensus shattered in the Democratic Party, and even then most of the pieces were picked up and revivified by Ronald Reagan. While little came of Truman’s domestic Fair Deal, the foreign policy themes that dominated his 1949 inaugural address were not forgotten.

The First Inaugural Address of Dwight D. Eisenhower

by Michael J. Birkner

Always a distinctive moment in the life of a nation, the inauguration of a new chief executive takes on special significance when a transition from one party to another is involved. The inauguration of Dwight D. Eisenhower as the nation’s 34th president, moreover, was conducted in the midst of a stalemated war in Korea, a war that was one of the factors contributing to Eisenhower’s decisive victory over Democrat Adlai Stevenson in November 1952.

Eisenhower’s election was predicated on his reputation as the man who orchestrated the defeat of Adolf Hitler’s armies and voters’ conviction in 1952 that it was time for a change. The American public was increasingly impatient with a drumbeat of petty corruption cases involving Truman administration officials, with rising inflation, and a seemingly endless war in Asia. Throughout his exhausting whistlestop campaign in Fall 1952, Eisenhower hammered home three key themes: communism, corruption, and Korea, as central to his crusade. The slogan, C2, K1, became a Republican anthem. Democrats’ response that Americans never had it so good did not resonate as well with voters. Eisenhower took 55% of the popular vote and earned a decisive 442-89 victory in the electoral college.

Because he had promised in a late campaign speech in Detroit to “go to Korea” and determine the best course of action there, Eisenhower followed through in December. He quickly concluded, based on an on the ground assessment, that there was no easy path to victory. Eisenhower needed to find a way to achieve peace with honor—ending the war without sacrificing a foot of South Korea territory to the communists.

En route home, he spent a week on board the cruiser USS Helena bound for Hawaii, accompanied by Charles Wilson and Herbert Brownell, his designees for Secretary of Defense and Attorney General, respectively. At Wake Island, they were joined by Ike’s choices for Secretary of State, Treasury, and Budget Director, along with his longtime confidant, General Lucius Clay. The purpose was to enable his key advisers to get to know one another and chart a course for the new administration.

Once home at Morningside Heights on the Columbia University campus in New York City, after a Christmas holiday break, Eisenhower began writing his inaugural address, working first with C.D. Jackson and later with Emmet John Hughes, both of whom were on loan to him from Time/Life. Ike shared a draft of the address at a pre-inauguration meeting with his cabinet at New York’s Commodore Hotel on January 12, 1953, eliciting vigorous applause. As one of his biographers has noted, “he wanted neither to lecture nor to preach as he tried to articulate the grounding principles of his administration.” Despite the positive response from his top aides, Ike was not satisfied that he had struck the right notes. As recounted by Hughes, on January 17 Ike began working on an entirely new version of his address. According to Hughes, Eisenhower “felt a restless anxiety never displayed, before or later, about any speech.” But the new draft did not jell. The president-elect then decided, with Hughes’ help, to rework the version he had delivered to the cabinet. He continued to do so right up to the 20th, removing references to Moscow after UN Ambassador-designate Henry Cabot Lodge commented about problems with the phrasing.

Inauguration day in Washington dawned cool and overcast, though the sun peeked through the clouds during the ceremony. Ike and Mamie attended a special service in the morning at the National Presbyterian Church. He was not yet a member, but would join the church within months of taking up residency in the White House. After changing into his inauguration dress, which included striped trousers and dark gray formal jacket as well as a precedent-breaking homburg in place of the traditional silk top hat, Ike was driven to the White House. There he engaged in a brief, frosty interaction with President Harry Truman, declining Truman’s offer of hospitality before they took a limousine ride, as per tradition, to the Capitol. The harsh campaign rhetoric each had directed at the other still stung, and contributed to the frost. Their conversation during the short ride was mundane, focused on the crowd, the weather, and the importance of an orderly transition. Ike asked Truman who had ordered his son John home from Korea for the inaugural ceremonies. “I did,” Truman replied. Eisenhower offered a brief thank you, and that was the extent of their exchange. Ike reiterated his thanks in a letter to Truman three days later, expressing appreciation for “your thoughtfulness in ordering my son home from Korea . . . and even more especially for not allowing either him or me to know that you had done so.”

At noon, before an impressive crowd eager to celebrate the Republicans’ return to power in Washington, Eisenhower was sworn in by Chief Justice Fred Vinson, as was his young Vice President, Richard M. Nixon. Eisenhower used two Bibles: a George Washington Bible and one his mother gave him when he graduated from West Point.

Breaking another precedent, Eisenhower offered a brief prayer before commencing with his formal address: “May cooperation be permitted and be the mutual aim of those who, under the concepts of our Constitution, hold to differing political faiths; so that all may work for the good of our beloved country and Thy glory. Amen.”

The inaugural speech Eisenhower delivered was neither the longest nor the shortest of its kind; nor was it filled with florid expressions. But one biographer’s dismissal of the speech as “tedious and instantly forgettable” is grossly unfair.

Eisenhower’s major focus in the twenty-minute address was the future of mankind. Would it be slave or free? Would Americans respond effectively to the challenges of their times? Are we moving towards the light, he asked, or are “the shadows of another night closing in upon us?”

Eisenhower highlighted the importance of the nation’s founding documents and the watchfulness of Divine Providence. The struggle against atheistic communism, he observed was central to America’s future. “Freedom is pitted against slavery; lightness against the dark.” The leaders of the free world, in this telling, needed to work together; danger lay in “discord.”

Eisenhower said his administration would be guided by certain fixed principles. He listed nine of them by number and briefly elaborated. Key examples included abhorring war and standing firm against aggression; placing love of country above comfort and convenience; recognizing that economic health was “the indispensable basis of military strength and the free world’s peace”; support for the United Nations as a means of strengthening “special bonds the world over”; and a profound conviction that all peoples and nations were equal. No race, Eisenhower observed, is inferior or expendable. Underscoring his commitment to this last premise, Eisenhower said he wanted America’s friends to know that he would “observe the difference between world leadership and imperialism; between firmness and truculence; between a thoughtfully calculated goal and a spasmodic reaction to the stimulus of emergencies.” Above all, Ike insisted, his administration would defend the “deathless dignity of man.”

As president, Eisenhower lived up to his commitments to prudent stewardship of American resources and an open hand of friendship offered even to the nation’s major adversary, the Soviet Union. That his approach to waging Cold War sometimes fell short of this high standard seems indisputable. That he kept the peace and oversaw eight years of increased material prosperity is equally indisputable.

Following delivery of his address Eisenhower’s day in the spotlight was not over. After a brief lunch, he and Mamie reviewed a parade of floats along Pennsylvania Avenue, including ten floats from his native state of Texas relating the various stages of his life, West Point cadets marching past the review stand, and even some saddled up Kansas and California cowboys. Remarkably, Ike permitted one of the cowboys to lasso him, surely the first and last time for such an occurrence at a presidential inauguration! The parade went on for what Eisenhower later recalled was too many hours—five, in fact, rather than the scheduled three. “Not until nearly seven o’clock did the last two elephants go by,” Ike recalled in his memoir,

Mandate for Change

. Then it was off to the White House to change clothes, and attendance at two inaugural balls where Ike offered brief comments. Around one in the morning on January 21, 1953 Dwight Eisenhower went to bed as president of the United States.

The Second Inaugural Address of Dwight D. Eisenhower

by Louis Paul Galambos

On November 6, 1956, American voters gave Republican Dwight David (Ike) Eisenhower an impressive (57.4%) majority of their votes for a second term as President of the United States. This former Supreme Commander of Allied Forces in World War II, military commander of the North Atlantic Treaty Organization, and thirty-fourth U.S. President swept the Electoral College vote 457 to 73 against his Democratic rival, Governor Adlai Stevenson. The breadth of this victory should have made the Second Inaugural Address a mere victory lap for his party and its acclaimed leader. There were, however, too many dark clouds around Washington and the nation to allow the Inauguration to descend into pride and puffery.

The President and the American voters still had reason to wonder if their elected leader would remain healthy through the next four years. Eisenhower had long experienced a number of stress-related problems, beginning with his years at West Point prior to American entry into World War I. He smoked throughout his military career and was chain-smoking as many as four packs of cigarettes a day when he commanded the successful D-Day landing in France. This habit and the pressures of his career caught up with him repeatedly and in September 1955, he suffered a major heart attack. He had barely recovered before a massive attack of ileitis in June 1956 sent him back to the hospital and into surgery. Again, he recovered and won the 1956 election, but he, First-Lady Mamie Eisenhower, and the nation could not be certain he would be able to provide the firm hand that he had displayed in the previous four years.

The President’s vigorous participation in the Inaugural Ceremonies on January 21, 1957, gave reassurance that he had fully recovered from his heart attack and subsequent surgery. On a cold, gray day with occasional light flurries of snow, the President stood during the entire 3 hours of the parade. A similarly positive conclusion had been projected by Ike’s State of the Union Address on January 10, and his Annual Budget Message on January 17th. In the Budget Message, he reported on a growing economy, a balanced budget, and a successful effort to control inflation. The State of the Union Address was a less optimistic call to hard duty in a dangerous world, but there too, the President could see foreshadowed “a world transformed by the spirit of freedom.”

His Second Inaugural Address offered a similar vision of America’s “time of trial.” While we enjoyed prosperity, he said, much of the world experienced “want, discord, danger. New forces and new nations stir and strive across the earth, with power to bring, by their fate, great good or great evil to the free world’s future.” The breakup of the old empires and the socialist- and communist-leaning new governments of Africa and Asia were forefront on the President’s mind. Indeed, much of the world was swinging to the Left, toward the Soviet Union and away from the American model of democratic capitalism. Eisenhower frequently found that broad transition difficult to understand and confront, but in his Inaugural Address, he stamped the struggle in stark, moral terms.

In Europe, there was abundant evidence of International Communism’s “bondage.” Soviet tanks had just recently crushed the Hungarian Revolution. “Budapest,” Ike said, “is no longer merely the name of a city; henceforth it is a new and shining symbol of man’s yearning to be free.” But of course, those men and women who had pledged “their lives to that love” had been defeated. Nor had the German problem been solved: “In the heart of Europe, Germany still stands tragically divided. So is the whole continent divided. And so, too, is all the world.” Ike called for Americans to stay the course, to commit themselves to “our firm and fixed purpose—the building of a peace with justice in a world where moral law prevails.”

The moral order and the American alliance system had both become shaky in 1956, when Israel, Britain and France launched an invasion of Egypt over control of the Suez Canal. Egypt’s President Nasser had provoked the attack by nationalizing the Canal, but Eisenhower recognized that the Suez Canal Company, as well as the invasion, was a relic of a fast-fading colonial era of gunboat diplomacy. Incensed because he had not been informed of the attack, the President looked to “the authority of the United Nations. For in that body rests the best hope of our age for the assertion of that law by which all nations may live in dignity.” Leaning hard against America’s three allies, Eisenhower would shortly succeed in ending the invasion and performing “the work of peace” that he called for in his Inaugural Address.

The President left no doubt that we still needed our Cold War allies to continue their opposition to the “divisive force” of “International Communism and the power that it controls. The designs of that power, dark in purpose, are clear in practice. It strives to seal forever the fate of those it has enslaved. It strives to break the ties that unite the free. It strives to capture—to exploit for its own greater power—all forces of change in the world, especially the needs of the hungry and the hopes of the oppressed.” Eisenhower was seeking support for the foreign aid that would satisfy some of those “needs” and fulfill some of those “hopes.” He acknowledged that the international struggle would be expensive. “To counter the threat of those who seek to rule by force, we must pay the costs of our own needed military strength, and help to build the security of others. We must use our skills and knowledge and, at times, our substance, to help others rise from misery, however far the scene of suffering may be from our shores. For wherever in the world a people knows desperate want. There must appear at least the spark of hope, the hope of progress—or there will surely rise at last the flames of conflict.”

As the Address made clear, the Eisenhower strategy had not changed. He would, above all, avoid “the flames of conflict.” “We seek peace,” he said, “knowing that peace is the climate of freedom. And now, as in no other age, we seek it because we have been warned, by the power of modern weapons, that peace may be the only climate possible for human life itself.” To that end, he would also seek continued prosperity for Americans and for the millions elsewhere “seeking freedom, equality, and opportunity.” Other goals, foreign and domestic, were embodied in the dual themes of peace and prosperity. Left unexplored in the Address was the great struggle of African Americans for their full civil rights, a struggle that President Eisenhower would soon be forced to push higher in the goals of the Second Administration. On January 21, 1957, however, President Eisenhower folded that and other formidable issues into his concluding prayer that Americans would someday see “the turbulence of our age yield to a true time of peace, when men and nations shall share a life that honors the dignity of each, the brotherhood of all.”

Camelot
The Inaugural Address of John F. Kennedy

by Barbara Ann Perry

January 20, 1961, John F. Kennedy’s Inauguration Day, dawned clear but frigid, after the eight-inch snowfall on the nation’s capital overnight. JFK and his wife, Jacqueline, had already thrilled Washington on Inauguration Eve, looking like a couple just stepping out of a fairy tale about a handsome prince and beautiful princess, as they attended a star-studded gala, produced by their friend Frank Sinatra. After eight years of the elderly President Dwight Eisenhower, the New Frontier, as Kennedy’s administration would be called, burst on the scene with panache and vigor, a favorite JFK description (pronounced with his Boston accent as “vigah”) for the activism he envisioned to get “the country moving again.”

Kennedy’s election marked two unprecedented milestones: at age 43, he was the youngest candidate ever elected to the nation’s highest office and the first Roman Catholic. As he stood to take the oath of office, placing his hand on his Church’s version of the Bible, he represented the faith of a quarter of the U.S. population and an immigrant heritage of all but Native Americans. JFK was just three generations removed from his four great-grandparents who had emigrated as dirt-poor refugees from the mid-nineteenth century’s devastating Irish potato famine.

The outgoing president who, at 70, was the same age as Kennedy’s mother, and had suffered serious illnesses during his two terms in the White House, sat bundled against the icy temperatures, a scarf swaddling his neck, and his wispy white strands of hair blowing in the breeze. What a contrast when JFK stood at the podium, sans topcoat, scarf, gloves, or hat, his thick shock of auburn hair not in the least out of place. He had spent the weeks leading up to this historic day at his parents’ Florida beachfront compound, naming his Cabinet and sunning around the pool. Thus, despite his own medical issues, most of which remained hidden from the public, he looked the picture of health and vitality, even on the era’s black and white TV screens.

In his acceptance speech at the 1960 Democratic Conventions, Kennedy had introduced the metaphor that would identify his presidency: “We stand today on the edge of a New Frontier,” he declared in Los Angeles, “—the frontier of the 1960s, the frontier of unknown opportunities and perils, the frontier of unfilled hopes and unfilled threats. … Beyond that frontier are uncharted areas of science and space, unsolved problems of peace and war, unconquered problems of ignorance and prejudice, unanswered questions of poverty and surplus.” He then focused the frontier imagery primarily on domestic issues.

In his Inaugural Address, however, he chose to emphasize Cold War challenges that he would face in foreign and defense policy. Like all of JFK’s most important and memorable speeches, this historic inaugural address featured pithy syntax, soaring rhetoric, and compelling symbolism. He and his wordsmith, Theodore Sorensen, perfected the use of political symbols, defined by scholar Barbara Hinckley as those that “convey a larger range of meaning beyond themselves, with emotional, moral, or psychological impact. This larger meaning need not be independently true but will tap ideas people want to believe in as true.”

Kennedy began his first address to the American people and the world as president with a paean to freedom represented by his election and the peaceful transition of power, a not-so-veiled contrast to authoritarian regimes in the communist bloc. With a nod to the nation’s Founders, he praised their “revolutionary beliefs” that “are still at issue around the globe—the belief that the rights of man come not from the generosity of the state but from the hand of God.” Having fought anti-Catholicism to become president, vowing to maintain the constitutional separation of church and state, JFK did not hesitate to call on the deistic natural rights theory embraced by drafters of the Declaration of Independence and the Constitution.

Yet in the second paragraph of this speech, Kennedy cited how drastically the world had changed in the nuclear age: “For man holds in his mortal hands the power to abolish all forms of human poverty and all forms of human life.” He could not have known that in October 1962, during the Cuban Missile Crisis, he would hold in his hands the fate of the world, as it faced the possibility of nuclear annihilation if the United States and the Soviet Union went to war over the latter’s placement of atomic warheads, just ninety miles off the Florida coast and aimed at all major U.S. cities.

Illustrating Kennedy’s youth, in contrast to his predecessor, he fashioned one of the most memorable symbols of the entire speech. As the first president born in the twentieth century, he proclaimed, “Let the word go forth from this time and place, to fried and foe alike, that the torch has been passed to a new generation of Americans. …” He was leading the junior members of the World War II generation, many of whom, like him, were the young officers who served in Europe, where his brother Joseph Jr. lost his life as a Navy aviator, and in the Pacific, where JFK, a Navy PT boat skipper, nearly met his end when a Japanese destroyer rammed and sank his vessel. “The graves of young Americans who answered the call to service surround the globe,” Kennedy declared. “Now the trumpet summons us again.”

Whether fighting for “human rights” against fascism in the Second World War, or against communism in the Cold War, Kennedy signaled in the following passage—an exemplar of his and Sorensen’s crisp phrasing that brought to mind the Gettysburg Address—that “we shall pay any price, bear any burden, meet any hardship, support any friend, oppose any foe to assure the survival and success of liberty.”

A one-sentence paragraph introduced his promises to the world: “This much we pledge—and more.” He spoke directly to our “old allies whose cultural and spiritual origins we share,” to “those new states whom we welcome to the ranks of the free,” to “those people in the huts and villages of half the globe struggling to break the bonds of mass misery,” to “our sister republics south of the border,” and to the United Nations. From his days as a teenager devouring Winston Churchill’s history of the English people, magazines, and newspapers, and, as a college student, serving his father, Ambassador Joseph P. Kennedy Sr., in the United Kingdom, and then writing his Harvard honors thesis on Britain’s unpreparedness for World War II, JFK had been an staunch internationalist. He believed in the idealism of alliances and the practical contributions they made to America’s geopolitical interests. President Kennedy’s establishment of the Peace Corps, just two months after the inauguration, would embody both his ideals and pragmatism.

Now, as a Cold Warrior, he aimed his rhetoric at “those nations who would make themselves our adversary.” He called for peace to avoid “accidental self-destruction,” but swore to maintain parity in the arms race in order to avoid tempting the communists “with weakness.” “So let us begin anew—remembering on both sides that civility is not a sign of weakness. … Let us never negotiate out of fear. But let us never fear to negotiate,” JFK asserted. He offered an olive branch, along with a quiver of arrows, just as the American eagle possesses in the presidential seal.

Recognizing the potentially peaceful uses of science, Kennedy begged “both sides” in this bi-polar world (free v. communist) to invoke technology’s “wonders … instead of its terrors. Together let us explore the stars. …” The latter goal would go unheeded as both the U.S. and the USSR raced to be the first to land a man on the moon and return him safely to earth, with Americans, inspired by JFK, achieving that technological wonder in 1969, six years after JFK’s tragic assassination.

In the most quoted line from the address, Kennedy importuned his fellow Americans to “ask not what your country can do for you—ask what you can do for your country,” a sentiment borrowed and paraphrased from his prep-school headmaster. Yet it is JFK’s concluding oration that remains the heart and soul of his applauded Inaugural Address: “Finally, whether you are citizens of America or citizens of the world, ask of us here the same high standards of strength and sacrifice which we ask of you. With a good conscience our only sure reward, with history the final judge of our deeds, let us go forth to lead the land we love, asking His blessing and His help, but knowing that here on earth God’s work must truly be our own.”

The Art of Power: The Inaugural Address of Lyndon B. Johnson

by Mark K. Updegrove

On the evening of November 3, 1964, Lyndon Baines Johnson sat at the Presidential Suite at the Driskill Hotel in Austin, Texas, monitoring the results of the election that would relieve him of the stigma of being an “accidental president.” Nearly a year after assuming the presidency after the assassination of John F. Kennedy, he would find that not only had he won the office in his own right but had done so by yielding the biggest electoral mandate in American history to that point, garnering a whopping 61 percent of the popular vote against his Republican opponent, the senator from Arizona and conservative stalwart, Barry Goldwater. The titanic LBJ, who had spent nearly his entire adult life toward the acquisition and exercise of power, climbing the political ladder in Congress to become the most powerful Senate Majority Leader of the century, then moving on the become Kennedy’s vice president, had not only reached the highest rung, he had done so with a landslide. “Our victory was a mandate for action,” he wrote in his memoir

The Vantage Point

, “and I meant it to be used that way.”

Johnson had spent his first year in the presidency successfully achieving the legislative goals that Kennedy had failed to realize—a tax cut to stimulate a sluggish economy and the passage of the landmark Civil Rights Act, breaking the back of Jim Crow and its false promise of “separate but equal” segregated facilities. “Rightly or wrongly,” he said, “I felt from the very first day in office that I had to carry on for President Kennedy. I considered myself the caretaker of both his people and policy.” But he had begun the lay the groundwork for his own domestic agenda by picking up one unfinished by another president, one he would emulate more than any other: Franklin D. Roosevelt. “This is Kennedy’s program,” he told aides soon after taking over the Oval Office, “and we’re going to get it through. But if we’re going to compete with Roosevelt’s revolution…it’s got to be bigger than anything that has been envisioned so far.”

Bigger it was. Johnson had come to Washington during depths of the Great Depression in the mid-1930s as FDR’s New Deal, unprecedented government programs to lift Americans from economic ravage, was in full swing, bringing hope and possibility. He saw his administration as not just competing with the New Deal but completing it. Four months before the election, in a commencement address at the University of Michigan, he had planted the seeds of his own outsize domestic vision, unveiling the Great Society, an ambitious legislative agenda around civil rights, federal aid to education, immigration reform, poverty eradication, environmental preservation, and expanded health care. Now, with the presidency in hand for at least the next four years, he would use his Inauguration early in the New Year to promulgate the Great Society as the hallmark of his term in office.

January 20, 1965, as Lady Bird Johnson wrote, “dawned bright and beautiful,” with a temperature of 38 degrees and sunshine, blue skies, and scattered clouds over the U.S. Capitol. An estimated 1.2 million crowded into Washington for the 36th President’s Inauguration, besting the record set by Kennedy four years earlier by 200,000, further approbation for the bold but often insecure Johnson. Eschewing the top hat, cutaway coat, and striped trousers worn by his Twentieth Century predecessors, Johnson opted for decidedly less formal garb, donning an Oxford gray business suit. Marking an Inauguration Day first, Mrs. Johnson held the Bible on which her husband rested his left hand as he took the oath of office, establishing a tradition upheld by future First Ladies. After reciting the oath that thirty-four men had taken before him, Johnson stood behind the lectern and, for 23 minutes, sounded the overture of his administration.

In a slow, deliberate voice, he laid out a covenant for the American people comprised of “justice, liberty, and union” that allowed us to become a nation “prosperous, great, and mighty.”

Let us now join reason to faith and action to experience, to transform our unity of interest into a unity of purpose. For the Hour and the day and the time are here to achieve progress without strife; to achieve change without hatred; not without difference of opinion but without the deep and abiding divisions which scar the union for generations.

He made it clear that his vision of justice included all Americans. Portending his commitment to civil rights well beyond signing the Civil Rights into law the previous year, he declared, “Justice requires us to remember, when any citizen denies his fellow, saying: ‘His color is not mine or his beliefs are strange and different,’ in that moment he betrays America.” Underscoring the need for racial justice, as many as two hundred Blacks in Selma, Alabama, were being arrested after attempting to register to vote as the President spoke to the nation.

In perhaps the speech’s most memorable lines, Johnson elaborated on his view of the Great Society.

I do not believe that the Great Society is the ordered, changeless, and sterile battalion of ants. It is the excitement of becoming—always becoming, trying, proving, falling, resting and trying again—but always trying and always gaining.

While not on par with the Century’s most iconic Inauguration Day oratory, it reflected Johnson’s prodigious commitment to deliver social change. It was also in keeping with the view of domestic policy as a fluid, experimental exercise held by Roosevelt, who said, “It is common sense to take a method and try it. If it fails, admit it freely and try another. But above all else, try something.”

Echoing a chorus of positive reviews for the speech, the New York Times’ James “Scottie” Reston, the dean of White House correspondents, wrote, “President Johnson’s Inauguration was a dramatization of the American Dream. It was ‘bigger and better’ than ever before…In the poignant moment of commitment, he went back to the eternal things: justice, liberty, and unity.” The newly reinstated President danced the night away at a series of five Inaugural balls. As he left the last of them, a gathering at the Sheraton-Hilton where he danced only with women from Texas, he beseeched his fellow revelers, “Don’t say up too late. We’re on our way to the Great Society.”

In the days ahead, he would work tirelessly to make good on his promise. The Great Society was foremost on LBJ’s mind as he began his new term in office, setting his sights on a flurry of laws that would indeed rival those FDR championed around his New Deal. Johnson had a good head start. In addition to decisively delivering him the presidency, the election tide of 1964 had also brought more Democrats than had been in Congress since the days of the New Deal, with many newly elected lawmakers riding into office on Johnson’s back. Still, Johnson took nothing for granted. Acutely aware of the ephemeral nature of political capital—“When a man is first elected President, he’s a giraffe; six months later he’s a worm,” he said—he spent much of it the same year, while standing at the peak of his presidency. In 1965 alone, he set in motion a domestic agenda that included the signing of the Voting Rights Act, the Immigration Act, Elementary and Secondary Education Act, the Higher Education Act, the Highway Beautification Act, and the Clean Air Act; the creation of Medicare, Medicaid, the Department of Housing and Urban Development, the National Endowment for the Arts and the National Endowment for Humanities; and the implementation of Head Start. In many ways, the advance would create the foundation for modern America.

Conspicuously absent from LBJ’s Inauguration speech was any reference to the War in Vietnam, which, along with his formidable accomplishments, would define his presidency. Nor was there any allusion to the cold war or the threat of the spread of communism, which had been the centerpiece of Kennedy’s celebrated rhetoric four years earlier. Unlike JFK, it was domestic policy that fired LBJ’s imagination, not foreign policy. Vietnam, which had landed on his desk the day he inherited the presidency from Kennedy, was an unwanted intrusion, threatening to encroach on the Great Society. And while unity was central to Johnson’s Inauguration Day message, it was his escalation of Vietnam War that would divide the country, creating fissures that would mark the tumultuous latter days of the decade and contributing to LBJ’s decision not to seek reelection in 1968 so that he could concentrate on an honorable peace that would ultimately elude him.

The First Inaugural Address of Richard M. Nixon

by Ken Hughes

In his first inaugural address, Richard Milhous Nixon wrote his own epitaph: “The greatest honor history can bestow is the title of peacemaker.” Twenty-five years later he would have these words carved on his tombstone.

When he uttered them on Inauguration Day 1969, the words were a political promise and a personal aspiration. Nixon won and assumed office during the bloodiest years of America’s Vietnam War. A majority of Americans by then had concluded that the war was a mistake. As a motorcade took him from the White House to the U.S. Capitol, President-elect Nixon saw something his Cold War predecessors had not: protestors lining the streets. In the 1968 campaign, Nixon had promised to “end the war and win the peace,” a goal short of victory, but one that seemed more realistic. It would be, he promised, “peace with honor,” not “peace with surrender.” All of America would be watching and judging whether he kept this promise.

When Nixon aspired to the honor of “peacemaker,” however, he was talking about more than Vietnam. He hoped to change the terms of the entire Cold War, to see out the era of confrontation and usher in an era of negotiation.

In part this was a matter of necessity. When he left office as Vice President on January 20, 1961, America’s numerical advantage in nuclear weapons over the Soviet Union was at least 20-to-1. Eight years later, the two nations doomsday arsenals were roughly equal. President Nixon would not approach the Cold War as his predecessors had, because he no longer could.

Practical necessity was not Nixon’s only motive for changing course. He also possessed a particularly Nixonian vision of peace. Like his unexpected Democratic hero, President Woodrow Wilson, Nixon hoped to create an international framework to work out international differences without war. Wilson sought to create this framework idealistically, through open agreements openly negotiated. Nixon would try to get similar results through secret negotiations and backchannel deals. He thought he could play the Communist powers off one another, exploit the growing rift between the Soviet Union and the People’s Republic of China, use the prospect of improved relations with China against Russia, with Russia against China, and with both against North Vietnam. In three years he would look like a smashing success, in 25 years like an elder statesman, and in 50 years like an exposed fraud.

On Inauguration Day 1969, he looked like he was copying the most popular inaugural address of the Cold War, the one delivered by John F. Kennedy eight years earlier. Garry Wills identified numerous Nixonian echoes of the New Frontier. “Let this message be heard by strong and weak alike.” (Kennedy: “Let the word go forth to friend and foe alike.”) “Those who would be our adversaries, we invite to a peaceful competition—not in conquering territory or extending dominion, but in enriching the life of man.” (Kennedy: “To those nations who would make themselves our adversary, we offer not a pledge but a request: that both sides begin anew the quest for peace.”) “To all those who would be tempted by weakness, let us leave no doubt that we will be as strong as we need to be for as long as we need to be.” (Kennedy: “We dare not tempt them with weakness. For only when our arms are sufficient beyond doubt can we be certain beyond doubt that they will never be employed.”) Comparison of the imitation to the original recalls Mark Twain’s observation that the difference between the right word and the almost-right word is the difference between lightning and lightning-bug.

Not that it mattered much in the long run. By 1972, Nixon appeared to have delivered on his promises and more. He had inaugurated an era of rapprochement with Communist China and détente with the Soviet Union. In that year he became the first president to visit the capitals of either of these Communist powers. He had negotiated a nuclear arms control agreement with the Soviets. And, by playing Moscow and Beijing off one another, he got both to pressure Hanoi to accept his Vietnam settlement terms. The agreement, he declared, was “peace with honor.” In 1972, Nixon at least appeared to have some legitimate claim to history’s greatest honor.

Until the end of his life, he fought successfully to keep the public from hearing most of his secretly recorded White House tapes and reading most of the records of his negotiations with Communist leaders. This secrecy proved to be essential to preserving his image as a peacemaker. When his struggle to conceal his record ended with his death in 1994, the government began the long, slow process of declassifying the tapes and documents. In the following decades, these records revealed that Nixon had forged a “decent interval” deal with the Communists. He had secretly assured Moscow and Beijing that North Vietnam could take over the South without fear of American intervention, just as long as the North waited a year or two after Nixon withdrew the last American troops. The deal he called “peace with honor” was no peace at all. It was designed to postpone, not prevent, the collapse of South Vietnam.

That was not the worst of it. Declassified tapes and documents reveal that Nixon realized early on that South Vietnam could not survive without American troops. This meant that “peace with honor” was never achievable. America could either leave and lose the war or stay and fight it indefinitely. Neither alternative was peace.

But Nixon never admitted in public that he couldn’t deliver what he had promised. To conceal this failure, he kept the war going through all four years of his first term. That was the only way to keep South Vietnam from falling before Election Day 1972, a defeat that would have destroyed his chances at a second term. The price of his reelection was the death of 20,000 Americans and many thousands more Vietnamese, North and South.

In his first inaugural, Nixon laid out the terms by which history would judge his presidency. The test of his presidency would be whether he earned the title of peacemaker. In some ways, he did. Détente and rapprochement eased international tensions and improved relations with China and Russia. Those achievements were real, although we now see that they were tainted by Nixon’s secret assurances to both Communist powers that he would accept defeat in Vietnam, as long as they delayed it long enough for him to duck responsibility. History has yet to devise a title to bestow on leaders who prolong wars to avoid losing elections, who fraudulently package delayed defeat as peace, who sacrifice human lives for political gain.

A Moment of Triumph Before Disaster: The Second Inaugural Address of Richard M. Nixon

by Thomas Alan Schwartz

Saturday, January 20, 1973, was a relatively mild day in Washington, cloudy but with no rain in the forecast. Richard Nixon’s second inaugural address took place in a very different atmosphere, both literally and figuratively, from his first one. That event, on a bitterly cold and overcast day, had brought thousands of antiwar demonstrators to Washington who hurled objects at the presidential limousine and disrupted the inaugural parade. There were a few demonstrators present in 1973, but their cause no longer seemed as relevant or urgent. A settlement in Vietnam was only days away, and Richard Nixon used his short speech to proclaim that America now stood “on the threshold of a new era of peace in the world.” Fresh off his impressive electoral triumph, carrying 49 states with a popular vote of 60 percent of the electorate, Nixon was at the peak of his political popularity and power. What is truly amazing is how quickly all of it would disappear, and Nixon would resign in disgrace less than twenty months later.

With the help of his National Security Adviser, Henry Kissinger, Nixon had engineered a “trifecta” of foreign policy successes in 1972 that helped to lead to his overwhelming electoral victory. His trip to China, the first of an American president, captured the imagination of Americans, and although it lacked any substantive agreements, it gave rise to the view of Nixon as a brilliant and shrewd foreign policy leader. His subsequent summit meeting in Moscow, and the signing of the first Strategic Arms Limitation Treaty, seemed to signal the end of the Cold War hostility that had shaped a generation of Americans. Finally, the imminent prospect of a Vietnam peace settlement, although delayed and seemingly threatened by the renewed Christmas bombing of North Vietnam, gave Americans hope that their prisoners of war would be returned and America’s long nightmare in Indochina was finally over. To most Americans, Nixon’s claim in his inaugural that “1972 will be long remembered as the year of the greatest progress since the end of World War II toward a lasting peace in the world,” did not seem like a classic Nixon exaggeration.

Having won his campaign against Senator George McGovern, a Democratic challenger whose slogan was “Come Home, America,” Nixon made it clear that the peace he sought would not bring with it a return to pre-World War II isolationism. Nixon vowed to build a “structure of peace,” in which America’s role would remain “indispensable.” However, he also made it clear that a post-Vietnam America would be cautious about using military force, and that “the time has passed when America will make every other nation’s conflict our own.” Nixon also encouraged the belief, widely shared among the public, that America would enjoy a “peace dividend,” and could now redirect its energies toward its domestic challenges, “to make life better in America—to ensure better education, better health, better housing, better transportation, [and] a cleaner environment.” Although the actual resources proved more limited than many Americans hoped, the Federal Government did begin spending far more on domestic programs in the 1970s.

Yet Nixon also sounded a more traditional Republican theme when he made the case for a more decentralized approach to decision-making, and a more limited governmental role in American life. His choice of words foreshadowed the Reagan Revolution of the 1980s when he argued, “The time has come to turn away from the condescending policies of paternalism—of ‘Washington knows best.’” Although he was not specific in terms of amounts or dollar figures, he seemed to be calling for tax cuts by saying, “Government must learn to take less from people so that people can do more for themselves.” And in what was clearly designed to be a play on the very famous closing line from John Kennedy’s inauguration—“Ask not what your country can do for you, but what you can do for your country,” Nixon said. “In the challenges we face together, let each of us ask—not just how can government help, but how can I help?”

Lower taxes, limited government, less federal regulation, more individual responsibility–all of these arguments serve to connect Nixon’s advocacy to ongoing themes in American conservatism and to issues that the Republican Party has long embraced. There was also a specific reference to the tumultuous Vietnam period through which the country was emerging—“as America’s longest and most difficult war comes to an end”—and that still seems quite relevant to the politically polarized America of 2021. Nixon called for greater “civility and decency” in public debate, urging “each of us” to show “a new level of respect for the rights and feelings of one another, a new level of respect for individual human dignity which is the cherished birthright of every American.” In his first inaugural address, Nixon had called on Americans to “lower their voices,” but the continuation of the Vietnam War did not lead to that. Instead, Nixon had faced in his first term massive protests and political division, including the Vietnam moratoriums, the huge protests after the Cambodia invasion, and the attempt to shut down Washington in the spring of 1971.

In one of the more curious passages in the speech, Nixon’s rhetoric foreshadows a theme of President Donald Trump, who recently established a President’s Advisory 1776 Commission to further “patriotic education.” Nixon contended that in recent years American children “have been taught to be ashamed of their country, ashamed of their parents, ashamed of America’s record at home and its role in the world.” In what was likely a reaction to the first wave of revisionist historical instruction in some schools, Nixon contended, “We have been beset by those who find everything wrong with America and little that is right.” Although Nixon did not use the now common expression, “American exceptionalism,” he did proclaim that America’s “record in this century has been unparalleled in the world’s history for its responsibility, for its generosity, for its creativity, and for its progress.” Closing off the speech, he returned to the theme of a “structure of peace” that would last for “generations to come,” and connected this to the forthcoming Bicentennial celebrations of the 200th anniversary of America’s founding in 1976, over which he fully expected to preside. “Let us pledge together to make these next four years the best four years in America’s history, so that on its 200th birthday America will be as young and as vital as when it began, and as bright a beacon of hope for all the world.”

Richard Nixon is not a person with whom it is easy to sympathize. Listening to his voluminous tape recordings, which captured the man behind the public image he projected, it is not hard to be repelled by his cynical manipulation of issues and his crude prejudices and hatreds. Yet there is still an element of tragedy in his Presidency that is reflected in this speech. Nixon had extricated America from an unwinnable war and reconciled the country with its two giant Cold War enemies, and he clearly hoped that this would allow the country the opportunity to heal and address its numerous domestic problems. But the Watergate scandal, a reflection of some of his worst political instincts and insecurities, would soon overshadow the vision presented in this speech, and lead to his downfall. The tragedy may not be fully Shakespearean, but it is still epic.

Remarks Upon Taking the Oath of Office as President

by John Robert Greene

The Inaugural Address of Gerald R. Ford as the thirty-eighth President of the United States, delivered from the White House East Room at 12:05 PM on Friday, August 9, 1974, was unique in the annals of American History. Ford was the first vice president to accede to the presidency under the terms of the 25th Amendment, following the resignation that morning of Richard M. Nixon. Moreover, while he was the eighth vice president to inherit his office from a sitting president, he was the first to deliver an address to the American people upon the occasion of his taking power.

Vice-Presidential speechwriter Robert Hartmann, soon to serve as a Counselor to President Ford, remembered that Ford gave him only one day’s notice to craft comments which would follow Ford’s swearing in. In light of the implosion of the Nixon presidency, Hartmann remembered that as he began thinking, he jotted down three key themes—“Take Charge,” “Legitimacy,” and “Truth is the Glue.”

Hartmann then worked to set the tone for the speech. A large part of this was deciding what to call it. It would be delivered in the shadow of a presidential resignation, and the air of sheer exhaustion and relief that permeated the nation that August negated the use of any of the pomp and circumstance that would normally accompany a presidential inauguration. Moreover, one of Ford’s immediate goals was to distance himself from his predecessor, a man known for his formal, often stilted speech delivery. With these thoughts in mind, Hartmann settled upon Ford’s opening line—that what he was about to deliver was “not an Inaugural Speech, not a Fireside Chat … Just a little straight talk among friends.”

The speech continued along a path designed to exorcise the ghost of Nixon Past. Hartmann’s dismissal of Watergate—My Fellow Americans, our long national nightmare is over”—was the most quoted passage of the speech, and it became one of the most memorable lines in modern inaugural history. However, when Hartmann had Ford claim that “Our constitution works. Our great republic is a government of laws and not men,” he was on less solid ground. Many Americans, upset that Nixon had yet to be indicted for crimes that included at minimum an obstruction of justice which had been recorded on the White House taping system, were about to deflate Ford’s honeymoon with charges of a deal between he and Nixon—charges that would only be intensified exactly one month after Ford took office when he pardoned Nixon. Still, the line exuded an optimism that Americans desperately wanted to experience, and few observers challenged this assessment at the time.

When Ford strode into the White House East Room, holding the hand of his wife Betty and surrounded by White House staffers, cabinet members, and congressional leaders who had just witnessed Nixon’s rather maudlin farewell (indeed, the Fords were the last to say goodbye to Nixon and his wife, Pat as they boarded Marine One on the South Lawn of the White House) he was understandably tense. Immediately following his swearing-in by Chief Justice Warren Burger, Ford began his speech in a tight, stilted delivery. This was unlike Ford, who loved the speechmaking and gladhanding of a political campaign and had a professional politician’s grace and ease in front of both crowd and camera. But as he moved through his address, Ford loosened up. He delivered Hartmann’s “long national nightmare” line with both conviction and forcefulness, as the new president looked square into eyes of his audience and proclaimed the start of his own administration.

But even this line was not enough for Ford to feel comfortable that he had separated himself from his predecessor: “If you have not chosen me by secret ballot, neither have I gained office by any secret promises. I have not campaigned either for the Presidency or the Vice Presidency. I have not subscribed to any partisan platform. I am indebted to no man, and only to one woman—my dear wife—as I begin this very difficult job.” The latter portion of that phrase was a break with tradition, as Ford became the first president to reference his wife in his Inaugural Address, a line that when he delivered it, nearly caused his voice to break. The rest of the talk emphasized Ford’s midwestern roots and his deeply held Episcopalian faith, as when he asked the nation for “your prayers for Richard Nixon and his family. May our former President, who brought peace to millions, find it for himself.” When he was finished, instead of attending parades and Inaugural Balls in his honor, Ford walked down the hall to the Oval Office, and immediately began a series of meetings with those in his new administration.

It all took less than fifteen minutes. At 850 words it was the fourth shortest Inaugural Address in history (only Washington’s First Inaugural, Lincoln’s Second, and Franklin Roosevelt’s fourth were shorter). It was so brief that many in the press did not know what to make of it—CBS News, for example, called Ford’s speech “Inaugural Remarks.” But whatever it was called, the speech was a resounding success. Ford’s reassuring presence, equally as much as Hartmann’s words, helped the country start to breathe again. Articulating the feelings of many Americans, when Ford’s speech was over, Warren Burger turned to Senate Minority Leader Hugh Scott and said “Hugh, it worked. Thank God it worked.”

The Peanut Farmer: The Inaugural Address of Jimmy Carter

by Mark Atwood Lawrence

Reflecting on the day he became the thirty-ninth president of the United States, Jimmy Carter recorded a revealing shard of memory in his diary. Even though he had pursued the nation’s highest office with uncommon energy over many months, Carter wrote, he was “genuinely surprised” when the Bishop of Minnesota, in delivering the benediction at the inauguration ceremonies, bestowed “blessings on President Carter.” The words “President Carter” were “startling to me,” he recalls.

The whole day, January 20, 1977, was like that for Carter. Rarely had a newly elected president been less invested in the pomp and fanfare that usually went with the nation’s highest office. The former governor of Georgia—a peanut farmer quick to extoll his small-town roots—wore a store-bought suit and a borrowed overcoat. He passed up the traditional inaugural service at the stately St. John’s Episcopal Church near the White House, joining instead his coreligionists at the humbler First Baptist Church several blocks away. He declined to hold the usual inaugural luncheon.

Following his swearing-in, Carter made his most striking gesture of the day. Moments after boarding a limousine for the mile-and-a-half ride to the White House, he ordered the driver to stop, got out, and began strolling down Pennsylvania Avenue hand in hand with First Lady Rosalynn, while their 9-year-old daughter Amy ambled—and sometimes skipped—alongside. Carter hoped his walk would offer a “tangible indication of some reduction in the imperial status of the president and his family.” It worked. The crowds along the parade route warmly cheered the Carters, who won broad acclaim for the egalitarianism they projected.

Less celebrated was Carter’s inaugural address, hardly a masterpiece of the genre. To be sure, the speech earned dutiful applause and respectful coverage at the time. But it has seldom garnered favorable comment from historians and biographers. It was, writes historian Randall Balmer, a “workmanlike” mélange of well-worn themes from the campaign. Biographer Jonathan Alter calls the speech “disjointed” and “loosely structured,” gentle ways of critiquing the lack of intellectual coherence, poetic flow, or emotional punch.

Better speechwriting might have helped knit Carter’s ideas together into something more powerful, and a more polished delivery—almost always an elusive goal for Carter—might have left a better impression. But there was a more fundamental reason why Carter fell well short of the grandest inaugural orations. The speech’s tepidness owed much to the very modesty that had enabled Carter to win the White House and underlay his most memorable gestures on Inauguration Day. To have asked Carter for something grander would have meant asking him to be a different sort of leader and to have understood the national mood in a different way.

The address oozed humility. Indeed, perhaps the most extraordinary moment came when Carter thanked his predecessor and political rival, Gerald R. Ford, an unprecedented gesture of selflessness in an inaugural speech. Otherwise, the address stands out for its brevity (1,228 words, taking a mere 14 and a half minutes to deliver) and studied lack of pretension. Carter opened by quoting not the founding fathers or other luminaries of American history but his high school teacher, Miss Julia Coleman, whose admonition to her students in a humble Georgia schoolhouse—“We must adjust to changing times and still hold to unchanging principles”—set the tone for everything that followed.

Aides talked Carter out of going so far as to quote a Biblical passage (2 Chronicles 7:14) condemning “wicked ways” and calling for national healing through forgiveness of “sin.” Such fervid self-criticism seemed too strong for Americans who did not share Carter’s particular brand of Christianity. But the verse Carter selected instead—Micah 6:8—sent a broadly similar message by stressing his dedication to justice, mercy, and walking “humbly” with God. And Carter retained other notes of self-effacement in his text. “Your strength can compensate for my weakness,” he told the American people, “and your wisdom can help to minimize my mistakes.”

Carter hit much the same theme when he turned from his personal shortcomings to the nation’s. “We have learned that 'more' is not necessarily 'better,' that even our great nation has its recognized limits, and that we can neither answer all questions nor solve all problems,” Carter averred in perhaps the most arresting lines of the speech. He appealed for a “spirit of individual sacrifice for the common good,” urging that Americans “must simply do our best” rather than striving to do everything.

These words unquestionably suited the political moment. Although America’s bicentennial in 1976 had triggered a wave of patriotic fanfare, Carter’s rise to the presidency took place against a backdrop of national setbacks and demoralization. The Watergate scandal, culminating in Richard Nixon’s resignation in 1974, caused many Americans to distrust the integrity, even the decency, of their leaders. America’s final defeat in Vietnam the following year stirred profound doubts about the nation’s entitlement to global leadership and the efficacy of the vast material power it wielded. Soaring inflation and other economic difficulties suggested, meanwhile, that the postwar economic boom was over. Cities crumbled, and environmental woes multiplied. All in all, as California Governor Jerry Brown put it in 1976, an “era of limits” appeared to be at hand.

Carter’s victory in the 1976 presidential race owed much to his image as a political outsider innocent of the corruption and error that had led the nation astray. From the moment he declared his candidacy, he gained traction largely because of who he was—a morally upright man who promised never to lie to the American people—and the promises of contrition and renewal that he offered. By the time of his inaugural, his professions of humility had become routine. If Americans looked past the speech and remembered other moments in a long day of political pageantry, it’s not difficult to understand why.

The cost of Carter’s approach—apparently one he was willing to pay—was a missed opportunity to highlight some intriguing big ideas that ran, if only vaguely, through the speech. These ideas were not entirely new, and Carter would articulate all of them more fully on other occasions. But if Carter had invoked them more eloquently at the outset of his administration, they might have resonated more powerfully with the public, helping to cast Carter in a glow of not just moral conviction but also ingenuity and vision. Three such insights in particular stand out, all of which deserve to be recalled in 2021 at another moment of national doubt.

First, Carter called attention to his commitment to the advancement of human rights as a core concern of U.S. foreign policy. “Our moral sense dictates a clearcut preference,” he insisted, “for these societies which share with us an abiding respect for individual human rights.” What made the point especially notable was Carter’s suggestion that dedication to principle would not undercut American power, as the Republican administrations of the earlier 1970s had tended to believe. Rather, Carter insisted “the trust which our nation earns” through adherence to its core values “is essential to our strength.” More abstractly, he declared that the pursuit of “moral duties” seemed “invariably to be in our own best interests.”

Second, Carter proposed a military policy that would balance the pursuit of arms control with the preservation of national strength. The president’s dedication to arms reduction was plain to see, as it had been throughout the campaign. “We pledge perseverance and wisdom in our efforts to limit the world’s armaments to those necessary for each nation’s own domestic safety,” intoned Carter, suggesting a desire for deterrence at minimum levels of weaponry. He even held out “the elimination of all nuclear weapons from this Earth” as his ultimate goal. But, as usual with Carter, peacemaking ambitions coexisted with a concern for national defense befitting a former Naval officer. While the United States would never seek to “intimidate” its foes, he declared, “it is clear that a world which others can dominate with impunity would be inhospitable to decency and a threat to the well-being of all people.”

Third, Carter declared his dedication to making the government not only more “compassionate” but also—a word easy to miss among the jumble of more high-minded adjectives—“competent.” He declared that his inauguration marked a “new beginning” for the nation and encapsulated a “new spirit” among Americans. In a slight contradiction, he even suggested that a “serious and purposeful rekindling of confidence” had already taken hold across American society. But his more intriguing assertion was to herald a “new dedication within our Government”—the start, he hoped, of a new era in which Americans could be “proud” of what occurred in Washington.

Carter went no further with this theme or, for that matter, any other elements of domestic or foreign policy. In sticking to broad generalities, he was, of course, hardly alone; few presidents have used their inaugurals to engage the intricacies of policy matters. Moreover, Carter had good reason to believe that his primary task at the outset of his administration was to establish a new tone as the country grappled with pervasive doubt and distrust. Low national morale was a real problem.

Yet the speech fell short of Carter at his best. A master of detail who was often criticized for micromanagement of complicated policy issues, Carter showed few hints of the intellectual command that had made him an effective leader back in Georgia. His repeated expressions of humility, meanwhile, highlighted traits that many Americans would come to see as naïveté and excessive meekness as the United States faced mounting economic woes as well as foreign policy crises in the later years of his term. The political mood that brought Carter to office proved fleeting. By1980, many Americans had lost interest in the genuine innovations that Carter espoused and rallied around a very different notion of renewal associated with Ronald Reagan and a revitalized nationalist wing of the Republican Party.

The First Inaugural Address of Ronald Reagan

by Gil Troy

In the first 105 words of his 1981 inauguration speech, Ronald Reagan painted the horizons–and defined the limits–of what would be known as the Reagan Revolution. In celebrating this “solemn and most momentous occasion” as “an orderly transfer of authority,” he rejoiced: what “we accept as normal is nothing less than a miracle.” Reagan was suggesting that the answer to America’s malaise could be found in a patriotic renewal, by returning to core principles and the irrepressible confidence that had propelled Americans forward since the American Revolution. That faith in the past as a solution to present problems and the key to a proud, prosperous, and peaceful future, is why Reagan never claimed to be launching a revolution. It was, he would say eight years later in his Farewell Address, the “Great Rediscovery: a rediscovery of our values and our common sense.”

The new President had much riding on his twenty-minute address that bright, balmy January day. Americans were, he noted, “confronted with an economic affliction of great proportion,” stagflation–a debilitating combination of high inflation and surging unemployment. Those problems were exacerbated by an unwieldy, unproductive, and ever-growing federal government, bankrolled by “a tax system which penalizes successful achievement and keeps us from maintaining full productivity.” Beyond that, reeling from the 1960s’ and 1970s’ revolutions and disillusionments, Americans had lost faith in themselves and their government. Too many feared “that society has become too complex to be managed by self-rule.” Reagan’s predecessor Jimmy Carter unintentionally fed that crisis of confidence, with his constant emphasis on America’s new limits and his listless handling of the humiliating Iranian hostage crisis, as Iranian radicals held 52 American diplomats and marines captives for 444 days. Further adding tension and sowing doubt, were “the enemies of freedom,” especially the menace Reagan chose not to name explicitly: Soviet Communism.

Finally, Reagan knew that many Americans doubted him. He had won only 50.7 percent of the vote, despite his advisers’ claim of a “Reagan mandate.” Ignoring his two-terms as California governor and nearly twenty years of political speechifying, Democrats mocked Ronald Reagan as a Hollywood B-movie actor and failed Las Vegas pitchman, who lacked a presidential cv, aura, or smarts.

Nevertheless, Reagan was inviting Americans to trust him, their country, and themselves, as one, integrated, red-white-and-blue package. Splashy consumption became one colorful way to take back the night. The President’s thousand-dollar morning suit, the First Lady’s $10,000 gown, the $16 million-dollar inaugural price tag, the private planes landing at National (soon to be Reagan) Airport, the limousines deployed on the ground, all signified Reagan’s new direction. Although even some Republicans found the consumption too conspicuous, the festivities revealed a characteristically open American approach to wealth, not as something to be resented because aristocrats monopolized it, but as something accessible to be enjoyed, or at least revered. Ultimately, the celebration of wealth reflected the Reagan paradox: his odes to traditional values coexisted with his role as an avatar of American consumption, a maestro of materialism.

Ronald Reagan used his inauguration and his “first hundred days,” to establish a new national tone. Proof of a collective desire for a new mood bubbled up in 1980. The national euphoria–and sense of vindication–which greeted the “Miracle on Ice,” the American Olympic team’s surprise hockey triumph over the Soviet Union in February 1980, demonstrated what the Washington Post called “hero-starved” Americans’ yearning for a return to patriotism and national “self-esteem.” Two months after the inauguration, Walter Cronkite would retire as the CBS News anchor. Reagan would replace “Uncle Walter” as the kindly paterfamilias of America’s ever-changing family. All this required, he told his fellow Americans, “our willingness to believe in ourselves and to believe in our capacity to perform great deeds.”

Reagan sought to restore faith in American individualism by targeting big government. This debate had been intensifying since Franklin D. Roosevelt’s New Deal. Democrats became the party of government expansion, as Republicans tried putting on the brakes. Anxious to preserve “this last and greatest bastion of freedom,” Reagan proclaimed: “In this present crisis, government is not the solution to our problem; government is the problem.”

Subtly needling the Democrats, whom Republicans caricatured as the party of special interests, Reagan appealed to one “special interest group that has been too long neglected. … ‘We the people,’ this breed called Americans.”

Seeing to restore the balance, Reagan insisted: “We are a nation that has a government—not the other way around.”

Ronald Reagan had been singing this song of limiting government and empowering Americans since the mid-1950s, when he became a pitchman for General Electric, as his Hollywood career faded. It surged with “The Speech,” his ringing endorsement of Barry Goldwater in 1964. And it echoed in many of his riffs as California governor and on the speakers’ circuit as he built toward his 1976, then 1980, presidential runs. He had no “intention to do away with government,” he insisted. He just wanted “to make it work—work with us, not over us; to stand by our side, not ride on our back.”

Reaffiming his faith in “freedom” and “the dignity of the individual,” he insisted that “our present troubles parallel and are proportionate to the intervention and intrusion in our lives that result from unnecessary and excessive growth of government.” Then, one of Reagan’s defining lines: “It is time for us to realize that we are too great a nation to limit ourselves to small dreams.”

Leaping from the political realm to the existential, he rhapsodized: “let us begin an era of national renewal.” Seeing heroes as walking bundles of hope, Reagan saluted “individuals and families whose taxes support the Government and whose voluntary gifts support church, charity, culture, art, and education.” And after honoring the American Revolution, warning “those who practice terrorism and prey upon their neighbors,” and toasting Inauguration Day as a “day of prayer,” he turned toward his home, to the West.

Noting that the ceremony had never been held on the West front of the Capitol, he saluted the men behind the monuments he now faced: George Washington, Thomas Jefferson, Abraham Lincoln. Looking toward “the sloping hills of Arlington National Cemetery” across from the Potomac, he honored America’s soldiers who had sacrificed everything so we could enjoy our freedom. “Under one such marker lies a young man—Martin Treptow,” he said. Treptow died in World War I. In his diary he wrote: “I will fight cheerfully and do my utmost, as if the issue of the whole struggle depended on me alone.”

Reagan ended by summoning “our best effort, and our willingness to believe in ourselves and to believe in our capacity to perform great deeds; to believe that together, with God’s help, we can and will resolve the problems which now confront us.” Dismissing the cynics, he declared: “And, after all, why shouldn’t we believe that? We are Americans. God bless you, and thank you.”

Naysayers would note that Treptow wasn’t buried in Arlington National Cemetery–although the phrase “one such marker” could apply to any military gravesite anywhere in the world. But believers–and the newly-converted–delighted in the next triumphal few minutes. Striding into the President’s Room of the Senate, Reagan signed an Executive Order freezing federal civilian hiring. “This begins the process of restoring our economic strength and returning the Nation to prosperity,” he said.

As the inaugural luncheon in Statuary Hall ended, Reagan announced the perfect coda to his red, white, and blue inaugural: “With thanks to Almighty God, I have been given a tag line, the get-off line everyone wants at the end of a toast or speech,” the shameless showman admitted. The hostages “now are free of Iran.” Ayatollah Khomeini had given the old performer a great gift to help “begin an era of national renewal.”

After a shrewd courtesy visit to the Speaker of the House, Tip O’Neill–who felt snubbed by his fellow Democratic Jimmy Carter at the 1977 inauguration—Reagan rode down Pennsylvania Avenue to his new home. The inaugural parade celebrated the themes of the inaugural–and the three pillars on which Ronald Reagan’s historical reputation still stands: peace, prosperity, and patriotism.

He promised all three in his 20-minute talk. Eight rocky years later, he was able to make the case that he delivered all three–at least partially. With the Soviet Union imploding, the Cold War was ending. The stock market was booming and inflation had faded. Meanwhile, the celebration of traditional American values Reagan launched in the inaugural, continued.

True, various problems persisted. Debates about Reagan’s legacy continue to rage among historians. But there’s a clear line between the vision he articulated in 1981, and the case he made emphasizing his successes eight years later. And, as he would say in his Farewell Address in his folksy, aw shucks way, looking back on his administration, and his first inauguration: “All in all, not bad. Not bad at all.”

The Second Inaugural Address of Ronald Reagan

by Iwan W. Morgan

Ronald Reagan’s inauguration to a second term as president marked the fiftieth inaugural ceremony in American history and the only one ever to be held indoors in the Capitol Rotunda (bitterly cold weather had ruled out the traditional open-air ceremony). At 2,561 words, his inaugural address was the longest for a second-term president since James Monroe’s tally of 4,472 in 1821. Reagan had delivered his first inaugural address in 1981 amid the worst economic conditions since the Great Depression of the 1930s and at a dangerous time in the Cold War when the Soviet Union appeared to have gained ascendancy over the United States. In 1985, however, the country was once more prosperous, secure, and optimistic about the future. In recognition of this, voters had re-elected Reagan to a second term in 1984 by a landslide over Democrat Walter Mondale—he received 58.8 percent of the popular vote and carried every state except Minnesota (plus the District of Columbia). His second Inaugural Address spoke to America’s restored confidence in expressing pride at the progress made in the last four years and looking ahead to what needed to be done in the next four to consolidate national renewal. In many ways, it followed on in spirit from the iconic political commercial of his re-election campaign, "It’s morning again in America."

In his first Inaugural Address, Reagan insisted that restoration of prosperity depended on reducing the size of the federal government and cutting federal taxes in order to incentivize wealth-creation by individual Americans. This conservative anti-statist message was also at the heart of his 1985 address, which identified the two key domestic goals of his second administration as being tax reform and deficit elimination. With regard to the former, he avowed, "We must simplify our tax system, make it more fair and bring the rates down for all who work and earn." These words heralded the enactment of the Tax Reform Act of 1986, the most significant tax reform measure of the second half of the twentieth century. This simplified the tax code into two brackets (instead of fourteen), removed the working poor from the tax rolls, and eliminated or reduced numerous tax-breaks enjoyed by business and investors to pay for this largesse.

In contrast, Reagan fell far short in his pursuit of a balanced budget because he wanted to achieve one entirely through domestic program retrenchment whereas Democrats and Republican fiscal hawks in Congress called for military cutbacks and tax increases. This failure to find political agreement also doomed Reagan’s advocacy in the 1985 inaugural address of a constitutional amendment to stop the federal government spending more than it took in annually in taxes. Instead of restoring fiscal discipline, he would preside over an era of unprecedented deficit expansion and public debt growth: in 1981 he had told Americans that gross federal debt was equivalent to a stack of $1,000 bills 67 miles high, but when he left office the pile was some 200 miles high.

Reagan’s 1985 Inaugural Address also referenced America’s recent progress in advancing African American civil rights but acknowledged that more needed to be done to build a country "rich in dignity and abundant with opportunity for all our citizens." These good intentions fell on largely deaf black ears. African Americans were the one group who remained resistant to his optimistic vision of America’s future because they resented his first-term retrenchment of public assistance programmes and his continuing toleration of lilywhite private Christian schools in the South. In his last year in office, Reagan would veto the Civil Rights Restoration Act of 1988 to strengthen educational desegregation on grounds that this represented an unjustified expansion of federal authority over the decisions of private organizations. This made him the first president since Andrew Johnson in 1866 to veto a civil rights bill, but he was quickly overridden by Congress.

If Reagan’s upbeat inaugural vision of America’s future did not endear him to African Americans, it was also out of step with the constrained economic prospects of millions of ordinary Americans, regardless of their race, Notwithstanding the Great Depression, the US economy performed remarkably well in the first 75 years of the twentieth century in keeping average income mostly rising and economic inequality mainly falling. In the years from the late 1970s to the present, the former has stagnated and the latter has soared. Broader structural changes in the economy pertaining to the growing significance of finance and technology and the loss of manufacturing jobs made it harder for many in the lower half of the income distribution to secure decently-paid employment. Nevertheless, Reagan’s economic policies contributed to rising income inequality because they disproportionately benefited the wealthy in reducing government and cutting taxes.

Reagan’s 1985 inaugural address focused mainly on domestic issues but gave much more attention to foreign and defense issues than its 1981 predecessor. In his first term he had launched America’s greatest defense expansion since the Korean War to overtake the perceived lead that the Soviets had gained in defence capabilities in the 1970s. This had intensified the Cold War, causing many Americans to grow concerned that the world was heading for nuclear confrontation. Seeking to reassure them that his goal was "peace through strength", Reagan put increasing emphasis on his desire to negotiate nuclear-arms reduction in his re-election campaign. Continuing this theme, his 1985 Inaugural Address looked forward to "the total elimination one day of nuclear weapons from the face of the Earth." In it, he also spoke of his plans for research into the development of the Strategic Defense Initiative (SDI), popularly dubbed "Star Wars", to construct a space-based security shield that could prevent incoming missiles from reaching America in the event of a nuclear attack.

In his second term, Reagan’s determination to follow through on nuclear arms reduction made greater progress than almost everyone but him expected. He was fortunate to deal with a new Kremlin leader, Mikhail Gorbachev, who realized that the Soviet economy could not sustain the arms race. In four summit meetings at Geneva, Reykjavik, Washington and Moscow, their negotiations produced the Intermediate Nuclear Force Treaty of 1987, which eliminated an entire class of nuclear weapons for the first time in history, and laid the foundations for the peaceful termination of the Cold War in the early 1990s. Paradoxically, SDI was a stumbling block in their early talks because Reagan would not agree to its elimination. Gorbachev decided, however, that he should not throw away the chance of lasting peace for a weapon still only in the research phase of development.

Reagan’s second term would end on a great foreign policy triumph but international affairs nearly undid him prior to this success. In contrast to his 1981 address that portrayed the rising threat of communism, his 1985 inaugural spoke of freedom, "one of the deepest and noblest aspirations of the human spirit," being on the march in the world, nowhere more so than in America’s own hemisphere, and promised support for its advance. This was a veiled reference to the secret financial assistance to buy arms that the Reagan administration was providing, in violation of congressional prohibitions, for the Contra rebels in their campaign to overthrow the Marxist Sandinista government of Nicaragua. This illegal initiative soon intersected with another to sell arms to Iran in violation of American and international law in return for its help in freeing US hostages held by Islamist groups in the Lebanon. In late 1986, shortly after funds from these sales began to be diverted to the Contras, both operations came to light. Reagan found himself under scrutiny for his role in the so-called Iran-Contra affair that might have become his Watergate, but investigators accepted his disavowals of detailed knowledge of the transactions.

Reagan had no thought of what lay ahead with Iran-Contra when delivering his 1985 Inaugural Address, one of the most optimistic of all time. The fortieth president’s confidence in his country shines through it. The address contained several historical references to how Americans had endured difficult times in the past while remaining united in their common cause of advancing freedom. An extended passage spoke of how two of the founders, John Adams and Thomas Jefferson, had renewed their friendship in old age after falling out over the election of 1800. Far from being nostalgic for bygone times, Reagan’s historical parables were intended to guide America’s future, which he believed would be even greater than its past. Essential for this in his mind was that his fellow-citizens should focus on what united rather than divided them. Today’s Americans might profitably read (or listen to) the 1985 Inaugural Address to heed its stress on national unity. Ronald Reagan, one suspects, would have been uncomfortable with the political polarization of the early twenty-first century.

"A Thousand Points of Light": The Inaugural Address of George H. W. Bush

by Mary Kate Cary

President George H. W. Bush gave his inaugural address on the 200th anniversary of George Washington’s Inauguration. To mark the occasion, he chose to be sworn in on two Bibles: the one that George Washington used, and a family Bible opened to the Beatitudes. As the historian and author Jon Meacham pointed out to him, George Bush was one of only three presidents—along with Washington and Eisenhower—to open his address with a prayer. Meacham quoted that prayer years later at Bush’s funeral, in his famous eulogy for the late president.

President Bush once reminisced about his inaugural address in a compilation of his favorite speeches, entitled

Speaking of Freedom

. In it, he remembered the details of the day:

“Inauguration Day at dawn was beautiful and sunny, with just a little chill in the air—nothing like the bitter cold of some past inaugurations in Washington. We were all up early, and the day began with a family prayer service at St. John’s Church on Lafayette Square. Afterward, Barbara and I met the Reagans for coffee at the White House, which was very relaxing.”

Once they arrived at the ceremonies, the President-elect enjoyed being surrounded on the podium by his wife, children, grandchildren, and his eighty-seven-year-old mother, as Justice Sandra Day O’Connor swore in Vice President Quayle, and Chief Justice William Rehnquist “did the honors” for President Bush. Then the President remembered this about the address itself, which was written with the help of former Reagan speechwriter Peggy Noonan:

“When we began working on the speech earlier in January, I knew I wanted to begin with a prayer. A few other presidents have done that, but not too many. Then the speech went on to describe what I called ‘the age of the offered hand.’ We were seeking a new engagement with others—whether domestically, through those Americans already known as ‘the thousand points of light,’ as we sought to solve our nation’s toughest challenges; through our relations with Congress, to work together without partisan rancor; or through our efforts to work with other nations to promote freedom for all people and end oppression. All over the world, the day of the dictator was over, and a ‘new breeze was blowing.’”

The theme of the speech was built upon a powerful but unattributed quote: “I take as my guide the hope of a saint: in crucial things, unity; in important things, diversity; in all things, generosity.”

For example, in the speech, the President made a reference to President Kennedy’s inaugural address. Kennedy had said in 1960: “Now the trumpet summons us again—not as a call to bear arms, though arms we need; not as a call to battle, though embattled we are …”

Instead, President Bush added to Kennedy’s allegory: “Some see leadership as high drama and the sound of trumpets calling, and sometimes it is that. But I see history as a book with many pages, and each day we fill a page with acts of hopefulness and meaning. The new breeze blows, a page turns, the story unfolds. And so, today a chapter begins, a small and stately story of unity, diversity, and generosity—shared and written, together.”

He referred to this theme of unity, diversity, and generosity again when he turned dramatically to face the assembled House and Senate leadership next to him on the steps of the U.S. Capitol: “To my friends, and yes, I do mean friends—in the loyal opposition, and yes, I mean loyal—I put out my hand. I am putting out my hand to you, Mr. Speaker. I am putting out my hand to you, Mr. Majority Leader. For this is the thing: this is the age of the offered hand … The American people await action. They didn’t send us here to bicker. They ask us to rise above the merely partisan. ‘In crucial things, unity’—and this, my friends, is crucial.”

To critics, the “age of the offered hand” sounded naive, given that both houses of Congress were under Democratic control—in fact, Democrats were then nearing 40 years of majority rule in the House—and increasing partisanship roiled Washington. However, President Bush went on to win bipartisan support for landmark legislation such as the 1990 Civil Rights Act, the Clean Air Act of 1990, and the Americans with Disabilities Act—as well as Congressional approval for the successful first Persian Gulf War.

But perhaps the biggest legacy of the speech was its foreshadowing of the end of the Cold War and the fall of the Soviet empire. President Bush rightly sensed that the great nations dominated by the Soviets were moving toward democracy, and that their citizens knew how to secure a more just and prosperous life for themselves. We wouldn’t need to invent a new system for them, he said, because, “We know what works: Freedom works. We know what’s right: Freedom is right.” Within a year of his Inaugural, the Berlin Wall would come crashing down and millions of East Europeans would be freed from totalitarianism—without a shot being fired. He later spoke often of “Europe, whole and free.”

“Re-reading the speech now,” President Bush wrote years later, “I am struck by the feeling we all had that tremendous change was about to take place, and the sense of momentum that was with us all that day.”

How right he was. The world events that took place soon after his Inaugural address changed the lives of millions of people all over the globe. George Bush will best be remembered for standing for unity, diversity, and generosity during a crucial moment in world history.

The Comeback Kid
The First Inaugural Address of Bill Clinton

by Steven M. Gillon

As he stood before the flag-draped façade of the Capitol, with a sea of people stretching to the Washington Monument, Arkansas governor William Jefferson Clinton witnessed a deeply divided and demoralized nation. His party had been out of power for 12 years, during which a revitalized conservative movement led by Ronald Reagan scaled back cherished Democratic social programs. While Reagan’s successor, George H. W. Bush, had skillfully led the nation’s response to the end of the Cold War, he had neglected problems on the home front. After seven booming years, the economy sputtered. The GNP increased at an anemic 2.2 percent, a reflection of rising unemployment, falling housing starts, and low consumer confidence.

Despite Bush’s economic failures, the Democratic Party in 1993 was still trying to recover from old political wounds. During the 1960s, the once powerful New Deal coalition had shattered in the face of hot button social issues involving race, crime, and taxes. These deep divisions reached a boiling point in 1992 after the acquittal of four white police officers accused of savagely beating an African American motorist, Rodney King. Shortly after the verdicts were announced, African Americans in South Central Los Angeles erupted into the deadliest urban riot in over a century. By the time the violence ended three days later, 58 people lay dead, over 800 buildings were destroyed, and thousands more were damaged or looted. During his campaign, Clinton had attributed the riots to “12 years of denial and neglect” of festering racial issues under Reagan and Bush. But an opposing explanation—first touted by Nixon in the late 1960s—argued that such unrest revealed the necessity for “law and order.” Once elected, Clinton would also embrace this alternate narrative, striking a balance between activist social policy and more punitive measures.

By straddling political divides in this way, the Clinton presidency seemed for many observers to promise a turning point, a shift away from the stale partisan debates that had divided the nation since the 1960s. After all, Clinton had won the presidency by blending liberal and conservative positions. He had campaigned for office as a “New Democrat,” someone who understood the economic concerns of the struggling middle class, while also adopting traditionally conservative positions on crime and welfare. In the weeks before the address, Clinton made clear to speechwriters that he wanted to use this moment to emphasize the concept of an “American renewal” which fused elements of both tradition and innovation.

His inaugural address, just 14 minutes long, was the third shortest in televised history, but it did not lack substance. After thanking his predecessor and others of his generation for their service and sacrifice, Clinton proclaimed that a new generation had come to power—“a generation raised in the shadow of the Cold War.” He challenged this subset of “young Americans” to embark on what he called “a season of service” and pledged that his administration, as the standard-bearer for this generation, would do its part to revitalize the country.

It was not difficult for Clinton to make the case that his election represented a thorough changing of the guard. Only 46 years old, Clinton was the third youngest president in history, after John F. Kennedy and Theodore Roosevelt. As America’s first “baby boomer” president, Clinton possessed no memory of World War II. Instead, his political views were shaped by the tumultuous events of the 1960s—the civil rights movement, antiwar protests, and a youth-led rebellion against authority. With an identity born from this revolutionary era, Clinton appeared to intimately understand the nature of radical change.

But Clinton’s novelty did not mean an ignorance of the past, and his speechwriters made sure to sprinkle his address with subtle references to previous presidents. In addition to invoking George Washington and Thomas Jefferson, Clinton paid homage to Abraham Lincoln’s Gettysburg Address by calling for a celebration of “the mystery of American renewal.” The inauguration, he continued, was “held in the depth of winter, but by the words we speak and the faces we show the world, we force the spring.” This season signaled a renaissance, when “the world’s oldest democracy” would manifest “the vision and courage to reinvent” itself. Hinting at what would guide this reinvention, Clinton invoked Franklin Roosevelt’s call during the Great Depression for “bold, persistent experimentation.” Most significantly, America’s rebirth would embrace the spirit of John F. Kennedy, someone Clinton had idolized since the age of 16. Echoing JFK’s inaugural address, Clinton emphasized the necessity of sacrifice and service. “My fellow Americans,” he stated in his casual, conversational tone, “you, too, must play your part in our renewal.” In summoning these themes—rebirth, experimentation, sacrifice—Clinton positioned himself within a specific political genealogy, one that stood for liberalism’s deepest values.

Yet, his words were also tinged with more conservative overtones regarding responsibility and limited government. In an obvious reference to his campaign promise to “end welfare as we know it,” Clinton asserted that the time had come to “break the bad habit of expecting something for nothing, from our Government or from each other.” He then offset this statement with an appeal for togetherness: “Let us all take more responsibility, not only for ourselves and our families but for our communities and our country.” By yoking individual responsibility to social awareness, Clinton was starting to present the contours of a new kind of centrism.

Clarifying this centrism also meant criticizing the Bush presidency, an approach that Clinton had honed during his campaign for president. People, he declared, were “working harder for less” while health care costs devastated families and “the fear of crime” sowed distrust among many Americans. “We know we have to face hard truths and take strong steps, but we have not done so” he said in an obvious jab at his predecessor. “Instead, we have drifted, and that drifting has eroded our resources, fractured our economy and shaken our confidence.” The Bush administration, Clinton implied, had left the nation lost and unmoored without a robust social safety net.

Significantly, though, Clinton’s approach to these problems blended aspects previously seen as incompatible. His campaign booklet “Putting People First” had outlined how his administration planned to expand social programs that had been starved during the previous 12 years. Indeed, before the election, he rarely even mentioned the deficit. But by the time of his inauguration, Clinton switched gears and decided to make deficit reduction, not new spending, his top priority. “To renew America we must be bold,” he said. “We must do what no generation has had to do before. We must invest more in our own people—in their jobs and in their future—and at the same time cut our massive debt.” That seeming contradiction—practicing financial discipline while also investing in the future—would prove to be one of the greatest challenges faced by the Clinton administration.

But embracing those challenges, Clinton claimed, was necessary to adapt to the new world order. For the previous half-century, the threat of Soviet aggression abroad and communist subversion at home had forged a fragile consensus in favor of an interventionist foreign policy. Now, with the Cold War over, Clinton stressed how advances in technology and global trade bound the world together, presenting both unprecedented opportunities and challenges. This globalized “New World” was “more free but less stable,” because “profound and powerful forces” exerted constant, unpredictable change. Thus, America’s most urgent task would be to discover how to “make change our friend and not our enemy.” And one way to do that, he suggested, was to adopt new frameworks for thinking about and doing politics.

However, the high-minded tone of this speech disguised a troubling political reality. Clinton fully realized that he had secured only 43 percent of the popular vote. To assemble a governing coalition, he needed to win over the 19 percent of the electorate who had cast a ballot for eccentric Texas billionaire Ross Perot, whose campaign had focused on deriding the corruption and waste in Washington. In a direct appeal to these voters, Clinton acknowledged that while the capital “is often a place of intrigue and calculation,” under his administration, politics would be reformed so that “power and privilege no longer shout down the voice of the people.”

After this mildly populist promise, the new president concluded with a rhetorical flourish, invoking God’s help in achieving his agenda. “From this joyful mountaintop of celebration, we hear a call to service in the valley,” Clinton concluded. “We have heard the trumpets. We have changed the guard. And now, each in our own way and with God’s help, we must answer the call.”

But no appeal to the Almighty could erase an indisputable fact: not everyone embraced Clinton’s call for change. Soon enough, the intensity of that opposition would become boldly apparent, as controversy and scandal engulfed his administration.

The Politician
The Second Inaugural Address of Bill Clinton

by Russell L. Riley

The historical image of Bill Clinton as president is dominated by Bill Clinton the politician. Both favorable and unfavorable accounts of Clinton’s incumbency tend to focus on his political pliancy. The upside, for those who find merit in Clinton’s ways, was a rare level of success for a Democratic president in an epoch typically unfriendly to his party at the presidential level. In the three elections before Clinton succeeded in 1992, his party had secured only 173 electoral votes in total, nearly one hundred short of the level needed for victory in a single cycle. Moreover, two years into his presidency, the so-called “permanent” Democratic majority in the House of Representatives fell victim to Newt Gingrich’s Republican Revolution, joining a newly Republican Senate, too. Presidential achievement in this environment, using any standard metric, is difficult. Thus Clinton’s successes, including a rare Democratic reelection and a balanced federal budget, built on an innovator’s flexibility in setting objectives and a mariner’s skill in tacking towards them. He was, by the favorable portraiture of journalist Joe Klein, “the Natural.”

However, for his opponents, this adaptability was a sign that Clinton had no principles, either in matters of public business or in his private affairs. He was “Slick Willie,” spineless, unmoored to anything other than his own success. Ironically, then, Bill Clinton’s shape-shifting was, by this common characterization, at the center of both his extraordinary successes and his extreme failures as president.

Clinton’s second inaugural address, however, demonstrates a flaw in this interpretation. It reveals a consistent and durable core to Bill Clinton’s approach to politics. Three familiar keywords stand out: opportunity, responsibility, and community. History shows that these are not casual references tossed into the speech as polite applause lines. They are instead cornerstones to a persistent philosophy of government.

They appear together most prominently in Clinton’s May 1991 keynote address to the Democratic Leadership Council (DLC), the centrist party organization he helped to develop in the lean decade of the 1980s. Bruce Reed, who would become Clinton’s White House domestic policy advisor, later observed that this “was the speech of [Clinton’s] life … and still one of the best political speeches I’ve ever seen anyone give…. [It was] pitch perfect.” Its core message? A call “to give the people a new choice … that offers opportunity, demands responsibility, gives citizens more say … —all because we recognize that we are a community, we are all in this together, and we are going up or down together” (emphasis added). The remainder of the speech was devoted to elaborating on each element of that triad. Then, as DLC founder Al From was to observe, these concepts were at the heart of Clinton’s presidency, buttressing his efforts to reform the national welfare system, his sense of fiscal responsibility, his embrace of free trade, and his focus on national service.

These themes were demonstrably not the ephemeral product of a focus group or a tactical response to the dynamics of a single campaign season. They were, instead, the product of long and hard thought by Clinton about how his chosen party could succeed in a nation that had in five of six elections voted overwhelmingly against it.

Clinton was a southerner and a Democrat. But he was not in any conventional sense a Southern Democrat. On cultural issues, especially race and gender, he was decidedly a product of the 1960s, his inclusive sensibilities whetted at Oxford and Yale. And he retained a faith in activist government that did not much survive the civil rights movement in the white South. Yet because he chose to pursue a political career in his native Arkansas, Southern Democrats dominated his world. Their reactions determined whether he would succeed or fail. Thus he learned how to lead among people who were often skeptical of his intentions. He knew they had to be brought along. Opportunity, responsibility, and community was an incantation, intended to help Americans accept a role for government that might not occur naturally to them.

Still, it is tempting to dismiss these as mere catchwords, meaningless because they are so common in our political discourse—standards, as it were, in the Great American Songbook. But a review of all the inaugural speeches since World War II indicates otherwise. In only one address before Clinton’s time, Reagan’s second (in 1985), were all three words included—and even that instance is not a direct parallel, because Reagan spoke solely of “the responsibility of the National Government,” not personal responsibility in the Clintonian sense. So Clinton’s invocation was practically unique. Given that history, a second discovery is equally striking: George W. Bush included all three in his 2001 inaugural, echoing (without acknowledging the fact) Clinton on all points. For example, “America, at its best,” Bush noted, “is a place where personal responsibility is valued and expected. Encouraging responsibility is … a call to conscience.” This suggests that Clinton’s influence on his times—notwithstanding his own personal irresponsibilities—was more substantial than has been previously acknowledged, and might have persisted had the events of September 11, 2001 not completely upturned the nation’s political terrain.

These notes of remarkable consistency, however, are embedded in a speech otherwise infused with great uncertainty. Clinton’s second inaugural exposes a president laboring to fathom the obscure currents of history engulfing his times and how best to respond to them. There are two components of the speech where these uncertainties are especially notable.

The first is in the state of America’s foreign relations. For the previous fifty years, presidents could always fall back on Cold War-rhetoric, and the unifying mission of defeating global communism, as a consistent element of the job description. But Clinton was elected immediately after the Cold War had ended. His foreign policy team had tried fruitlessly throughout his first term to identify what would come next—a simple organizing principle that would communicate the nation’s approach to an indeterminate new era. Absent that new consensus, the 1997 inaugural address was far less concerned with foreign affairs than most since the Second World War. The term “terror” does get two quick mentions, foreshadowing a world to come. Otherwise, foreign policy gets comparatively meager attention.

Second, this speech reveals a leader trying to find his own way in these uncharted waters. Clinton had always wanted to be not just a good president, but a great one. His fine grasp of American history, however, told him that the greats were mainly the product of war or some other major emergency. And he knew that he was serving in an almost uniquely peaceful era for the United States. That reality sent him on an intellectual quest—to identify a powerful example unconnected to those common kinds of crises, who in turn might be a model for the heroic presidency he wanted his to be. This search led him to Theodore Roosevelt.

By Clinton’s (idiosyncratic) reading, Roosevelt drew his strength from his ability to navigate the United States successfully through the dramatic economic upheavals at the beginning of the 20th century. His use of the national government to rein in the excesses of industrial America, and to moderate the disruptive forces caused by mass relocations “from farm to factory … [and] from country to city,” were what, by Clinton’s reading, put Roosevelt on Mount Rushmore. But they also gave Clinton reason to see parallels in his own time.

Theodore Roosevelt is nowhere mentioned in Clinton’s second inaugural address. But much of the speech is given over to describing a political and economic environment much like Roosevelt’s. The country was “at the edge of a new century,” an era of sweeping change. “We began the 20th century with a choice, to harness the Industrial Revolution to our values of free enterprise, conservation, and human decency. Those choices made all the difference. At the dawn of the 21st century a free people must now choose to shape the forces of the Information Age and the global society, to unleash the limitless potential of all our people…. We need a new government for a new century.” That historical predicate provided Roosevelt the foundations for presidential greatness. Perhaps it would do the same for him.

It did not. Although Clinton’s second term difficulties had little to do with anything related to this address, his attempt to define the times was too abstract for most to grasp, and his claim to Roosevelt’s mantle met with a disdainful reaction as trial balloons circulated in the press. Theodore Roosevelt biographer Edmund Morris, for example, penned a dismissive op-ed for the New York Times pungently headed “The Rough Rider and the Easy One.” So on these grounds, the speech didn’t work. But it isn’t alone.

Second inaugural addresses are notoriously difficult. Indeed some presidential speechwriters have suggested that they should be graded on a generous curve, perhaps tossing out Lincoln’s entirely to make things fair. The huge benefit inherent in most—meaning first—inaugural addresses is that they have all the advantages of newness, of turning the page, just months after the electorate has announced that change is exactly what it wanted. Every second inaugural address, conversely, is freighted with the weight of continuity. The excitement of a new beginning can seldom be replicated. Thus, second inaugurals are always written on unwashed blackboards: The words may be meaningful and well-constructed, but the chalk is never as vibrant as when the slate was clean.

The First Inaugural Address of George W. Bush

by James Mann

George W. Bush was the first president in more than a century to lose the popular vote but win the Electoral College; one had to go back to Benjamin Harrison in 1888 to find a comparable election. Bush had, moreover, won in the Electoral College only after the Supreme Court had ruled, by the close vote of 5 to 4, that Florida’s electoral votes should be awarded to him and not his Democratic opponent, Al Gore. Under those circumstances, Bush chose the theme for his Inaugural Address to be one of civility, delivering a speech that offered only a few glimpses of the initiatives and ideas that would follow in his presidency. Yet they were in the speech, if one looked closely.

The dispute in Florida had been bitter and prolonged, arousing passions and partisanship that were still raw on Inauguration Day. Despite the damp, foggy weather, roughly 300,000 people turned out on the streets of Washington. Protesters carried signs that said, “Hail to the Thief.” Bush supporters, in turn, countered with placards that said, “W Stands for Winner.”

Gathered around the stage for the swearing-in was an array of leaders who had dominated public life in America in previous years or would do so in the years to come. The leaders of the past started with Bush’s proud, teary father George H.W. Bush; the Bushes were that day about to become the first father-son team of presidents since the Adams family. The outgoing president Bill Clinton sat on the stage, too, along with Gore, the outgoing vice president. Hillary Clinton, who had two weeks earlier been elected to the U.S. Senate, sat alongside her husband. The master of ceremonies for the day’s events was Mitch McConnell, who was then the Senate majority whip. Looking on from a choice seat just off the stage was the mayor of New York, Rudy Giuliani, just entering into what many assumed would be a relatively uneventful final year in office.

What George W. Bush gave them and those who watched on television that day was a 14-minute paean to civic virtues, repeatedly emphasizing the importance of showing respect to political opponents. He first thanked Clinton for his service and then thanked Gore for “a contest conducted with spirit and ended with grace.” Bush alluded to the partisan divisions of the election in soothing terms. “Sometimes our differences run so deep, it seems we share a continent, but not a country. We do not accept this and we will not allow it,” Bush said. Not just once but three times he returned specifically to the theme of civility in political discourse. “Civility is not a tactic or a sentiment. It is the determined choice of trust over cynicism, of community over chaos,” he asserted.

After all the tensions of the disputed election, the reaction to these passages would be overwhelmingly positive. “A Step Toward Common Ground,” a headline on the front page of the Washington Post said the following day. The New York Times news analysis said Bush had “started to dispel the challenges to his legitimacy.” Liberal columnist E.J. Dionne called the speech “excellent” and “Bush at his best.”

The address, written by Bush’s speechwriter Michael Gerson, was cast mostly in terms of abstractions and ideals. Yet within the speech, there were also just a few words and phrases that served brief notice of the political battles that would later come to dominate George W. Bush’s presidency. In fact, the speech contained offerings to each of the three conservative constituencies that had helped Bush win the Republican nomination.

Some history is in order here. Ronald Reagan had assembled a Republican coalition that had brought together tax-cutting libertarians, foreign-policy hawks, and evangelicals. All three of these constituencies had then, in different ways, become disaffected with President George H.W. Bush. Throughout the 1990s, in the wake of his father’s failure to win re-election, George W. Bush forged strong links to all three of these conservative factions within the party. He had, for example, promised substantial tax cuts during his presidential campaign.

In his Inaugural Address, George W. Bush gave a nod to each constituency. For economic conservatives, Bush promised, “We will reform Social Security and Medicare. … And we will reduce taxes to recover the momentum of our economy.” As it turned out, Bush would not press hard to privatize Social Security until his second term, and even then he failed. But he would move for significant taxes cuts in the first six months of his presidency, and in that he succeeded.

For evangelicals, the speech contained religious references, indeed ten of them in the short address. “When we see that wounded traveler on the road to Jericho, we will not pass to the other side,” said Bush, referring to the parable of the Good Samaritan. This and the other references were offered as part of Bush’s campaign theme of compassionate conservatism. It included, among other things, the idea of faith-based initiatives that would take social programs out of the control of the government and into the hands of churches and charities. That idea, too, could be found in the Inaugural, though couched in abstract wording: “Compassion is the work of a nation, not just a government,” Bush asserted. “And some needs and some hurts are so deep they will only respond to a mentor’s touch or a pastor’s prayer.”

So then what about foreign policy? Where in this Inaugural are any precursors to the future war in Iraq, the single aspect of Bush’s presidency for which he would most be remembered? Where, in other words, are the references in the speech aimed at hawks or neoconservatives?

One answer might be that the September 11 attacks, which set in motion the chain of events leading up to the Iraq War, hadn’t happened yet. On Inauguration Day, there were already a few within the administration who were pressing for more aggressive action against Saddam Hussein, but at that point, it was a secondary issue; at the time of the Inaugural, the neoconservatives had other priorities. At the top of their wish list was the desire for the United States to withdraw from the ABM Treaty of 1972, which stood in the way of the United States constructing missile-defense systems. In the careful phrasing of Bush’s Inaugural, they could find a passage alluding to missile defense: “We will confront weapons of mass destruction, so that a new century is spared new horrors.” Eleven months later, Bush would announce that the United States was formally withdrawing from the ABM treaty.

The word Iraq itself isn’t in the speech. But look carefully and one finds a seemingly cryptic seven-word phrase that hints at some the broader ideas and the intellectual debates that led up to the Iraq War. Bush declared at one point that America sought to shape “a balance of power that favors freedom.”

That phrase almost certainly came from Condoleezza Rice, who had served as the principal foreign-policy advisor during Bush’s campaign and was that day taking over as his national security advisor. The phrase was an allusion to the longstanding debates over realism vs. idealism in foreign policy, Rice had written an article for Foreign Affairs the previous year that discussed the idea and limits of a balance-of-power approach to the world, and in the fall of 2002, as the United States was moving determinedly toward war with Iraq, she gave a speech that was specifically entitled, “A Balance of Power that Favors Freedom.”

What did that mean? Again, some background is relevant here. The neoconservative movement first became galvanized in foreign policy during the Nixon administration, in opposition to Henry Kissinger’s balance-of-power diplomacy in general and to détente with the Soviet Union in particular. Careful balance-of-power considerations then once again dominated the thinking of the George H.W. Bush administration, during which the president and his national security advisor Brent Scowcroft had labored to avoid a break in relations with China and had sought to slow down the break-up of the Soviet Union. Indeed, one of the several reasons the George H.W. Bush administration had decided not to go on to Baghdad at the end of the Persian Gulf War in 1991 had been a balance-of-power consideration: the desire to leave Iraq in a position to serve as a counterweight to Iran.

Rice herself had been a protégé of Scowcroft. She and others in the administration were not prepared, at the very start of the new administration, to throw out completely the concept of balance of power diplomacy. But they also wanted to acknowledge the neoconservative argument that a reliance on balance-of-power considerations fails to take into account the ideals of freedom and democracy. Hence, “a balance of power that favors freedom” amounted to a declaration that the new administration would not be governed by realist, balance-of-power concerns to the extent that Bush’s father’s administration had been.

Finally, the wording of Bush’s Inaugural also suggested to an activist, interventionist role for the United States overseas. A decade after the end of the Cold War, more than a few Americans were arguing that there were not many causes America needed to become involved in overseas. Bush rejected that notion. “The stakes for America are never small,” he said. “If our country does not lead the cause of freedom, it will not be led.”

There was very little commentary concerning these phrases in the speech on Inauguration Day or the days afterward. They were mostly lost amid Bush’s repeated appeals for civility and unity. Indeed, at the time of the Inauguration, there was considerable speculation that, the new president, having come to the White House, without a majority of the popular vote, Bush would of necessity have to move to the center of the political spectrum and to win Democratic support in order to govern.

It didn’t turn out that way. Bush pressed hard for tax cuts in the earliest months of his presidency and got them passed in the face of substantial Democratic opposition. The following year he began driving toward a war with Iraq that produced even more intense divisions within the country than had the 2000 election.

Throughout it all, Bush remained generally civil to his political opponents, in striking contrast with the next Republican president, Donald Trump. But for Bush, civility in style definitely did not mean centrism in substance.

A Vision of America
The Second Inaugural Address of George W. Bush

by Mark J. Rozell

President George W. Bush delivered his second inaugural address on January 20, 2005, after having won a meaningful reelection with a majority national popular vote and clear Electoral College majority. Bush’s first term initially stood under the cloud of his having lost the popular vote to Democrat Al Gore, and emerging barely victorious after a disputed election settled by the U.S. Supreme Court by a one-vote margin thirty-six days after Election Day.

The terrorist attacks on the United States on September 11, 2001 transformed Bush’s presidency and established the context for a second inaugural address that differed greatly from his first. Bush began his first term committed to a robust domestic policy agenda, having pledged that the United States should not embark on regime change abroad, but rather focus on challenges at home.

After the terrorist attacks, the president pivoted from a domestic policy focus to protecting the homeland and combatting forces of terrorism abroad. The United States thus embarked on military actions and eventual occupations in Afghanistan and Iraq, with strong bipartisan support in Congress and the national generally. As the Middle East wars dragged on long beyond public expectations and American casualties grew, support for the president’s actions abroad declined and thus he entered the 2004 election cycle in a difficult political position.

Bush’s victory in 2004 over Democratic Senator John Kerry gave the president the opportunity to define his legacy—a task he would begin to take up in his second inaugural address and second-term policy agenda. The president’s address projected a bold vision of the United States’s worldwide leadership in promoting human freedom and liberty. It was a speech that harkened back to the ideals of Woodrow Wilson and John F. Kennedy.

Bush opened by establishing the historic context of the times—that the United States had fought a long Cold War for freedom, and once victorious “came years of relative quiet, years of repose, years of sabbatical—and then there came a day of fire”, referring to 9/11. The president then notes that this country that stood tall and victorious after the collapse of communism had now “seen our vulnerability”. He attributed that vulnerability to an ideology of hate that posed “a mortal threat”. He proclaimed that only “the force of human freedom” around the world could break this threat. Here the president made his call for the United States to lead the worldwide quest for human freedom and liberty, as a necessary means to protect this country: “The survival of liberty in our land increasingly depend on the success of liberty in other lands. The best hope for peace in our world is the expansion of freedom in all the world”. Whereas John F. Kennedy had called upon the nation to defend freedom around the world wherever it was under threat, Bush here calls for the U.S. to both protect and expand freedom throughout the world.

In making this call for the expansion of freedom around the globe, the president is at once providing a defense of his administration’s military actions in the Middle East, and calling on the United States to embark on an even larger role of international leadership in defense of freedom. Bush then ties this bold internationalist vision to the foundational beliefs of our Republic, that all people have inalienable rights best protected by a system of self-government. Advancing the ideals of our Founding Fathers the president extolled, “is the urgent requirement of our nation’s security, and the calling of our time”.

The president then issues his boldest proclamation: “The survival of liberty in our land increasingly depends on the success of liberty in other lands. The best hope for peace in our world is the expansion of freedom in all the world”.

The president’s soaring rhetoric of the U.S.’s obligation to protect its homeland by promoting liberty abroad recalled his oft-stated controversial claim during his first term that preventing terrorism at home required fighting the terrorists abroad. It was clear at the time of the second inauguration that the United States’s efforts to advance liberty and democratic institutions abroad through military interventions in Afghanistan and Iraq had been a failure, and the costs of the Middle East wars were piling up with no apparent end in sight. What had begun from a conviction that military interventions would topple oppression regimes and democratic institutions would then emerge throughout the region had instead turned into a long-term military engagement seen by many of the peoples of the Middle East as a hostile occupation.

The second inaugural address thus can be seen in part as Bush’s legacy having largely hinged on his administration’s policies of military intervention abroad, and these needed a rationale. Bush drew on American ideals out of its founding and also its past role in fighting tyranny abroad to preserve those ideals and bring freedoms to others. Critics of the president at the time noted that the threat of terrorism was not analogous to the great twentieth century threats to the United States and required a very different twenty-first century strategy. No one questioned the president’s assertions of the rightness of the cause of freedom from oppression, so well expressed in his second inaugural address, but whether the foreign policies of the United States during his administration were conducive to advancing freedoms abroad.

Bush’s second inaugural address had little to say of the domestic policy challenges of his second term. With such a grand vision for the nation’s role in the world framing the first and most substantial portion of the address, his modest goals for America at home stand out in striking contrast. Briefly the president mentions several issues that later he would put forth in his annual State of the Union Address—home ownership, retirement savings, and health insurance reforms. These stand in this speech as mere foreshadowing of a second term domestic agenda.

Finally, the president spoke of advancing freedom depending on the “private character” of the people—“on integrity, and tolerance toward others, and the rule of conscience in our own lives”. He notes that the foundations of character are families, community, and faith. These values are at the core of a highly decentralized governing system that relies on citizen virtue and strong communities. He notes that the country has its divisions, “by party and background”, but are united by “the cause of freedom”.

The common thread of the speech was the president’s call to the nation to advance freedom in the world as the aspiration of all humanity, at a time during which many do not live free. He does not present in his inaugural address any specific policies to advance freedom internationally. Like many inaugural addresses, this one is large on articulating a broad vision, but very short on specifics.

At this writing in late 2020, President Bush’s vision of a nation united in purpose significantly stands in contrast to the contemporary image of the United States as an intensely polarized nation unable to agree on much at all. At a time when many of the nation’s leaders have advanced politically by stoking divisions in the nation, Bush’s call to a common national purpose may seem a hopeless aspiration now. It was a noble quest, presented at a time when the country already was in the throes of partisan division, that would only intensify during the presidencies of Barack Obama and Donald J. Trump. President Bush could not then heal the nation of its divisions, but he set forth the words that addressed a fundamental challenge of our times.

"A New Birth of Freedom"
The First Inaugural Address of Barack Obama

by Tracy Denean Sharpley-Whiting

Barack Obama’s speeches in the run-up to his inauguration in January 2009 were a brew of soaring oration, Aristotelian rhetoric, and elements of the Black Jeremiad. Authors such as Frederick Douglass, with his “What to the Slave Is the Fourth of July?” (1852), Martin Luther King, Jr.’s “The Other America”—delivered at Stanford University in 1967—James Baldwin’s epistolary The Fire Next Time, and Jeremiah Wright’s social gospel-infused sermons were parts of a canon of literature and performance that gave intellectual form and substance to Obama’s oratorical stylings and rhetorical grace. His campaign had used variations of a hope and change motto, while the candidate himself embodied a multiracial America, brimming with expectancy and possibility. And yet, his first inaugural address was decidedly understated. Barack Obama appeared to have taken clearer-eyed stock of the moment.

On Tuesday, January 20th, besides his inauguration, the nation was also celebrating the 200th year anniversary of the birth of America’s 16th president, Abraham Lincoln. Lincoln, the Great Emancipator and uniter in post-Civil War America, had always figured centrally as a point of political comparison and emulation for the Democratic president-elect. Lincoln’s Springfield, Illinois was where both he and then Senator Obama served as state lawmakers and where the late Republican president delivered his 1858 “A House Divided” speech. And Springfield, rather than his adopted hometown of Chicago, was also where Barack Obama announced his candidacy for the presidency. As Lincoln had in 1858 as well as in his two subsequent inaugural addresses of 1861 and 1865, Obama’s first inaugural address similarly broached the themes of unity, war, healing, reconciliation, and rebirth. Despite his having garnered over 65,000,00 votes, the most in a presidential election at that time, an electoral college rout of 365 votes, and an approval rating of 67% that January, America’s house at the start of 2009 was ablaze and surreptitious partisan chicanery was afoot. He would need to rally the nation after a hard-fought and won election, remind them of the guiding principle of E pluribus unum.

Before taking the podium, Obama took a commemorative train ride from Philadelphia, Pennsylvania to Washington, D.C. in honor of Lincoln. Philadelphia, “The City of Brotherly Love,” had also played host to Obama’s campaign-saving speech on race: “A More Perfect Union.” In many respects, his first inaugural address picked up where “A More Perfect Union” left off. America’s 44th president, a mixed-race man who identifies as African American, understood his journey as improbable when he offered that his “father less than 60 years ago might not have been served in the local restaurant.” But there he was now “stand[ing] before you to take a most sacred oath” on “this magnificent mall” with “men and women and children of every race and every faith … every language and culture, drawn from every end of this Earth. … Christians and Muslims, Jews and Hindus, and non-believers.” That what was improbable became possible is, for Obama, a uniquely American story, “the meaning of our liberty and creed.” The American experiment of democracy is necessarily bound up with this braided history. In his recounting of the diversity of the American experience, of those who “traveled across oceans in search of a new life … toiled in sweatshops, and settled the West, endured the lash of the whip, and plowed the hard earth,” one hears echoes of Langston Hughes’s “I Too Sing America” and Walt Whitman’s “I Hear America Singing.” And in a few subtle rhetorical moves, he makes short work of the oversimplified idea of America as a Christian nation of voluntary immigrants. Barack Obama is only the second president in an inaugural address to concede the “peculiar and powerful interest,” as Lincoln so eloquently remarked in his second inaugural address, of enslaved Blacks as involuntary arrivals on America’s shores at its founding. He is also the only president to recognize atheists and agnostics alike in an inaugural address.

Obama had inherited a nation at a bleak crossroads, “amidst gathering clouds and raging storms.” His lesson on our “patchwork heritage” as a signal call to unity, as a benchmark of “our strength,” was the address’s prelude to realism, his ticking off of the dire predicament the country had now found itself. America was enmeshed in two seemingly never-ending wars in Afghanistan and Iraq, the latter of which he had given a full-throated denunciation of as a “dumb war” in 2002 as a junior Senator from Illinois. Rejecting as “false the choice between our safety and our ideals”. … “the rule of law and rights of man,” Obama argued that “our security” emanates from “the justness of our cause.” Unapologetic with respect to America’s “way of life” and unwavering in “its defense,” he was nonetheless unsparing in his criticism of the previous administration’s squandering of America’s resources and use of “power” as unaligned with “the justness of our cause” and “the tempering qualities of humility and restraint.” If wars abroad proved fiscally imprudent and morally dubious, “greed and irresponsibility” ravaged the domestic economy whose automotive, banking and other financial institutions were on the brink of collapse. Failing schools and “[t]oo costly” healthcare rounded out the new president’s litany of indicators of crises. The indices pointed to a “nagging fear that America’s decline is inevitable.”

Obama demanded Americans marshal their collective strength. In looking backward, he cast the war over slavery and session and its deleterious aftermath of segregation as one of America’s greatest challenges. For having “tasted the bitter swill of Civil War and segregation,” a rebirthed nation “emerged from that dark chapter stronger and more united,” he assured his audience. Obama walks his listeners even further back in America’s history to its birth where “patriots huddled on the shores of an icy river,” while “the enemy advance[ed]” as evidence of Americans strength and solidarity. Here he turned to progressive pamphleteer, Thomas Paine, whose inspirational words General George Washington would have read to his soldiers: “Let it be told to the future world … that in the depth of winter, when nothing but hope and virtue could survive … that the city and the country, alarmed at one common danger, came forth to meet [it].”

Given the hardships overcome during these watershed moments in American history, Obama understood that Americans could once again rise to these new challenges by leaning into the values of “honesty and hard work, courage and fair play, tolerance and curiosity, loyalty and patriotism. … [which] have been the quiet force of progress throughout our history.” American exceptionalism, first articulated by Thomas Jefferson, is the sinewy thread throughout the address. And it is this exceptionalism that will compel Americans to “set aside childish things” that “strangled our politics” and sowed division. If American exceptionalism is the thread, then an indivisible America, not a red or a blue America, a theme that resonated throughout his campaign for the presidency, is the needle. Threading the needle, Obama forecasts to the global community that America will be “ready to lead once more.”

“This election,” he argued, represented a pivot in the American mind, the choosing of “hope over fear,” “unity of purpose over conflict and discord.” But Barack Obama’s election also ushered in a new and premature way of thinking about America as postracial. Celebrated as the realization of a dream deferred, the actualization of our democratic ideals in practice, postracial America was but a fever dream ripe for the breaking. Reveling in America’s promise and progress, “gathering clouds” were already on the horizon and swollen to bursting with the emergence of the Tea Party and an era of white grievances and tribalism.

Faith in America's Future: The Second Inaugural Address of Barack Obama

by James T. Kloppenberg

Barack Obama’s second inaugural address invokes Thomas Jefferson’s Declaration of Independence and Abraham Lincoln’s second inaugural in support of principles and policies that Obama championed from his first political campaigns. Obama entered public life as a community organizer in the impoverished Far South Side of Chicago, where he worked with a network of progressive religious activists to address glaring inequalities. His first electoral victory put him in the Illinois State Senate, where he struggled to forge compromises and address partisan gerrymandering. His 2004 speech at the Democratic National Convention, which stressed Americans’ unity at a time of increasingly stark divisions, launched his rapid, unlikely ascent from obscurity to the US Senate in 2004 and the presidency just two years later. In 2012, reelected by a smaller margin than in 2008 and confronting an increasingly hostile Republican majority in Congress, he delivered an inaugural address that showed his debts to the American democratic tradition and highlighted the distinctiveness of his sensibility.

For Obama, liberty always meant more than freedom from constraint. The libertarian idea of freedom, doing whatever an individual wants to do, has dominated Republican Party ideology ever since Ronald Reagan declared government the “problem” in his first inaugural address. Instead, Obama contends that freedom, consistent with the tradition of “ordered liberty” central to American political thought since the seventeenth century, is always bounded by law. Individuals exercise their liberty when they act according to ethical maxims and within legal guidelines, not when they follow their preferences, or their impulses, regardless of the consequences for others.

For Obama, freedom is but an empty promise when individuals lack the means to develop their capacities. In his book

The Audacity of Hope

, Obama embraced the principles that Franklin D. Roosevelt articulated in his final campaign for the presidency in 1944, a “second bill of rights” that includes the right to a job, food, clothing, housing, health care, education, and insurance against the hazards of unemployment and old age. When Obama proclaims that “preserving our individual freedoms ultimately requires collective action,” he has in mind securing individuals’ freedom to fulfill their potential, not freedom from government. He calls for the nation to shoulder its responsibilities to “care for the vulnerable,” to guard everyone from “life’s worst hazards and misfortune,” and to secure for all citizens “a basic measure of security and dignity.”

Equality, as Obama understands it, requires more than equal protection before the law, crucial as that principle is. Like Benjamin Franklin, John Adams, Thomas Jefferson, and James Madison, Obama insists that “our country cannot succeed when a shrinking few do very well and a growing many barely make it.” The nation’s eighteenth-century founders believed that the rough equality of condition enjoyed by American men—with the glaring exception of enslaved Black people—not only distinguished the democratic United States from European monarchies, with their traditions of inherited aristocratic privilege, but it also made possible self-government. Like those earlier champions of democracy, Obama argues for a system of taxation in which the amount owed to the community increases along with the wealth derived from the conditions secured, and the laws enacted, by that community. Working from the premise that “all of us are created equal,” Obama locates more recent campaigns for equality regardless of gender, race, or sexual preference in the tradition of earlier struggles against white male supremacy waged by abolitionists and advocates of woman suffrage.

Much as Americans celebrate “initiative and enterprise,” and productive as America’s market economy has been, Obama argues that the economy “thrives” for all only when it “rewards the effort and determination of every single American.” He rejects the neoliberal idea that increasing innovation and productivity require lavish compensation for some while others cannot escape “the brink of hardship,” let alone “find independence and pride in their work.” Although Obama denies that “all society’s ills can be cured through government alone,” he rejects the shibboleth that all economic regulation is an illegitimate intrusion. Government has set the rules for the marketplace since the eighteenth century, and the nation’s greatest economic growth came through establishing “rules to ensure competition and fair play.” When conditions are as unequal as they are in twenty-first century America, the idea of equal opportunity, like the abstract idea of purely negative freedom from constraints, rings hollow.

Obama also departs from some aspects of earlier American political thought. He denies the existence of uniquely privileged perspectives and universal, unchanging truths. Shaped by late twentieth-century ideas of anti-foundationalism, cultural anthropology, historicism, and philosophical pragmatism, Obama insists that we must not “mistake absolutism for principle.” From his point of view, all ideas should be seen as cultural creations that reflect particular historical circumstances. The meaning of abstract principles such as liberty, equality, and democracy changes over time. Every generation must interpret the Constitution, the living law that “We the People” authorized and possess the power to amend. We must make persuasive arguments based on our values rather than venerating the document as sacred writ. Earlier Americans of European descent took for granted their right to possess lands occupied by indigenous people and their superiority to women and nonwhite people, assumptions about white male supremacy that most Americans now question. For centuries many Americans failed to recognize the need to preserve and protect rather than simply exploit the natural resources of the continent. Now, Obama observes, the hard fact of climate change requires us to develop “sustainable energy sources” to “preserve our planet.”

Finally, Obama accepts not only the inevitability of different points of view but also the potentially productive quality of disagreement. We must not “substitute spectacle for politics” or allow “name-calling” to take the place of “reasoned debate,” because deliberation is the lifeblood of democracy. Americans need not understand liberty, equality, and the role of government in the exact same way in order to respect, debate with, and learn from each other. Self-rule does not require consensus. It demands only reverence for the rule of law, a commitment to marshaling evidence in support of arguments, reliance on persuasion rather than violence, and a willingness to concede our own limitations. Obama concedes that he does not have all the answers; he admits “that our work will be imperfect.” That epistemic humility, which has inspired his admirers and frustrated his critics on the left as well as the right, has from the start been integral to Obama’s understanding of American democracy.

The Inaugural Address of Donald Trump

by Nicholas F. Jacobs

The morning of Friday, January 20, 2017 began as one might expect. The peaceful and orderly transition of presidential power to the 45th President, Donald John Trump, contained all the pomp and circumstance of the traditional Washingtonian affair: morning church services at St. John’s Episcopal Church across from the White House, followed by tea with the Obama’s; the incoming and outgoing presidents shared a motorcade down Pennsylvania Avenue to the Capitol. In the aftermath of one of the most bitterly contested elections in American history, featuring two of the most historically disliked candidates for office, Trump’s Inauguration Day festivities seemed to clamor for a return to normalcy. Welcoming the crowds that had gathered on the Mall to hear the new president speak, Senator Roy Blunt echoed all the trappings of the day’s symbolic importance, quoting Jefferson, Lincoln, FDR, Kennedy, and Reagan in a quick three-minute speech. After all, he argued, presidential inaugurals were “not a celebration of victory, but a celebration of democracy,” that every American could, and should, honor.

But as he had done so many times before, Trump shattered those expectations. For the newly-sworn in president, Inauguration Day—politics in general—was only ever about winning. Trump had built a personal brand around the idea that, in life, as in business, there are only winners or losers. As president, he was to be no loser.

Trump won the Electoral College, although he lost the popular vote by 2.8 million ballots. No matter, this was a day when “the people” would “start winning again, winning like never before.” Standing before former presidents, Congressional leaders, and other long-serving political dignitaries Trump spoke about “their victories,” but echoed his campaign’s central refrain that “their triumphs have not been your triumphs.”

Contemporaneous accounts of Trump’s speech use a variety of adjectives to describe his message: unprecedented, dismal, nationalist, authoritarian, populist. But more than anything else, the simplistic and unadorned notion of “winning” defines the address, as it defines so much of Trump’s public philosophy: the purpose of government is to help those that win, and to help them keep winning; winners get to rule and losers must accept their fate; especially in the global arena, Americans must win first. Despite his speech’s relative simplicity and brevity, this single idea captures much about the state of American politics on the eve of Trump’s inaugural, and what the next four years under a Trump administration would bring. There were winners and losers in politics—no middle ground.

Steve Bannon, one of the architects of Trump’s campaign and likely co-author of the speech, often commented that its anti-establishment rhetoric and disdain for convention were in homage to Andrew Jackson’s grassroots assault on America’s governing institutions in the mid-1800s. In this view, Trump was tapping into a deep history of populist protest, led by strong presidents. Trump’s speech, however, was decidedly modern. Even Jackson’s inaugural referenced the Constitution, and the limits it contained on executive power; even Jackson gave “reverence” for “the examples of public virtue left by my illustrious predecessors.” For Trump, compromise, moderation, and restraint were not ancient virtues, but rather outdated excuses made by “a small group in our nation’s Capital,” the real victors, who perpetually “reaped the rewards of government while the people have borne the cost.”

Trump styled himself as a leader of a new movement—a movement, ironically, of losers. Days leading up to the inaugural, Trump supporters celebrated at “DeploraBalls”—galas named in homage to Hillary Clinton’s off-the-cuff remark that most of her electoral opponents’ supporters could be placed in what she liked to call “the basket of deplorables.” On the campaign trail, as in his inaugural, Trump described the communities in which his movement thrived as one in a state of permanent decline: “trapped in poverty,” “deprived of knowledge,” “robbed … of unrealized potential,” the victims of “American carnage.” Unlike other catastrophes that elevated presidents to office and motivated their calls to unity, Trump portrayed this crisis as one purposefully and deliberately constructed by a ruling class, and which disproportionately affected his followers, the “righteous public.”

For most of those listening to Donald Trump’s address, this was, perhaps, an unrecognizable image of their country. But, to those that voted for Trump, there was enough truth in his message to catapult him into office. As Hillary Clinton would pointedly recognize two years after losing, “I won the places that represent two-thirds of America’s gross domestic product. So I won the places that are optimistic, diverse, dynamic, moving forward, and his whole campaign, ‘make America great again,’ was looking backwards.” Trump won, in other words, the losers in the new global economy. Trump won because he blamed the recognizable, if simplistic problems of open-borders, immigrants, racial antagonisms, China’s unfair business practices, and a ruling elite who profited from the arrangement, including, and perhaps most importantly, members of his own Republican Party. Of course, poor Americans also voted for Clinton as did the wealthy vote for Trump, but Clinton’s comments are a testament to the bi-partisan legitimacy bestowed on Trump’s self-serving idea of a deeply fractured America. Whether it was objectively true is largely beside the point. Perceptions are what counts in politics, and Trump seemed to understand that more than most of his opponents were willing to concede.

The administration’s obsession with the image of winning defined its governing approach from the start. Trump became the first president to formally declare his re-election campaign on Inauguration Day. Barely 24 hours had passed before the White House called its first press conference to accuse the media of intentionally portraying the new president as a loser, because the crowds at his inauguration were visibly smaller than those of the Women’s March on Washington—a hundreds of thousands sized rally the day after Inauguration Day, largely in protest of the new president’s perceived hostility to reproductive rights and gender equality. The president’s chief political advisor and former campaign manager, Kellyanne Conway, gave an unvarnished view of the White House’s decision to challenge the reporting. Conway’s claim that the administration simply gave “alternative facts” to the media’s narrative captured the political double-speak or absurdity of the false numbers the White House produced about T.V. ratings and attendance. But more so, it was demonstrable proof of Trump’s demand that he be seen as a winner. And winners do not have fewer attendees at their inaugural than the president you supposedly repudiated.

Throughout his term, the former reality T.V. star’s actions fit the pattern he established on Inauguration Day. He bragged about large crowds and maintained an exhausting schedule of rallies that crisscrossed the nation—a “thank you tour” that he continued even after he took the oath of office. He intentionally refused to play to presidential expectations—from shrugging off questions about whether he would use his powers to go after political opponents, to refusing to condemn white supremacists in the aftermath of Neo-Nazi demonstrations in Charlottesville, Virginia. No matter his personal sympathies, any other course of action would have suggested that somebody had power over what the president could or should say. That is how losers talk.

Accepting the party’s nomination at the Republican National Convention in 2016, he declared that he “alone” could fix America’s ailments. Whereas other presidents had downplayed the degree to which they relied on executive authority, Trump staged carefully choreographed media ops for almost every executive order he signed, always lifting them up for the cameras to capture his bold signature at the bottom of the page. He signed his first, a largely symbolic order to undermine the implementation of the Affordable Care Act, or Obamacare, just after his inaugural parade ended. Throughout his campaign, Trump promised to “Make America Great Again”—not wealthier, more equal, or run with smaller government. Understanding that “greatness” is always in the eye of the beholder, Trump’s approach to the presidency reflected the orientation of an image-obsessed brand-builder. On June 1, 2020, Trump returned to St. John’s, in the midst of nation-wide protests with systemic racism and police violence—an extraordinary moment of public acknowledgement that any promise of American greatness means addressing these enduring challenges. In contrast, and after ordering the National Guard to disperse peaceful protestors with tear gas, Trump invited the press to photograph him holding up a bible in front of the damaged church—the image of a president in control, and winning.

With time, we will be able to place Trump’s presidency in full historical relief. His actions and rhetoric are so raw that it is near impossible to recognize their consequences in the same way that we might interpret a Roosevelt’s or Adamses. Nevertheless, I would argue that most accounts fail to acknowledge the coherent message that motivated Trump’s campaign for office and his presidency. Some will say that Trump painted a false image of American decline for his political benefit or that he cared about nothing more than his personal aggrandizement. I cannot peer into Trump’s mind and unravel his motives. Over 74 million Americans voted to re-elect Donald Trump—over 11 million more votes than he first received. This was no mere cult of personality. As unconventional and jarring as his Inaugural Address was, it makes clear his commitment to leading a movement of Americans who genuinely felt themselves as disenfranchised, voiceless, and, for too long, on the losing side. Especially since Trump did lose re-election, those feelings are not likely to dissipate anytime soon.

Technical Matter

I hope that by reading the inaugural addresses and essays, you’ve come away with a better understanding of how the United States has reached its current point. Presidents don't live in a vacuum—they are molded by those around them, the times in which they live, and through their experiences. How the Schoolmaster, Woodrow Wilson, approached his presidency was far different from the Tennessee Tailor, Andrew Johnson. And neither had the experiences of Old Hickory, Andrew Jackson, who felt that the presidency was stolen from him in a Corrupt Bargain by John Quincy Adams, the one-term president and son of another one-term president, John Adams. And no president since has come into office with the gravitas, mandate, and support of George Washington, “First in war, first in peace, and first in the hearts of his countrymen,” and the only president to be elected twice by unanimous vote.

The push and pull between different ideas paved the way for the nation and continues to do so. We all experience life differently, which influences how we think. But that discourse—between true believers that wish for a better world—has built the United States into what it is. The country has faced difficult times and will do so in the future—but as a nation united, it has prevailed.

This book began as a labor of love in February of 2020. As someone with no background in history or historiography (or editing a book, really), it was a constant learning experience. It was made easier through a combination of factors, with others' generosity being the most significant, followed by the availability of the right tool at the right price (free) and the lack of copyright on the inaugural addresses themselves (freedom). I’ve outlined the steps I took to produce this book—some technical, some not. There is no grand plan that all came together—instead, it was a constant, consistent effort for the better part of a year.

If the steps help clear the way for someone else to do what I did, it’s worth it. If you have any questions, my email is open: yuvraj+mfa@librecron.com.

Why This Book?

There was no lightbulb moment that this is what I had to do, and I think those kinds of moments are few and far between. I was interested in history and politics, 2020 was an election year, and I stumbled across a transcription of the inaugural addresses on Project Gutenberg. The idea kicked around in my head for a couple of weeks before I decided to act on it. For a project like this, reading plenty is the single most useful thing you can do. You'll discover works that you want to work on. Penguin Classics, Oxford World Classics, and Norton Critical Editions come with extra matter—introductions, notes, critical essays, etc. They helped define the concept of the book, and I ran with it.

The most important thing is a genuine interest in the topic. It can be anything, not necessarily a collection (like the inaugural addresses are). Critical essays on, say, Dracula, Paradise Lost, Pride & Prejudice, Black Beauty, or anything that catches your interest is just as valid. Or it could be something else—an overall introduction to a book, a close introspection of it, etc. But that genuine interest is important—it’ll keep you going. It isn’t necessarily a requirement, but you’re more likely to get to the end.

Emails & Essays

The most important part of the project was the essays. I was familiar with many of the contributors' works, knew them to be experts, or was referred to them by someone else. Each contributor is an expert on the president they wrote about, or their era—and often, more than one. I knew that I could take care of the technical side, but that’s only one (small) part of the equation. The most important thing is the content.

I reached out to each contributor via email. I never wrote directly into the email app or program. Instead, I did all my writing in a separate text editor (Drafts was my choice) or word processor and then copied the email into my client (Spark, which has some extra features that came in useful). This is for two main reasons:

I prefer to spend as little time in email as possible. This is one of those things you learn about yourself through observation. Continually checking my email and paying attention to the notifications was detrimental to the work at hand, so I sequestered email to different, specific parts of the day. (Though I often fell short of my ideal.)

I didn’t want to send the email until I was completely ready. Doing it in a different editor ensured I wouldn’t just click send. It helped me reduce errors, though some still got through.

Before I had begun emailing, I considered what the overall text required. From the beginning, I knew that what I did not want was something scholarly. The vast majority of readers are not scholars, but as fellow Americans, are concerned with the history, state, and future of the United States. Instead, I was looking for a short description of the situation that surrounded the inaugural and what may have influenced its contents. What might the incoming president have to deal with? What was in store for them down the line? If it was their second term, how was it different from or influenced by the first? We have the benefit of hindsight, after all—while Lincoln didn’t know that his 2nd term would be cut so short, we have an idea of what he intended to do in it. And we know what happened when, instead, Andrew Johnson took the reins.

Software & Hardware

I’m well entrenched in the Apple ecosystem, but that is no requirement. You could do something like this with almost anything; powerful hardware is not a requirement. But friendly tools are a joy to work with, so take that as you will.

I didn’t need much in terms of software or hardware. Everything was created on my MacBook Pro (Retina, Mid 2012) running macOS Catalina. The only other hardware I used was my iPad Air 2 running Apple Books & Kindle to make sure the book looked right; my iPhone 7+ to do the same; and my Kindle Paperwhite (again, to test). On my MBP, I used the Apple Books app and Calibre to do the same.

The most important bit of software was the toolset created by Standard Ebooks, “a volunteer driven, not-for-profit project that produces new editions of public domain ebooks that are lovingly formatted, open source, and free.” The toolset is available on GitHub and is free to use. It requires some bit of technical knowledge, but nothing too complicated. A comprehensive step-by-step guide is available, and you can get started by producing an ebook with them. However, the toolset is geared towards working on existing books found on Project Gutenberg—not towards writing new ones. For the latter, you may want to explore different software such as Vellum, which lets you create beautiful books (at a price—$199 for ebooks, $249 for ebooks + paperbacks). I used Vellum once to test it out and it’s nice—but my experience ended at the free trial. If you want to write full works from scratch, Scrivener is a joy to use, as is Ulysses. However, a tool only ever makes the writing enjoyable—it cannot make your writing better. That requires practice and lots of it. Virtually any text editor will do if you want to write. Just be sure it can output to .docx if you need to submit a manuscript; that wasn’t the case here, as the Standard Ebooks toolset just builds the needed ebook files.

Towards the end, as I added the endnotes, I knew that I would have to write the same thing over and over again. This is the kind of thing that is ripe to be automated. One thing to note when it comes to automation: it is often not a good idea to try and preemptively automate tasks. Rather, you will find that your conception of the task and the reality of it are enough at odds to make your automation fall short. It is better to consider the task and then automate it if possible. To enter an endnote using the Standard Ebooks toolset, I would need to write the string <a href="endnotes.xhtml#note-#" id="noteref-#" epub:type="noteref">#</a>, where # is an endnote number. This is the sort of thing that you can easily write wrong. I used another bit of software, Keyboard Maestro, to instead write it for me. I wrote a short snippet called ;senote (it could be anything; I chose that because it was easy to remember) so that whenever I invoked it, I would be prompted for a number (which would be equal to the endnote number in this case). The number would then be automatically inserted in place of # with the rest of the string. This cut down significantly on how much I needed to write and made typos less likely to occur.

The words you’re reading now were written in GNU Emacs, “an extensible, customizable, free/libre text editor.” Specifically, it was written in the markdown-mode major mode and olivetti-mode minor mode, which made it appealing to my eyes. Emacs is available on Windows, macOS, and probably all Linux distributions. There is a learning curve associated with the editor. I’m not a power user, but I do enjoy using it. Simpler options exist - Microsoft Word (the standard for manuscript writing), Apple Pages, Scrivener, Ulysses, and more. If I had a thought come to me and I was away from my laptop, I would use Drafts on iOS to capture it and transfer it to Emacs, to the necessary document, when I had the time. Emails were the only thing I kept in Drafts and, when done, deleted.

I preferred to use Emacs because it got out of the way and let me focus on my writing. All I needed (and wanted) was a blank slate, and it excels at providing that. Each bit of writing required multiple passes and rounds of editing.

It ought to be noted that the tool is always ancillary to the writing. While the right tool can make a job easier, more than one tool can accomplish a particular task. Most any text editor will do, though if you plan to work with an editor, make sure that you can output to Microsoft Word. While there are workarounds, simplicity is often underrated. Just because something is hard doesn’t mean it’s good, and the simplest route is not only the path of least resistance but of the least errors. Use what you enjoy and what will get you to the finish line with the least amount of hurdles. That is often the right tool.

What’s Next?

I anticipate I’ll continue to work on books like this, though the next few will be shorter. I’m interested to see far we can take ebooks as a medium, as they offer obvious advantages over traditional books. I intend to update this book every time a presidential term ends, but it might evolve in other ways as well.

Acknowledgments

This book would have been impossible without the kindness, generosity, and grace of others. I will remain indebted to each scholar & historian that devoted the time necessary to contribute an essay. They are listed, along with a little more information, in the most reasonable manner I could think of—by order of appearance.

Stephen H. Browne is a rhetorical critic and professor in the Department of Communication Arts & Sciences at Penn State. He earned his BS at the University of Oregon in 1979, his MA at Colorado State University in 1982, and his PhD at the University of Wisconsin-Madison in 1987. Among the many books he has written, three are about United States presidents: The First Inauguration: George Washington and the Invention of the Republic, The Ides of War: George Washington and the Newburgh Crisis, and Jefferson’s Call for Nationhood: The First Inaugural Address.

Kevin Butterfield is the Executive Director of the Fred W. Smith National Library for the Study of George Washington at Mt. Vernon, the historic home of George Washington. Before that, Dr. Butterfield was the Director of the Institute for the American Constitutional Heritage and Constitutional Studies Program at the University of Oklahoma and the Wick Cary Professor and Associate Professor of Classics and Letters. Dr. Butterfield earned his BA in History from the University of Missouri, his MA in History from the College of William and Mary, and his PhD in History from Washington University in St. Louis. In 2015, he published The Making of Tocqueville’s America: Law and Association in the Early United States, an analysis of the associations among the people of the early United States.

Dr. R. M. Barlow is a Research Associate for The Adams Papers at the Massachusetts Historical Society. A specialist in early American diplomatic and military history, she earned her HBA in History at Lakehead University, her MA in Greek and Roman studies at the University of Calgary, and her MA and PhD in History from the University of Virginia.

Peter S. Onuf is Professor Emeritus at the University of Virginia, where he held the Thomas Jefferson Memorial Foundation Professorship until his retirement. He earned his AB and PhD from Johns Hopkins. A noted Thomas Jefferson scholar, Dr. Onuf has authored several books about the third president, including “Most Blessed of the Patriarchs”: Thomas Jefferson and the Empire of the Imagination, a New York Times Bestseller co-authored with Annette Gordon-Reed, The Mind of Thomas Jefferson, Jefferson’s Empire: The Language of American Nationhood, and Jeffersonian America co-authored with Leonard Sadosky.

Annette Gordon-Reed is the Carl M. Loeb University Professor of History at Harvard Law School. She earned her AB from Dartmouth and her JD from Harvard Law School. A noted legal scholar and historian, Professor Gordon-Reed is credited with changing the scholarship of Thomas Jefferson regarding his relationship with his slave, Sally Hemings. Her first book, Thomas Jefferson and Sally Hemings: An American Controversy, helped shed more light on this part of the third president’s life, and her 2008 book The Hemingses of Monticello won 16 awards, including the 2008 National Book Prize and 2009 Pulitzer Prize in History. In 2011, she published Andrew Johnson for The American Presidents Series, a short biography of the 17th president. In 2010, Gordon-Reed was conferred the National Humanities Medal by President Barack Obama and was awarded the MacArthur Fellowship. In 2019, she was elected a member of the American Philosophical Society.

Stuart Leibiger is professor and chair of the History Department at La Salle University. He received his BA from the University of Virginia and his MA and PhD from the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill. His book, Founding Friendship: George Washington, James Madison and the Creation of the American Republic, was published by the University of Virginia Press in 1999. He has written numerous articles on the Founders for newspapers and historical magazines, journals, and encyclopedias, and has been a historical consultant for television documentaries and museums. He has worked on the editorial staffs of the Papers of George Washington and the Papers of Thomas Jefferson. In 2015, he won the George Washington Memorial Award, a lifetime achievement award for the study of George Washington given annually by the George Washington Masonic Memorial Association in Alexandria, Virginia. In 2016, he received La Salle University’s Lindback Distinguished Teaching Award.

J. C. A. Stagg is a professor at the University of Virginia and the editor of The Papers of James Madison. He earned his BA and MA at the Univerity of Canterbury and his PhD from Princeton University. A leading authority on James Madison and an expert on the War of 1812, Dr. Stagg has edited and authored more than 20 books and monographs. The Papers of James Madison are published by University of Virginia Press and provide rich and detailed primary-source material by the fourth president. Outside of the papers, Dr. Stagg published The War of 1812: Conflict for a Continent in 2012, Borderlines in Borderlands: James Madison and the Spanish-American Frontier, 1776-1821 in 2009, and Mr. Madison’s War: Politics, Diplomacy, and Warfare in the Early American Republic, 1783-1830 in 1983.

Daniel Preston is the recently retired editor of The Papers of James Monroe at the University of Mary Washington. The project's goal is to publish ten scholarly volumes, the most recent of which is Volume 7, published in 2020. In 2008, Dr. Preston published James Monroe: An Illustrated History, which uses portraits, photographs, and art to help readers understand the fifth president.

Sandra Moats is an Associate Professor in the History Department at the University of Wisconsin–Parkside. She earned her BA and MA from Smith College and her PhD from UCLA. In 2014, she was an Inaugural Research Fellow at George Washington’s Mount Vernon. In 2009, she published Celebrating the Republic: Presidential Ceremony and Popular Sovereignty, from Washington to Monroe, examining how the actions and symbolic gestures of the first five presidents helped invent the political culture of today. Her second book, Navigating Neutrality: George Washington and the American Government in the Turbulent Atlantic, will be published by the University of Virginia Press in 2021.

Dr. C. James Taylor is the former Editor-in-Chief of the Adams Papers at the Massachusetts Historical Society, having joined the project in 2002 after serving as the editor & project director for The Papers of Henry Laurens. He currently edits the John Quincy Adams Digital Diary at the Massachusetts Historical Society.

Harry L. Watson is the Atlanta Distinguished Professor of Southern Culture at the University of North Carlina in Chapel Hill. He earned his AB from Brown University and his PhD from Northwestern University. His research focuses on the period between the Revolution and Civil War, with a particular interest in the antebellum South and Jacksonian America. In 1993, he was a founding editor of Southern Cultures, a peer-reviewed quarterly journal on the history, culture, society, and experience of the American South, and continued as editor until 2009. From 1999-2012, he directed the UNC Center for the Study of the American South. Dr. Watson has written several books, including Building the American Republic, Volume 1: A Narrative History to 1877], Liberty and Power: The Politics of Jacksonian America, and Andrew Jackson vs. Henry Clay: Democracy and Development in Antebellum America.

Thomas Coens is an editor of the Papers of Andrew Jackson and Research Associate Professor of History at the University of Tennessee, Knoxville. He earned his BA in history from Yale and his PhD from Harvard with a dissertation entitled The Formation of the Jackson Party, 1822-1825. Dr. Coens is working on a short history of Andrew Jackson and Indian Removal entitled The Forked Tongue: Andrew Jackson, the 1830 Indian Removal Act, and the Betrayal of Native America.

Michael J. Gerhardt is the Burton Craige Distinguished Professor of Jurisprudence at the University of North Carolina School of Law in Chapel Hill. He is director of the Center on Law and Government at UNC, a Scholar in Residence at the National Constitution Center, and Visiting Professor at the University of Pennsylvania Law School. He earned his BA at Yale, his MSc at the London School of Economics, and his JD from the University of Chicago Law School. He’s the author of seven books, including The Forgotten Presidents: Their Untold Constitutional Legacy, The Federal Impeachment Process: A Constitutional and Historical Analysis, The Power of Precedent, and most recently Lincoln’s Mentors: The Education of a Leader, an exploration of the impact five different men had on the life of Abraham Lincoln during the decade before his presidency.

Daniel Walker Howe is Rhodes Professor of American History Emeritus at Oxford University in England and Professor of History Emeritus at UCLA. He earned his BA in American history and literature at Harvard, his MA from Magdalen College, Oxford, and his PhD in history at the University of California, Berkeley. He taught at Yale from 1966-73, UCLA from 1973-92 (where he chaired the history department), and Oxford from 1992-2002. He was the Harold Vyvyan Harmsworth Professor of American History at Oxford from 1989-1990. In 2008, Dr. Howe won the Pulitzer Prize in History for What Hath God Wrought: The Transformation of America, 1815–1848, the 5th volume in the Oxford History of the United States series. It also won the 2007 American History Book Prize and was a finalist for the 2007 National Book Critics Circle Award for Nonfiction. Other books authored by Dr. Howe include Making the American Self: Jonathan Edwards to Abraham Lincoln and The Political Culture of the American Whigs. In 2001, Dr. Howe served as the president of the Society for Historians of the Early American Republic and is a fellow of the American Academy of Arts and Sciences and the Royal Historical Society.

Christopher J. Leahy is a Professor of History at Keuka College. He earned his BA from Washington and Jefferson College, his MA from Virginia Polytechnic Institute & State University, and his PhD from Louisiana State University Baton Rouge. In 2020, Dr. Leahy published President without a Party: The Life of John Tyler, the most comprehensive biography of Tyler in more than half a century and the first academic study in 80 years.

Walter R. Borneman is an American historian and lawyer. He earned his BA and MA from Western State College of Colorado and his JD from the University of Denver. He is the author of several books, including Polk: The Man Who Transformed the Presidency and America, 1812: The War The Forged a Nation, The French and Indian War: Deciding the Fate of North America, and most recently Brothers Down: Pearl Harbor and the Fate of the Many Brothers Aboard the USS Arizona. He’s won awards from the Society of Colonial Wars in the State of New York, the Tennessee Library Association and Historical Commission, the Colorado Humanities Program, and the Samuel Eliot Morison Award for Naval Literature for The Admirals: Nimitz, Halsey, Leahy, and King–The Five-Star Admirals Who Won the War at Sea.

Michael F. Holt is Langbourne M. Williams Professor of American History, Emeritus at the University of Virginia. He earned his BA from Princeton and his PhD from Johns Hopkins. He is the author of several books, including Franklin Pierce for the American Presidents Series, The Fate of Their Country: Politicians, Slavery Extension, and the Coming of the Civil War, and The Rise and Fall of the American Whig Party: Jacksonian Politics and the Onset of the Civil War. He was the Pitt Professor of American History and Institutions, Cambridge University from 1993-94, a Fellow of the National Humanities Center for 1987-88, and won a National Endowment for the Humanities Senior Fellowship for 1976-77.

Claude Welch is a SUNY Distinguished Service Professor and retired professor of the Department of Political Science at the University at Buffalo. He earned his BA at Harvard University and his PhD at Oxford University.

Peter A. Wallner is a retired professor of history at Franklin Pierce College. He earned his BA from Waynesburg University and MA and PhD in U.S. History from The Pennsylvania State University. Dr. Wallner wrote a two-volume history of Franklin Pierce: Franklin Pierce: New Hampshire’s Favorite Son covers Pierce’s life up until the night of his inauguration, and Franklin Pierce: Martyr for the Union; the duo comprises the first major reassessment of Pierce’s life, presidency, and legacy in 70 years.

Jean H. Baker is an American historian and Professor Emerita of History at Goucher College. She earned her BA at Goucher College and her MA and PhD at Johns Hopkins. Dr. Baker is a member of the American Council of Learned Societies, the Organization of American Historians, the American Historical Association, and the Berkshire Conference of Women Historians. In 1982, she was a National Endowment for the Humanities fellow. She is the author of several books, including Mary Todd Lincoln: A Biography, James Buchanan for the American President’s Series, Sisters: The Lives of America’s Suffragists, Margaret Sanger: A Life of Passion, and most recently, Building America: The Life of Benjamin Henry Latrobe.

David S. Reynolds is a Distinguished Professor of English at The Graduate Center at the City University of New York. He earned his BA from Amherst College and his PhD at the University of California, Berkeley. Before teaching at CUNY GC, Dr. Reynolds taught at Northwestern University, Barnard College, Rutgers University–Camden, NYU, Baruch College, and the New Sorbonne University. He’s the author of several books, including Abe: Abraham Lincoln in His Times, Mightier than the Sword: Uncle Tom’s Cabin and the Battle for America, Waking Giant: America in the Age of Jackson, John Brown, Abolitionist: The Man Who Killed Slavery, Sparked the Civil War, and Seeded Civil Rights, and Walt Whitman’s America: A Cultural Biography, a winner of the Bancroft Prize, the Ambassador Book Award, and a Finalist for the National Book Critics Circle Award.

Richard Carwardine is a Welsh-born historian and Emeritus Rhodes Professor of American History at Corpus Christi College, Oxford. He focuses on the period of American history between 1776 and the Civil War, with a particular interest in the relationship between politics and religion of the era as well as the life, presidency, and legacy of Abraham Lincoln. He earned his BA and MA from Corpus Christi College and his PhD from The Queen’s College, Oxford. From 2010–2016, he served as President of Corpus Christi College, Oxford. Dr. Carwardine is the author of Lincoln: A Life of Purpose and Power, winner of the Lincoln Prize, The Global Lincoln, and Evangelicals and Politics in Antebellum America.

Michael Les Benedict is an American historian and Emeritus Professor of History at the Ohio State University. He earned his BA and MA from the University of Illinois and his PhD from Rice University. He served as Parliamentarian of the American Historical Association from 1988–2017 and is a past President of the Society for Historians of the Gilded Age and Progressive Era. He has been a visiting scholar at OSU Moritz College of Law and the University of Texas Law School. He’s written several books, including The Impeachment and Trial of Andrew Johnson and The Blessings of Liberty, and more than 50 articles and essays in history, law and political science journals and in edited volumes of essays on historical subjects.

Emerita Professor Joan Waugh of the UCLA History Department researches and writes about nineteenth-century America, specializing in the Civil War, Reconstruction, and Gilded Age eras. Waugh has published numerous essays and books on Civil War topics, both single-authored and edited, including The American War: A History of the Civil War Era, (Flip Learning, 2015; 2nd edition, 2019), co-written with Gary W. Gallagher, and her prize-winning U. S. Grant: American Hero, American Myth, (University of North Carolina Press, 2009). The recipient of Huntington Library, NEH and Gilder-Lehrman fellowships, Professor Waugh is currently Co-President of the Society of Civil War Historians.

John F. Marszalek is an American historian and is the executive director of the Ulysses S. Grant Association’s Grant Presidential Library at Mississippi State University. He retired in 2002 as a Giles Distinguished Professor Emeritus. He has authored or edited 13 books and more than 250 articles & book reviews. Sherman: A Soldier's Passion for Order was a finalist for the Lincoln Prize, while Assault at West Point, the Court Martial of Johnson Whittaker was made into a film on Showtime. He serves on the board of advisors of the Lincoln Forum, the Lincoln Prize, the national Lincoln Bicentennial Commission, and the Monitor Museum.

Dustin McLochlin is the Curator at the Rutherford B. Hayes Presidential Library and Museum and Instructor at Bowling Green State University. He earned his BA at Indiana University Kokomo and his MA & PhD from Bowling Green State University.

Charles Calhoun is Professor Emeritus of History at East Carolina University. He earned his BA from Yale University and his PhD from Columbia University. He has authored six books and edited four, including The Presidency of Ulysses S. Grant, Benjamin Harrison for the American Presidents Series, and From Bloody Shirt to Full Dinner Pail: The Transformation of Politics and Governance in the Gilded Age. Dr. Calhoun also served as president for the Society for Historians of the Gilded Age and Progressive Era.

Walter Nugent is the Andrew V. Tackes Professor of History emeritus at the University of Notre Dame, where he taught from 1984 until 2000. Before that, he taught at Kansas State University (1961-63) and Indiana University (1963-1984), where he was Associate Dean of the College of Arts & Sciences (1967-71) and in the central administration (1971-76), director of the university’s overseas study programs (1967-76), and chair of the history department (1974-77). He earned his AB in history from St. Benedict’s College (Kansas) in 1954, the MA in Modern European from Georgetown University in 1956, and the PhD in American history at the University of Chicago in 1961. He’s written thirteen books as sole author and co-authored or been series co-editor on over a dozen others, notably (with Malcolm Rohrbaugh) the Trans-Appalachian West series of Indiana University Press. He has also published some two-hundred journal articles and book reviews. Among his books are The Tolerant Populists, Second Edition: Kansas Populism and Nativism, Money and American Society 1865-1880, Structures of American Social History, Crossings: The Great Transatlantic Migrations 1870-1914, Into the West: The Story of Its People, Habits of Empire: A History of American Expansion, Progressivism: A Very Short Introduction, and Color Coded: Party Politics in the American West 1950-2016. He has been a Guggenheim fellow, twice a long-term fellow at the Huntington Library, twice a Fulbright senior lecturer (Jerusalem 1978-79, Dublin 1991-92), and directed NEH summer seminars for college teachers in 1979, 1984, and 1986. He has been president of the Indiana Association of Historians, the Society for Historians of the Gilded Age and Progressive Era, and the Western History Association.

Mark W. Summers is the Thomas D. Clark Professor of History at the University of Kentucky. He earned his PhD from the University of California, Berkeley. He’s written several books, including A Dangerous Stir: Fear, Paranoia, and the Making of Reconstruction, Rum, Romanism, and Rebellion: The Making of a President, 1884, and The Press Gang: Newspapers and Politics, 1865-1878.

Allan B. Spetter is Professor Emeritus of History at Wright State University, where he also chaired the history department. He earned his PhD from Rutgers in 1967. He is the co-author of The Presidency of Benjamin Harrison with Homer E. Socolofsky. The book serves as a study of a president that, like the other Gilded Age presidents, is often forgotten.

Matthew Algeo is an award-winning journalist and author. He holds a degree in Folklore from the University of Pennsylvania. He has written six books, including The President Is a Sick Man, Harry Truman’s Excellent Adventure, All This Marvelous Potential, and Abe & Fido.

Christopher Capozzola is a Professor of History at MIT. He earned his AB from Harvard College and his PhD from Columbia University. He is the author of two books: Bound by War: How the United States and the Philippines Built America’s First Pacific Century and Uncle Sam Wants You: World War I and the Making of the Modern American Citizen, which won the Lois P. Rudnick Book Prize of the New England American Studies Association. In 2018, he was awarded the MacVicar Faculty Fellowship for Undergraduate Teaching at MIT and has been a Distinguished Lecturer of the Organization of American Historians since 2011.

Christopher McKnight Nichols is an Associate Professor of History at Oregon State University and Director of the Oregon State University Center for the Humanities. Dr. Nichols is a scholar of the intellectual history of the US’s role in the world, with a focus on isolationism, internationalism, and globalization. Nichols is also an expert on US intellectual, cultural, and political history with an emphasis on the Gilded Age & Progressive Era through the present. He’s the author & editor of several books, including Promise and Peril, Prophesies of Godlessness (co-edited, co-authored with Charles Matthews), The Oxford Encyclopedia of American Military and Diplomatic History (co-edited with David Milne and Timothy Lynch), The Wiley Blackwell Companion to the Gilded Age and Progressive Era (co-edited with Nancy Unger), and the upcoming Rethinking American Grand Strategy (co-edited with Elizabeth Borgwardt and Andrew Preston). He has been elected a permanent member of the Council on Foreign Relations, is on the Board of Trustees of the Oregon Historical Society, and was awarded the Andrew Carnegie Fellowship in 2016.

Jean M. Yarbrough is the Gary M. Pendy, Sr. Professor of Social Sciences at Bowdoin College. She’s received two fellowships from the National Endowment for the Humanities—for 1983–84, when she was named a Bicentennial Fellow, and again for 2005–06, for the “We The People” initiative. She earned her BA from Cedar Crest College and her MA & PhD from The New School. She’s written and edited several books about Thomas Jefferson & Theodore Roosevelt, including Theodore Roosevelt and the American Political Tradition, The Essential Jefferson, and American Virtues: Thomas Jefferson on the Character of a Free People.

Jonathan Lurie is Professor Emeritus of History at Rutgers University. He earned his AB and MA from Harvard and his PhD from the University of Wisconsin, Madison. In 2005, Dr. Lurie was Fulbright Lecturer at Uppsala University Law School in Sweden and a Visiting Professor of Law at West Point in 1994–1995. Dr. Lurie is the author of William Howard Taft: The Travails of a Progressive Conservative, an assessment of Taft as a Progressive-Conservative, and The Chief Justiceship of William Howard Taft, a look at his distinguished role as the only president also to serve on the Supreme Court.

Robert Enholm is the former Executive Director of the Woodrow Wilson House and Global Fellow at the Wilson Center, a think tank that focuses on bridging the divide between policy and ideas. He earned his BA from the University of California, Davis and his JD from the University of California, Berkeley. Before being a director at the Woodrow Wilson House, he served at the United Nations in New York in the Office for the Coordination of Humanitarian Affairs as Chief of the Central Emergency Response Fund Secretariat, where he helped establish a $500 million international humanitarian relief fund.

John Milton Cooper is an American historian and Professor Emeritus of History at the University of Wisconsin, Madison. He earned his BA from Princeton and his MA & PhD from Columbia University. Dr. Coopper taught at the University of Wisconsin, Madison for almost 40 years, where he held two endowed professorships. He was awarded the Guggenheim Fellowship for 1979–1980 and the Fulbright Professorship in United States history at Moscow State University for 1987. His 2009 biography Woodrow Wilson: A Biography was a finalist for the 2010 Pulitzer Prize in Biography. Dr. Cooper has written widely on Wilson and his era, including Breaking the Heart of the World: Woodrow Wilson and the Fight for the League of Nations, and Pivotal Decades: The United States, 1900-1920. For more than twenty years, he served on the Editorial Advisory Committee to the Papers of Woodrow Wilson, edited by Arthur S. Link.

James Robenalt is an American lawyer and author. He earned his BA from Miami University and his JD from Ohio State University College of Law. With John W. Dean, he created The Watergate CLE, a continuing legal education program. His books include Ballots and Bullets: Black Power Politics and Urban Guerrilla Warfare in 1968 Cleveland, The Harding Affair: Love and Espionage during the Great War, and January 1973: Watergate, Roe v. Wade, Vietnam, and the Month That Changed America Forever.

Amity Shlaes is an American author and columnist and currently serves as the chair of the board of trustees at the Calvin Coolidge Presidential Foundation. She earned her BA in English from Yale. She’s the author of several books, including Coolidge, The Forgotten Man: A New History of the Great Depression, The Greedy Hand: How Taxes Drive Americans Crazy and What to Do About It, and Great Society: A New History.

Kendrick A. Clements is Professor Emeritus of History at the University of South Carolina. He earned his BA from Williams College and his MA & PhD from the University of California, Berkeley. In addition to several articles, he’s published seven books, including Hoover, Conservation, and Consumerism: Engineering the Good Life, The Life of Herbert Hoover: Imperfect Visionary, 1918–1928, and The Presidency of Woodrow Wilson.

Cynthia M. Koch is Historian in Residence and Director of History Programing for the Franklin Delano Roosevelt Foundation at Adams House, Harvard College. She was Director of the Franklin D. Roosevelt Presidential Library and Museum in Hyde Park from 1999–2011, after which she served as Senior Advisor to the Office of Presidential Libraries at the National Archives in Washington, DC. Dr. Koch earned her BA in History from Penn State University and her MA & PhD in American Civilization from the University of Pennsylvania.

David M. Kennedy is the Donald J. McLachlan Professor of History Emeritus at Stanford University. He is also the current editor of The Oxford History of the United States, an ongoing multi-volume history of the United States published by Oxford University Press. He earned his BA in history from Stanford and his MA & PhD in American Studies from Yale. Dr. Kennedy was the Harold Vyvyan Harmsworth Professor of American History at Oxford University in 1995–1996 and is a fellow of the American Academy of Arts and Sciences and the American Philosophical Society. He’s authored several books, including Freedom from Fear: The American People in Depression and War, 1929-1945, the 9th volume in the Oxford History of the United States and a recipient of the 2000 Pulitzer Prize in History, the 2000 Francis Parkman Prize, the Commonwealth Club of California’s Gold Medal for Literature, and the 2000 Ambassador Book Award, Over Here: The First World War and American Society, a 1981 Pulitzer Prize finalist, and Birth Control in America, a winner of the 1970 John Gilmary Shea Prize and the 1971 Bancroft Prize.

Michael Kazin is a professor of history at Georgetown University and the editor emeritus of Dissent magazine. He earned his BA from Harvard, his MA from Portland State University, and his PhD from Stanford. In 2020, he was elected to the American Academy of Arts and Sciences. He has won fellowships from the Guggenheim Foundation and the National Endowment for the Humanities and has been a Fulbright scholar in the Netherlands and Japan. Dr. Kazin is the author of several books, including A Godly Hero: The Life of William Jennings Bryan, The Populist Persuasion: An American History, War Against War: The American Fight for Peace, 1914-1918, and American Dreamers: How the Left Changed a Nation. His seventh book, a history of the Democratic Party, will be published next year.

David B. Woolner is Senior Fellow and Resident Historian of the Roosevelt Institute, Professor of History at Marist College, and Senior Fellow of the Center for Civic Engagement at Bard College. He earned his BA in English Literature and History from the University of Minnesota, his MA in History from McGill University, and his PhD in International History from McGill University. He has authored or edited numerous works, including The Last 100 Days: FDR at War and at Peace, Progressivism in America: Past, Present, and Future (co-edited with Jack Thompson), FDR’s World: War, Peace, and Legacies (co-edited with Warren Kimball and David Reynolds) and FDR and the Environment (co-edited with Henry Henderson).

Andrew Busch is the Crown Professor of Government and George R. Roberts Fellow at Claremont McKenna College, where he also serves as the Director of the Rose Institute of State and Local Government. He earned his BA from the University of Colorado-Boulder and his MA & PhD at the University of Virginia. Dr. Busch has authored or co-authored more than 15 books on American politics, including The Rules and Politics of American Primaries, Defying the Odds: The 2016 Elections and American Politics, Reagan’s Victory: The Presidential Election of 1980 and the Rise of the Right, and Truman’s Triumphs: The 1948 Election and the Making of Postwar America. In 2007, he was awarded a Fulbright fellowship to teach American politics at the Diplomatic Academy of Ukraine. He served as the Ann and Herbert Vaughan Fellow in the James Madison Program in American Ideals and Institutions at Princeton University from 2009–2010.

Michael J. Birkner is an American historian and professor of history at Gettysburg College. His focus is on 19th- and 20th-century America and is known for his work on Dwight D. Eisenhower. He earned his BA from Gettysburg College and his MA & PhD from the University of Virginia. Dr. Birkner has authored several books, including The Governors of New Jersey: Biographical Essays and Encounters With Eisenhower, and has co-edited three volumes on James Buchanan, the latest of which is The Worlds of James Buchanan and Thaddeus Stevens: Place, Personality, and Politics in the Civil War Era.

Louis Galambos is an American historian and Research Professor at Johns Hopkins University, where he is also the editor of the Papers of Dwight D. Eisenhower, a 21 volume, 14,000-page collection. He earned his BA in history from Indiana University and his MA & PhD from Yale. From 1975–78, he was the co-editor of the Journal of Economic History. In addition to the volumes of the Papers, Dr. Galambos is the author of Eisenhower: Becoming the Leader of the Free World and The Creative Society—and the Price Americans Paid for It.

Barbara Ann Perry is the Gerald L. Baliles Professor and Director of Presidential Studies at the University of Virginia’s Miller Center, a scholar of the American presidency and Supreme Court, and a biographer of the Kennedys. She co-chairs the Presidential Oral History program, a public service project meant to preserve the thoughts and recollections of officials who worked in past presidencies. She earned her BA in Political Science from the University of Louisville, her MA in PPE from Hertford College, Oxford, and her PhD in American history from the University of Virginia. She is the author of several books, including Jacqueline Kennedy: First Lady of the New Frontier, Rose Kennedy: The Life and Times of a Political Matriarch, 41: Inside the Presidency of George H. W. Bush (edited with Michael Nelson), 42: Inside the Presidency of Bill Clinton (edited with Michael Nelson & Russell Riley), and Edward M. Kennedy: An Oral History.

Mark K. Updegrove is the president and CEO of the LBJ Foundation and serves as Presidential Historian for ABC News. From 2009 to 2017, he was the director of the LBJ Presidential Library where he hosted the 2014 Civil Rights Summit, which included Barack Obama, George W. Bush, Bill Clinton, and Jimmy Carter. Updegrove is the author of four books on the presidency including The Last Republicans: Inside the Extraordinary Relationship Between George H.W. Bush and George W. Bush and Indomitable Will: LBJ in the Presidency. He has written for The New York Times, Politico, The Daily Beast, The Hill, and Time Magazine, and has appeared regularly on CNN and MSNBC. He has conducted exclusive interviews with six U.S. Presidents.

Ken Hughes is an American historian and expert on secret presidential recordings. He’s spent two decades scouring the Secret White House Tapes and shedding light on what they reveal. He earned his BS at Cornell University. He’s the author of two books, Chasing Shadows: The Nixon Tapes, the Chennault Affair, and the Origins of Watergate and Fatal Politics: The Nixon Tapes, the Vietnam War, and the Casualties of Reelection, with a third, regarding President Kennedy's role in the coup that overthrew South Vietnamese President Ngo Dinh Diem and led to his assassination, entitled Mortal Consequences on the way.

Thomas A. Schwartz is an American historian and Distinguished Professor of History at Vanderbilt University. He earned his AB in History from Columbia, his MA in History from Oxford, and his AM and PhD in History from Harvard. He is a past president of the Society of Historians of American Foreign Relations. He is the author of several books, including Henry Kissinger and American Power: A Political Biography, America’s Germany, and Lyndon Johnson and Europe: In the Shadow of Vietnam.

John Robert Greene is an American historian and Paul J. Schupf Professor of History at Cazenovia College. He earned his BA and MA in History from St. Bonaventure University and his PhD from Syracuse University’s Maxwell School of Citizenship and Public Affairs. An expert on the American presidency, his works include I Like Ike: The Presidential Election of 1952, The Presidency of George H. W. Bush, Betty Ford: Candor and Courage in the White House, and The Presidency of Gerald R. Ford.

Mark Atwood Lawrence is the director of the LBJ Presidential Library. Before that, he was Associate Professor of History, Distinguished Fellow at the Robert S. Strauss Center for International Security and Law, and Director of Graduate Studies at the Clements Center for National Security at The University of Texas at Austin. He earned his BA from Stanford and his PhD from Yale, where he was also a history lecturer. He has published several books, including The Vietnam War: A Concise International History, The Vietnam War: An International History in Documents, and Assuming the Burden: Europe and the American Commitment to War in Vietnam.

Gil Troy is an American presidential historian and Professor of History at McGill University. He earned his BA, MA, and PhD from Harvard University. He helped found the Engaging Israel Program at the Shalom Hartman Institute, which helps improve the discourse surrounding Israel. He’s the author of several books, including The Age of Clinton: America in the 1990s, The Reagan Revolution: A Very Short Introduction, Morning in America, and Leading from the Center.

Iwan Morgan is Emeritus Professor of US Studies at the Institute of the Americas, University College London. He earned his BA in History from the University of Wales, Aberystwyth, and his PhD in International History from the London School of Economics. His books include The Age of Deficits: Presidents and Unbalanced Budgets from Jimmy Carter to George W. Bush, Reagan: American Icon, and Nixon. He’s currently working on a book about Franklin D. Roosevelt, FDR: Transformational President in Depression and War.

Mary Kate Cary is a former speechwriter for President George H. W. Bush, helping write more than 100 addresses, and an executive producer for 41on41, a documentary about the president. In addition to being a speechwriter and documentarian, she teaches political speechwriting as an adjunct professor in the Politics Department at the University of Virginia and is a senior fellow at UVA’s Miller Center. She earned her BA in International Relations from the University of Virginia.

Steven M. Gillon is Scholar-in-Residence at The History Channel and a professor of history at The University of Oklahoma. He earned his BA in History from Widener University and his AM & PhD in American Civilization from Brown. He taught at Yale for nine years and then as University Lecturer in Modern History at Oxford University. He has authored or edited several books, including The Pact: Bill Clinton, Newt Gingrich, and the Rivalry that Defined a Generation, Separate and Unequal: The Kerner Commission and the Unraveling of American Liberalism, and America’s Reluctant Prince: The Life of John F. Kennedy Jr.

Russell Riley is co-chair of the Miller Center’s Presidential Oral History Program and is the White Burkett Miller Center Professor of Ethics and Institutions. A leading authority on elite oral history interviewing and the contemporary presidency, Dr. Riley has logged more than 1,500 hours of confidential interviews with senior members of the White House staff, cabinet officers, and foreign leaders since the Carter administration. He earned his BA from Auburn University and his PhD from the University of Virginia. He’s authored or edited six books, including Inside the Clinton White House, Bridging the Constitutional Divide, and The President’s Words: Speeches and Speechwriting in the Modern White House (co-edited with Michael Nelson).

James Mann is an American journalist & author and is a scholar-in-residence at Johns Hopkins. He wrote for the Los Angeles Times for more than 20 years and had stints earlier at The Washington Post and the The Baltimore Sun. He’s the author of several books, including Rise of the Vulcans: The History of Bush’s War Cabinet, George W. Bush for the American Presidents Series, The Obamians: The Struggle Inside the White House to Redefine American Power, About Face: A History of America’s Curious Relationship With China and The Great Rift: Dick Cheney, Colin Powell, and the Broken Friendship That Defined an Era.

Mark J. Rozell is the Founding Dean of the Schar School of Policy and Government at George Mason University, where he also holds the Ruth D. & John T. Hazel chair in public policy. He earned his BA in Political Science from Eisenhower College of Rochester Institute of Technology, his MA in Public Administration from the University of Virginia, and his PhD in Politics from the University of Virginia. He’s the author of nine books and the editor of 20 more, some of which include Federalism: A Very Short Introduction (with Clyde Wilcox), The South and the Transformation of U.S. Politics (with Charles S. Bullock, III, Susan A. MacManus, and Jeremy D. Mayer), and Executive Privilege: Presidential Power, Secrecy, and Accountability.

Tracy Denean Sharpley-Whiting is the Gertrude Conaway Vanderbilt Distinguished Professor of French in the Department of French and Italian at the Vanderbilt University College of Arts and Science, as well as the Chair of African American and Diaspora Studies. She earned her BA in French Literature and African American Studies at the University of Rochester and her PhD in French Studies from Brown University. She has authored several books, including Bricktop’s Paris: African American Women in Paris between the Two World Wars, Black France / France Noire: The History and Politics of Blackness, and The Speech: Race and Barack Obama’s ‘A More Perfect Union’.

James T. Kloppenberg is the Charles Warren Professor of American History at Harvard. He earned his AB at Dartmouth and his MA & PhD at Stanford. Dr. Kloppenberg has been awarded fellowships from the Guggenheim, Danforth, and Whiting foundations, the American Council of Learned Societies, and the National Endowment for the Humanities. In 2015, he was elected to the American Academy of Arts and Sciences. He’s the author of four books and the co-editor of two more, including Reading Obama: Dreams, Hope, and the American Political Tradition, The Virtues of Liberalism, and Toward Democracy: The Struggle for Self-Rule in European and American Thought.

Nicholas F. Jacobs is Visiting Assistant Professor of Government at Colby College. He earned his BA in Political Science from the University of Mary Washington and his MA & PhD in Government from the University of Virginia. He has been awarded several fellowships, including the Beeke-Levy Fellowship from the Franklin and Eleanor Roosevelt Institute, the Humane Studies Fellowship from the Institute for Humane Studies, the Arthur M. Schlesinger, Jr. Fellowship from the JFK Library, and the Moody Foundation Research Fellowship from the LBJ Library. His work appears in numerous journals, including Perspectives on Politics, Political Science Quarterly, Publius: The Journal of Federalism, Presidential Studies Quarterly, Political Research Quarterly, Studies in American Political Development, Journal of Policy History, Education and Urban Society, and The Forum.

I also wanted to thank others that helped make this book possible through their recommendations: Sara Martin at the Massachusetts Historical Society, Elizabeth Chew at Montpelier, Jack Rakove at Stanford, Robert Cherny at SFSU, Jeffrey Rosen at the National Constitution Center, and Ira Katznelson at Columbia University.

Thanks also to my family, who has been nothing but supportive as I worked on this book through a pandemic. Especial thanks to my late grandmother and grandfather, Ranjit Kaur and Paramjit Singh; both were teachers and instilled a love of reading in my youth that never left.